Chapter 1 German Indology, Sanskrit and Nazi ideology

K. Gopinath

Abstract

We first discuss Pollock’s work on the question of “German Indology, Sanskrit and Nazi ideology” in his paper “Deep OrientalismOrientalism (passim)? Notes on Sanskrit and Power Beyond the Raj" (1993). We critically examine his thesis on complicity of Sanskrit, through German Indology, for the Nazi genocidegenocide; other claims in the paper (such as German Indologists attributing degeneracy to India) are not addressed here, or briefly touched upon if at all. Using the propaganda modelpropaganda modelpropaganda (passim) of the US media proposed by Herman and ChomskyHerman and Chomsky (1988), we examine whether Pollock’s writings on this subject can best be explained from a propaganda modelpropaganda model. We end the paper with a brief discussion to examine if and how traditional knowledge systems or Indic systemsIndic!systems could have the protection that artistic works in principle enjoy - such as “moral rights”, a form of IPR. This has implications for Indic systems as many of them are in the informal domain and hence are subject to capture, disinformationdisinformation or “digestion”digestion.

Introduction

Sheldon Pollock’s work on the question of “German Indology, Sanskrit and Nazi ideology” is instructive in how certain questions are posed, extraneous elements subtly brought in, and selected evidence then marshalled to deduce or suggest certain desired conclusions. This is in essence how propaganda systems work and in this paper we attempt to show that it is indeed the case with Pollock's selective use of historical materials. I base my analysis on his 1993[1] paper “Deep Orientalism? Notes on Sanskrit and Power Beyond the Raj", starting first by summarising Pollock's main argument (in parts labelled A to E below).

A.
At the outset, Pollock expands the scope of the word “orientalism” very broadly and makes it equivalent to any system of domination or oppression: to wit,

“...orientalism is disclosed as a species of a larger discourse of power that divides the world into ‘betters and lessers’ and thus facilitates the domination (or ‘orientalizationorientalization’ or ‘colonizationcolonization’) of any group”. (Pollock 1993:77)

B.
But then, a good part of the last 5 centuries were mostly ones of European/American domination or oppression of the rest of the world. Cleverly, Pollock takes examples of inequality in Indian society in the past and now makes it also some type of (expanded notion of) “orientalism" because of the inequality that he perceives:

“indigenous discourses of power - the various systematized and totalized constructions of inequality in traditional India - might be viewed as a preform of orientalism”. (Pollock 1993:77)

Hence, there is now continuity between Indian “internal orientalism" and other types of later orientalisms. Furthermore, for Pollock, “Sanskrit knowledge presents itself to us as a major vehicle of the ideological form of social power in traditional India”, with “restriction of access to Sanskrit ‘literacy’ as a principal mode of domination”. Also, “Sanskrit studies, as an indigenous form of knowledge production [is] equally saturated with domination”, opines Pollock. Hence both Sanskrit knowledge as well as Sanskrit studies are implicated as major factors in oppression, which now is recast as internal “orientalism”.
C.
He then argues that German Indology has been the most productive “orientalism" in the past and documents that it transmogrified into an area of study that had many Nazi sympathizers. Unscientifically, Pollock does not consider other disciplines and check whether practitioners in those fields had any such sympathy for Nazis. For example, Martin HeideggerHeidegger, Martin (a celebrated philosopher) and Werner HeisenbergHeisenberg, Werner (a celebrated physicist), to quote just 2 names, have also been suspected to have Nazi sympathies. Indeed, from the 1920’s, there was a “Deutsch Physik”Deutsch Physik movement led by two Nobel laureates (Philippe LenardLenard, Philippe and Johannes StarkStark, Johannes) that rejected the (Jewish) physics of EinsteinEinstein, Albert (relativity theory, the inadmissibility of ether, etc). During WWII many famous German scientists participated in the German atomic bomb project (e.g., Hans Geiger, Walter Gerlach, Otto Hahn, Werner Heisenberg, Carl Friedrich von Weizsäcker). Another example is the discipline of anatomy; Sabine Hildebrandt (2016) discusses (in the “front matter” of the book) the

“anatomists’ involvement in racial hygieneracial!hygiene as the leading science of NS ideology” and that their “complicity with the Nazi state went beyond the merely ideological. They progressed through gradual stages of ethical transgressionethical transgression, turning increasingly to victims of the regime for body procurementbody procurement, as the traditional model of working with bodies of the deceased gave way, in some cases, to a new paradigm of experimentation with the ‘future dead.’ ”

(The involvement of anatomists will be discussed further in connection with the genocidegenocide in NamibiaNamibia and later during WWII.) In disciplines such as anthropology and genetics, racial theories were de rigueur not just in Germany but widespread in Europe and America till the end of WWII.

Furthermore, disputing the centrality or the ‘materiality’ of Indology studies in the German academia, using yearbooks of the latter used by Pollock himself, GrünendahlGrünendahl (2012:192) reports that he

“discovered that within this period [1933-38] two Indological chairs fell vacant, while the overall position of Indology remained as peripheral as it always had been in German academia, contrary to what Pollock would have us believe.”

Without comparative data of Nazi sympathies in other disciplines, Pollock’s thesis on the role of German Indology in the holocaustholocaust!Nazi is a house of cards; so too, his preposterous claim of Sanskrit’s culpability.
D.
The next step for Pollock is to conflate the native meritocratic system (AryanAryan vs non-Aryan) with racism though the word āryaārya was never used in the racial sense in India. It is surprising that even after notions of “Aryan race”Aryan!race have been debunked repeatedly, Pollock resuscitates it; note his almost casual way of posing it below without any supporting evidence with respect to “race”: native forms of oppression were

“creating the idea of race and concurrently legislating racial exclusivity, asserting linguistic hierarchy and claiming superiority for the language of the masters, and securing an order of domination by monopolizing ‘life chances’ such as forms of literacy”. (Pollock 1993:78)

If race is really involved, how does Pollock explain the phenomenon of a saṁnyāsin's “non-caste”hood“non-caste” hood as they can be initially from any varṇavarṇa (see, for example, how BuddhaGautama Buddha phrases this in Aggañña Sutta); no racial system in the world, that I am aware of, would allow such a change. Similarly, DharampalDharampal (1971:preface) reports, while travelling in the late 50’s, that “there was no jati on a yatra” (ie. during long pilgrimagespilgrimage, many normative practices do not obtain). The Indic tradition also has many examples of kṣatriya-skṣatriya (such as ViśvāmitraViśvāmitra) becoming brāhmaṇa-s;brāhmaṇa the Peshwa Baji RaoBaji Rao, Peshwa I could be considered as a recent example in the opposite direction. There was upward mobility too; example can be given of ShivajiShivaji who categorised himself as a Kṣatriya using the flexibility in the system itself. Many jāti-sjāti have created genealogies or declared themselves as sūrya-vaṁśī (“belonging to the Solar Genealogy”) or candra-vaṁśī (“belonging to the Lunar Genealogy”) based on the social reality obtaining. There is enough evidence to argue that the jāti-varṇa system is closer to a somewhat fluid sociological system of differentiation/inequality (that is not too different from other systems elsewhere in premodern times) and not based on biological race.

Interestingly, the native varṇa-jātijāti system was misconstrued into an inflexible “caste" systemcaste!system by the British/Europeans based on their own social regimentation prevailing in Europe/Americas since at least the 15th century with, for example, castas, mestizos, and mulattos in the Americas. Furthermore, the “one-drop” rule“one-drop” rule in US statutes and elsewhere all the way into the beginning of the 20th century made even a “drop” of black or Native American blood made them the inferior race; even Thomas Jefferson’sJefferson, Thomas children through his mixed race concubine were born into slavery, with some of them having to “escape” to become free! There is still an ongoing project in many parts of the West where the varṇavarṇa-jātijāti system is to be declared as equivalent to racism with attendant stringent penalties (eg. attempted discussion/legislation in UK/EU parliaments or UN, or in the academia where Dalits are equated with blacks through the Afro-Dalit project)Afro-Dalit project.

With the racism angle thus brought in without any justification whatsoever, now one could argue that Nazis were only continuing the race discrimination that Indians were doing all along!

In the quote cited above, Pollock also mentions linguistic hierarchylinguistic hierarchy. This is surprising to me at least as many regional languages were in a ‘give and take’ relationship with Sanskrit; for example, almost all the well known poets of Telugu between 10th century and 16th century were also Sanskrit pandits. While prejudiced opinions are to be expected in any subjective enterprise (such as affinity for a language), to elevate them to notions of domination or superiority seem inappropriate. In the last 2 centuries, given the official neglectofficial neglect of Sanskrit and motivated writings of European or American Oriental scholars, such harmful ideas have gained prominence, especially in Tamil Nadu (for example, Dravidian linguistic “separatism”linguistic separatism). One can also use Pollock’s own argument against his own writing - that his use of “high” and convoluted Englishconvoluted!English language in his articles is a source of oppression and domination over others.
E.
Next, because of the resilience of the Sanskrit knowledge systems for more than 2 millennia, there must be, according to Pollock, something in Sanskrit (“deep structure"deep structure of order, domination and oppression?) that makes internal orientalism (see Pollock 2006) where he argues that Sanskrit cosmopolis is oppressive) and the German (Nazi) Indology orientalism variety possible. The Germans studied Sanskrit knowledge systems intensely and hence “infected” themselves with that virus of deep structure, and hence order, domination and oppression were the hallmark of Nazis. In a sense, Sanskrit or its knowledge systems molded the Nazis into murderous machines.

Going through these steps A to E, it is obvious that there are too many leaps of logic, convenient conflating of categories and too many rhetorical devicesrhetorical devices (jalpa/vitaṇḍājalpa/vitaṇḍā) used to, so to say, “pre-form" a conclusion. For example, in the section “For a Critical Indology" in this paper where there is a serious effort to prove some causal connection with Sanskrit and the Nazi holocaustholocaust!Nazi, he writes

1: “Reviewing Indology in the way we have just done, we encounter a field of knowledge whose history and object both have been permeated with power." (Pollock 1993:111)

Yes, in the way it has been presented by Pollock (ie. in isolation with respect to developments elsewhere), the field and the object matter does seem to revel in themes of domination and oppression. But does Pollock also weigh in other fields of knowledge, their histories and their objects? For a start, religious thought that permitted slaving societiesslaving societies in Arabia or of Spain/Portugal/England/US, or the Christian modelsChristian models of understanding that resulted in burning down AlexandriaAlexandria and its libraries, or the IslamicIslamic invasion ones that caused Nalanda'sNalanda libraries to be burnt or BamiyanBamiyan to be destroyedlibraries, destruction of recently, or the European/Machiavellian and racial systems of thinking in the 19th century that finally resulted in the British and other European powerspower!political to burn down the summer palace in BeijingBeijing along with its valuable artefacts in the late 19th century? Their role in creating the ground for later holocausts is not even hinted at. We may well heed the following “gentle" observation, even if not exactly apposite given Pollock’s obvious wide erudition:

ekaṁ śāstram adhīyāno na gacchecchāśtra-nirṇayam

If you know/study only one subject, you cannot go around saying anything authoritatively even in that subject!

Furthermore, continuing to quote from the same paper,

2: “From its colonial origins in Justice Sir William to its consummation in SS Obersturmführer WüstWüst, SS Obersturmführer [“Nazi" Indologist], Sanskrit and Indian studies have contributed directly to consolidating and sustaining programs of domination." (Pollock 1993:111)

Why are the studies consummated with Wüst, hardly known to most? Why not Ingalls or others? Bringing in Wüst is underhanded; it emphasizes the Nazi connection for no reason. The mention of William JonesJones, William makes it clear that German Indology is not entirely the subject of discussion here.

It is also not clear why these studies have contributed to domination; I believe Pollock has vastly overstated this aspect and will be discussed further down.

Also,

3: “In this (noteworthy orthogenesisorthogenesis) these studies have recapitulated the character of their subject, that indigenous discourse of power for which Sanskritpower!Sanskrit as a source of has been one major vehicle and which has shown a notable longevity and resilience." (Pollock 1993:111)

This quote may not be all that clear but what the sentence is likely to be saying, paraphrased, is that the subject of study (Sanskrit or Indology broadly) made its students (German Indologists) into supporters also of oppression/domination (effectively, Nazis or provide legitimacy for Nazis). The latter property is almost axiomatic of Sanskrit given the internal structure of Sanskrit itself (due to “orthogenesisorthogenesis", the property of an inflexible internal structure that manifests itself in any environment). It is not clear why Sanskrit alone of the classical languages is a major vehicle of discourse of powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of. One could argue that LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church), still used in Vatican liturgyVatican!liturgy, could fit the bill. The Roman empireRoman empire after all was a large empire for 6 to 7 centuries with a large war machine; it would not give any quarter to an enemy that would not fall in, a good example being how CarthageCarthage was annihilated to the last “man”. Given that Vatican is widely believed to have cooperated (see below) with Fascismfascism and Nazism, LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) is a far stronger contender, using a similar logic of argumentation, for inducing genocidalgenocide tendencies in Nazis.

Next:

4: “From such factors as the semantic realm of the distinction arya/anaryaanārya and the biogenetic map of inequalitybiogenetic map of inequality (along with less theorized material, from Vedic and epic literature, for instance), it may seem warranted to speak about a “pre-form of racism" in early India (Geissen 1988: 48ff.), especially in a discussion of indigenous “orientalism," since in both its classic colonial and its National Socialist [“Nazi"] form orientalism is inseparable from racism." (Pollock 1993:107)

Pollock cleverly introduces “racism" (biogenetic map of inequalitybiogenetic map of inequality?) here to set the stage for further mental manipulations by equating indigenous “orientalism” with racism; now one can talk about internal orientalism as racism. He then tars most of the early literature (Vedic and epic) as racist without having to give any proof (because “less theorized”). The most obvious racism that has been practised is that between black/white, European/ Native American, Arab/Nubian, European/Asian, European/ Yellow/Chinese/Japanese, etc. But the concept of race is at best extraneous in the larger Indian context as discussed before; what obtained here as many have argued is that of a reasonably fluid varṇavarṇa-jātijāti continuumvarṇa-jāti continuum (Dirks 2001). Note that biogenesis as understood conventionally is that life forms are produced by life forms (contrast with abiogenesis); it is not clear what Pollock exactly has in mind here; I am assuming this is Pollock’s convoluted way of talking about racism, just as with many other examples of such ambiguous uses in the paper.

Note that Pollock also weakens his own case:

5: “From among the complexities of NS analysis of the UrheimatUrheimat question it is worth calling attention to the way the nineteenth-century view expressed by SchlegelSchlegel, Friedrich von was reversed: the original Indo-Europeans were now variously relocated in regions of the Greater German Reich; German thereby became the language of the core (Binnensprache), whereas Sanskrit was transformed into one of its peripheral, “colonial" forms.” (Pollock 1993:92)

If German Indology makes Sanskrit into a peripheral form in the question of UrheimatUrheimat (the original home of the Aryans), an issue that “had always been a scholarly question prompted and driven by the ideological demands of the European polities in which this discourse originated” (1993:92), then it is strange that a peripheral form of “domination and oppression” (the AryanAryan/Sanskrit combine) would now be so central when it comes to holocaustholocaust!Nazi as Pollock has implied. In this connection, it is not clear why Sanskrit should be discussed at such lengths as Pollock has attempted.

What is striking is the almost complete erasure of the “elephant" in the room: British and US role in not seriously attempting to stop the Nazis till 1939 (e.g., Chamberlain’s Munich treatyMunich treaty in 1938; this is also a credible allegation by the Communists of that era) and active collaboration by VaticanVatican with Italian and German fascismfascism. Instead, he spends tens of pages looking at obscure sources from German Indologists who are hoping to use Indian (Sanskrit) materials to show “Indo-Germanic” superiority over other Europeans or provide some cover for Nazism. Or, find one Indian author with certain views (e.g., Bhaṭṭa LakṣmīdharaBhaṭṭa Lakṣmidhara) out of the many and make him the spokesperson for all Indians and even then probably not fairly. For example: “It is in this context that Lakṣmīdhara adduces a foundational principle of the traditional Indian discourse of powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of: ‘Whatever act the arya-s who know the VedasVeda claim to be dharmadharma, is dharmadharma; whatever they reject is said to be adharma.’” (Pollock 1993: 107). First, if Arya is taken to be the traditional meaning of “a noble person” instead of a member of a race that Europeans/Americans made it out to be, it is not clear what the difficulty is. Note also that the plural of Arya is used; hence it could be a “committee” of noble persons (a collegium of eminent judges?) and thus quite reasonable (just as law even now is what judges interpret it to be). Additionally, other formulations of dharmadharma are widely available and more accessible; e.g., Taittirīya UpaniṣadTaittirīya Upaniṣad (Śikṣā Valli, Anuvāka 11) instructs snātaka-s (“graduates”) as follows:

yāny anavadyāni karmāṇi | tāni sevitavyāni | no itarāṇi |
“Those actions that are blameless, follow only those, not any other”.

Compare with the Popperian conception of Science: “Consider hypotheses as provisionally true that cannot be refuted or falsified”

yāny asmākaṁ sucaritāni tāni tvayopāsyāni | no itarāṇi |
“What acts of ours are good, follow those, not any other”.

ye ke cāsmacchreyāṁso brāhmaṇāḥ | teṣāṁ tvayā’’sanena praśvasitavyam |

“Whosoever brāhmaṇa-s are better than ourselves, comfort them by offering a seat `don't so much as breathe aloud”!

Note here the open-ended perspective (for example, the inviting of `better' teachers) rather than the closed perspective (or authoritarian model) that Pollock wants to imply.

Critical Study of the Genesis of Nazi Genocide

If a serious academic were to critically understand the ghastly Nazi phenomenon, many alternative and pertinent explanations would suggest themselves and other than what Pollock wants to suggest such as casually implicating Sanskrit's “deep structure"“deep structure” for a role in genocidegenocide. Two major alternative explanations are as follows:

1. Church and persecution of Jews

First, consider Raul Hilberg'sHilberg, Raul magnum opus (Hilberg 1961) on the destruction of European Jews where he shows with great force that the many canonical lawscanonical laws of the church (he lists at least 22) and what the Nazis promulgated were same or very similar (see also NichollsNicholls, William 1993:204-206). To list only three examples (out of 22), consider:

a: “Jews and ChristiansChristians not permitted to eat together,”

Synod of ElviraSynod of Elvira, 306 CE

Cf. “Jews barred from dining cars,” Transport Minister to Interior Minister,

Dec 30, 1939, Document NGDocument NG-3995.

Or,

b: “Prohibition of intermarriage and of sexual intercourse between Christians and Jews,” Synod of Elvira, 306 CE

Cf. “Law for the Protection of German Blood and Honor,”

Sep 15, 1935 (RGB1 I, 1146).

Or,

c: “Jews not permitted to show themselves in the streets during Passion WeekPassion Week,”

3rd Synod of Orleans, 538 CE

Cf. “Decree authorizing local authorities to bar Jews from the streets on certain days

(i.e., Nazi holidaysNazi!holidays)”

Dec 3, 1933 (RGB1 I, 1676).

Given the extensive and detailed prohibitions on the Jews by the Church, one can easily surmise that deep-seated prejudices became established in the Church as well as internalized by the church-goers during the approximately two millennia, as admitted by no less than a recent Pope (Pope BenedictPope Benedict XVI, once a “Hitler Youth'' himself[2]) “... it cannot be denied that a certain insufficient resistance to this atrocity on the part of ChristiansChristians can be explained by an inherited anti-Judaismanti-Judaism present in the hearts of not a few Christians.”[3] For example, Matthew 23:31-33, says of PhariseesPharisees (“lower class” Jews), “... You snakes, you brood of vipers! How can you escape being sentenced to hell?”

However, for Pollock,

“The myth of AryanAryan!origins burst from the world of dream into that of reality when the process of what I suggest we think of as an internal colonizationcolonization of Europe began to be, so to speak, shastrically codified, within two months of the National Socialists' capturing powerpower!political (April 1933)”. (Pollock 1993: 86)

Where did the “shastrically" notion come from? Why not say it comes from the Synods (ie. synodically) as shown by Hilberg which is more direct historically and attested and not just some casually and casuistically thrown word? The mischief can be understood if one is discussing untouchability with its restrictions on sharing food in India: suppose I use the word “synodically" in such discussions as Jews and ChristiansChristians were also not to share food as per the Synod of Elvira CE 306? My submission is that Pollock's use of “shastrically" is in the same category.

Similarly,

“The whole weight of these early laws rested on the concept “Aryan"Aryan (or rather, somehow significantly, at first on its negation).” (Pollock 1993: 87)

But, what about Hilberg's detailed analysis? Is not non-Aryan here just another name for Judaic only as it is not stressing any aspect of AryanAryan culture but talking about Jews in a coded way only.

There is extensive literature on the subject of Catholic (Vatican)Catholic church, ProtestantProtestant(ism) and Lutheran complicityLutheran complicity and a good summary can be found in an “occasional” paper by EricksenEricksen, Robert P[4]. To quote just one relevant, though longish, passage (2009:13–14):

“Gerhard KittelKittel, Gerhard [a well known German ProtestantProtestant(ism) theologian during the Nazi years] assessed Adolf HitlerHitler!Adolf quite accurately and liked what he saw. That would explain why Kittel’s antisemitismanti-Semitism grew more intemperate between 1933 and 1944 and why he never apologized after 1945, but energetically defended his own harsh attacks upon Jews. He claimed that his antisemitismanti-Semitism had been entirely consistent with his Christian faith and no harsher than the antisemitismanti-Semitism of Jesus or Paul[47]. His only concession was to acknowledge the obvious, that the death camps could not be defended. I think this understanding best explains Kittel but also helps us understand those many other church leaders, pastors, theologians, and lay people who applauded Hitler, who called 1933 a year of rebirth, and, in the words of Paul AlthausAlthaus, Paul, considered Hitler “a gift and miracle from God”Hitler!“gift and miracle from God”[48]. The problem was not that they misunderstood Hitler, but that they so readily reconciled their consciences and their Christian identities to the harshness of the Nazi state.”

“Why? I have not tried to address that question here, but the short answer is this: They were so hurt by World War I and the national humiliation of the Versailles TreatyVersailles Treaty, they were so opposed to the open societyopen society created by democracydemocracy and the Weimar RepublicWeimar Republic, they were so frightened by the economic crises of hyper inflation and then the Great DepressionGreat Depression, and they were so threatened by the sociological changes of the modern world that someone as ideologically aggressive as Adolf HitlerHitler!Adolf seemed an answer to all their problems. He was the candidate of military strength and national pride; the candidate of family values, promising, among other things, to put women back in the home where they belonged; and the candidate whose antisemitismanti-Semitism fit their own preconceptions and concern that Jews did not really belong in an ideal, unified Christian society [49]. Based upon their hopes and dreams, ChristiansChristians and other Germans found it easier to march behind Adolf HitlerHitler!Adolf than we would like to think. An honest assessment of the historical record seems to make that clear. It cannot be the legitimate task of historians to bury, ignore, try to hide or try to ignore that complex reality.”

Tragically, Pollock precisely does that (even worse, shifts the blame) and trivialises the difficult experience of the Germans just after WWI as a mindless adoption of (concocted) racial ideas from a far away land (India) and Indic thought system that had no almost relevance in their lives except in the rarefied and far removed academic world.

Another source of Naziholocaust!Nazi thinking was the worldview of “German Christians”. Quoting from the same link for the Holocaust website (see United States Holocaust Memorial MuseumMemorial Museum), “Historically the German Evangelical ChurchGerman Evangelical Church (comprised of 28 regional churches or LandeskirchenLandeskirchen that included the three major theological traditions that had emerged from the Reformation: Lutheran, Reformed, and United) viewed itself as one of the pillars of German culture and society, with a theologically grounded tradition of loyalty to the state. During the 1920s, a movement emerged within the German Evangelical Church called the Deutsche ChristenDeutsche Christen, or “German Christians.” The “German Christians” embraced many of the nationalistic and racial aspects of Naziholocaust!Nazi ideology. Once the Nazis came to powerpower!political, this group sought the creation of a national “Reich ChurchReich Church” and supported a “nazified” version of ChristianityChristianity, nazified version of.” Martin Luther in the 16th century and other German historical figures were not free from anti-Jewish racismanti-Jewish and it is not surprising that German ChristiansChristians were, if not actively, at least passively involved in the pogromspogroms in Germany.

Yet another source of Naziholocaust!Nazi thinking was the {\sl völkisch}völkisch movement in Germany that “essentially combined nationalism with a sentimental patriotic interest in German folklore and history" (Ross 2011:504). Unfortunately, this descended into anti-Jewishanti-Jewish racism in many instances as Jews were seen as outsiders.

2. European Role in Genocides Just before WWI

Second, another likely explanation comes from the extensive experience of conducting regular genocidesgenocide by Europeans on the hapless natives of many countries in the 18th to early 20th century itself. Benjamin MadleyMadley, Benjamin writes about how expertise in genocidegenocide travelled from German campaigns in South West Africa to Auschwitz and suggests how this experience incubated ideas and methods adopted and developed by the Nazis in Eastern Europe (Madley 2005:429-464):

“The German terms Lebensraum and KonzentrationslagerKonzentrationslager, both widely known because of their use by the Nazis, were not coined by the HitlerHitler!Adolf regime. These terms were minted many years earlier in reference to German South West Africa, now NamibiaNamibia, during the first decade of the twentieth century, when Germans colonized the land and committed genocide against the local HereroHerero and Nama peoplesNama (people). Later use of these borrowed words suggests an important question: did Wilhelmine [German Emperor Kaiser Wilhelm IIKaiser Wilhelm II, 1888-1918] colonizationcolonization and genocide in NamibiaNamibia influence Nazi plans to conquer and settle Eastern Europe, enslave and murder millions of SlavsSlavs and exterminate GypsiesGypsies and JewsJews? This article argues that the German experience in NamibiaNamibia was a crucial precursor to Nazi colonialismcolonialism!Nazi/German and genocide and that personal connections, literature, and public debates served as conduits for communicating colonialist and genocidal ideas and methods from the colony to Germany."

Note that the genocidal campaigns against the Jews were started barely 2 decades later. At this stage, it is interesting to briefly list some additional details that are relevant to understand how the German colonialismGerman colonialism in NamibiaNamibia directly influenced Nazi thinking (most of this information is summarized from the document collection in Bartrop and JacobsBartrop and Jacobs (2015) vol2, p. 997-1110; we do not give detailed references here for brevity). In 1840’s, the Rhenish Missionary Society was established in NamibiaNamibia (the colonial German Southwest Africa). In 1884, Bismarck’s Berlin conference allotted spheres of influence in Africa amongst the colonial powerspower!political; Germany now had the 3rd largest area after Britain/France. During 1885-1904, there was intense competition between Hereros, Namas in Namibia and German outsiders for land/cattle; there were minor battles with multiple realignments amongst the contenders. Just as in US with respect to Native AmericansNative Americans, Germans wilfully broke signed treaties, stole land, and abused natives economically, racially, sexually etc. During the early part of this phase (1885-90), Heinrich GoeringGoering, Heinrich (father of the Nazi leader) was the Imperial Commissioner of South W Africa. In 1904, there was a major HereroHerero rebellion aided by Nama (the latter had realized by this time that Germans were a bigger danger). Gen van Trothavan Trotha, Gen., the Commander in Chief of German colonial forces (who incidentally was earlier part of 8 nation alliance that suppressed the Boxer rebellionBoxer rebellion in China), instituted a systematic policy of exterminationextermination, policy of (murder, dehydration, poisoning wellspoisoning wells); there were also medical experiments on the victims. The Germans also borrowed the concept of concentration camps from the British (from Lord Kitchener'sLord Kitchener camps for Boers and Africans).

The German colonizationcolonization of Namibia had the unfortunate effect of making racism and eugenicseugenics fashionable at the academic, social and political levels in Germany; US was already advanced in this area given that they had to either dispossess the Native Americans, subjugate blacks or provide legitimation for such acts, with as many as 23 US states (such as Indiana, California, Washington) having the earliest compulsory sterilizationsterilization programs in the world legally, inspired by the “scientific” discipline of “eugenics”, from 1907 onwards (See ReillyReilly, P R 1987:153-170)[5]. The direct academic roots of Nazi racism can be said to be through the tutelage of the German professor of medicine, anthropology and eugenics Eugen FischerFischer, Eugen who organized experiments on African victims of Heroro revolt (including on body parts, with organized export of skulls, etc). Due to the widespread sexual exploitation of the Namibians by the Germans, there was widespread alarm in Germany about mixed blood; his eugenics program therefore advocated “improvement of society by preventing birth of inferior races and encouraging birth of superior races”. He authored a book on mixed children of European men and HottentotHottentot (a derogatory term for Namibians) women in German southwest Africa. His recommendations that mixed descendants be not allowed to reproduce were followed and by 1912 interracial marriageinterracial marriage was prohibited throughout the German colonies (note the later Nazi regulations on Jews). Note that California was already much ahead in “thinking” on eugenics by the turn of the 20th century; by 1933, California stateCalifornia state, laws of had subjected more people to forceful sterilization than all other U.S. states combined (the latter number a total of 65,000) (Kevles 1994:18). The forced sterilizationsterilization program later engineered by the Nazis was partly inspired by California’s laws and initially had even support from Rockefeller Foundation!Rockefeller Foundation

Eugen Fischer also wrote an influential book on “principles of heredity” in 1921, the German title being closer to “Foundations of Human Hereditary Teaching and Racial Hygiene”, along with two others (Baur and Lenz). Fischer’s part in the book concentrated on the different racial groups on earth while Lenz’s part on the topic of racial hygiene. The second edition of this book was read by Hitler when he was in prison (1923) and the ideas in this book seem to have formed the core of racial ideas in Mein KampfMein Kampf (published Oct 1924); a search of this book shows complete absence of any Indic thinking other than the use of words AryanAryan or Swastika but with much discussion of racial theories common in Europe in connection with Jews, blacks and HottentotsHottentot (Namibians), including also the widely prevalent European notion that British rule is “beneficial” for India. In 1927, Fischer became the Director of Kaiser Wilhelm Institute of AnthropologyKaiser Wilhelm Institute of Anthropology and in 1933 started teaching racial hygieneracial!hygiene to SS doctors responsible to guard “purity of racerace, purity of”, the same year Adolf HitlerHitler!Adolf appointed him rector of the Frederick William UniversityFrederick William University of Berlin (now Humboldt UniversityHumboldt University). In 1935, he conducted experiments on racially mixed children in Rhine (born of German women and Asian/African soldiers during the Rhineland occupationRhineland occupation) and enforced their sterilizationsterilization. In 1943, his protégé’s student Mengele conducted infamous experiments on Jewish/Roma twins/dwarvesJewish/Roma twins/dwarves. Surprisingly, in 1952, he was appointed Hon. President of Anthropology Society!Anthropology Society (now “denazified”).

In 1985, an UN report declared HereroHerero genocidegenocide the first of the 20th century. With worldwide protests against apartheidapartheid regimes in South Africa and Namibia gathering steam from late 70’s, Namibia became independent in 1990; sensitive scholars in US may have come to know by now what happened in Namibia as there were also US student protests in ‘80s including at Columbia University (where some buildings were blockaded by students in 1985). In 2004, Germany’s ambassador to Namibia apologized for the gruesome genocidegenocide but rejected any possibility of reparations; some medical exhibits (skulls, etc) of the victims were returned though.

One can forcefully argue that a clear racist thought system that was responsible for genocidegenocide and enacted ruthlessly in Namibia a better candidate explanation for the later Nazi genocides of Jews, Gypsies and other “undesirables” than far-fetched ideas that Pollock advances, though it might have had a minor role in the ecosystem of racial ideas prevalent in Germany, Europe or US.

Note that genocides such as in Namibia were not rare either; MadleyMadley, Benjamin discusses 2 other not well known cases (MadleyMadley, Benjamin 2004:167-192) in a summary article. Genocidal campaigns were conducted in Canada, Australia resulting in the native populations totally wiped out (e.g., TasmaniansTasmanians. See “Colonial Genocides”) or reduced to very small populations that were forced out into inhospitable areas. Extremely brutal regimes were common with colonialists from Netherlands and Belgium.

One instructive case is that of the Native American exterminationextermination in US. In American HolocaustAmerican Holocaust, David StannardStannard, David E shows connection between American (“Columbus”) holocaust, Nazi holocaustholocaust!Nazi and also the Church, with the dead estimated in the 100s of millions (Stannard 1993). He writes that “wherever Europeans or white Americans went, the native people were caught between imported plagues and barbarous atrocities, typically resulting in the annihilationannihilation of 95 percent of their populations.” What kind of people, Stannard asks, do such horrendous things to others? His highly “provocative” answer: ChristiansChristians. “Digging deeply into ancient European and Christian attitudes toward sex, race, and war, the cultural ground was well prepared by the end of the Middle Ages for the centuries-long genocidegenocide!colonial campaign that Europeans and their descendants launched–and in places continue to wage–against the New World'sNew World original inhabitants” (of interest to us: also against Indic systemsIndic!systems). Stannard contends that the perpetrators of the American Holocaustholocaust!American drew on the same ideological wellsprings as did the later architects of the Nazi Holocaust.

More recently, MadleyMadley, Benjamin (2016) in his book An American Genocidegenocide!American writes

“Under US rule, CaliforniaCalifornia state, laws of Indians died at an even more astonishing rate. Between 1846 and 1870, California's Native American population plunged from perhaps 150,000 to 30,000. By 1880, census takers recorded just 16,277 California Indians. Diseases, dislocation, and starvation were important causes of these many deaths. However, abduction, de jure and de facto unfree labor, mass deathmass death in forced confinementconfinement, forced on reservations, homicides, battles, and massacres also took thousands of lives and hindered reproduction. ... The organized destruction of California's Indian peoples under US rule was not a closely guarded secret. Mid-nineteenth-century California newspapers frequently addressed, and often encouraged, what we would now call genocidegenocide, as did some state and federal employees. Historians began using these and other sources to address the topic as early as 1890. That year, historian Hubert Howe BancroftBancroft, Hubert Howe summed up the California Indian catastrophe under US rule: “The savages were in the way; the miners and settlers were arrogant and impatient; there were no missionariesmissionaries or others present with even the poor pretense of soul-saving or civilizing. It was one of the last humanhuntshumanhunts of civilization, and the basest and most brutal of them all." In 1935, US Indian Affairs commissioner John CollierCollier, John added, “The world's annals contain few comparable instances of swift depopulation - practically, of racial massacre - at the hands of a conquering race." In 1940, historian John Walton CaugheyCaughey, John Walton titled a chapter of his California history “Liquidating the Indiansliquidating the Indians: “Wars and Massacres." Three years later, Cook wrote the first major study on the topic. He quantified the violent killing of 4,556 California Indians between 1847 and 1865, concluding that, “since the quickest and easiest way to get rid of the Northern CaliforniaCalifornia state, laws of Indian was to kill him off, this procedure was adopted as standard for some years."”

Surprisingly, no obvious entity was held responsible in standard accounts till about 4-5 decades back; least of all the Church or Western powers. Columbus was widely praised as discoverer of the Americas, with resistance to observing Columbus DayColumbus Day formally starting in US only in 1992 in Davis, CA. Also Rajiv MalhotraMalhotra, Rajiv (2009) writes:

“The greatest episodes of ethnic cleansingethnic cleansing and genocidegenocide of Native AmericansNative Americans occurred in the period following independence that was dominated by Thomas JeffersonJefferson, Thomas and Andrew JacksonJackson, Andrew ... Because of the popular demonologydemonology of Native AmericansNative Americans and pseudo-scientific researchpseudo-scientific research to show their innate inferiority, ironically enough, the only defenders remaining were missionaries claiming that although Native Americans were presently savages they could be rescued by converting them to Christianity. Further physical genocidegenocide!physical could be prevented by completing the cultural genocidegenocide!cultural. Sadly, freedom loving Americans explained away their genocidegenocide of Native Americans as the natives’ inability to adapt to civilization:

“As American hopes of creating a policy based on Enlightenment ideas of human equality failed, and as it relentlessly drove the Indians from all areas desired by the whites, Americans transferred their own failure to the Indians and condemned the Indians racially” (HorsmanHorsman, Reginald 1981, p. 207).” (Malhotra 2009:184,195)

The role of the British in genocidal campaigns could be of considerable interest, given that as an “Eastern” speaker of the English language, the principal language of hegemony in India currently, we can be said to feel it acutely that we need to speak an oppressors’s language for economic survival, in contrast to what Pollock says, “Perhaps the western Sanskritist feels this most acutely, given that Sanskrit was the principal discursive instrument of domination in premodern India, ...”. Note that this sentiment of Pollock seems insubstantial or frivolous as he never experienced any oppression as such and his study or interest in Sanskrit can only be said to be voluntary; this may not be true for many “Eastern” English speakers or their immediate ancestors given the very recent history as we briefly discuss below.

The British engineered famines systematically, by levying and mindlessly enforcing unsustainable rates of taxes on land or exporting foodstuffs out even when famines were raging, in India and Ireland (Davis 2001)[6], and fought (along with other European and American powers) with China no less than 3 “opium wars"Chinese!opium wars to be able to drug the hapless Chinese. Mike DavisDavis, Mike (2001) concludes that between 12 and 29 million Indians died in the 1876-78 faminefamine alone and this happened when there was a surplus of grains in 1876; he holds British state policy responsible for the large scale murder. Lytton StracheyStrachey, Lytton (the godfather of the eponymic Bloomsbury bohemian intellectual) was the viceroy of British IndiaBritish India at that time and he was busy organizing, during this horrific faminefamine, the most colossal and expensive meal in world history for 68,000 officials, satraps and maharajas to celebrate “Kaiser-i-Hind”Kaiser-i-Hind Victoria (Davis (2001), chapter 1). Furthermore, in 1879, Viceroy Lytton “actually overruled his entire council to accommodate Lancashire’s lobby (the Association) by removing all import duties on British-made cotton, despite India’s desperate need for more revenue in a year of widespread faminefamine and tragic loss of life throughout Maharashtra” (Wolpert, 1989:248).” Due to lack of space we cannot go into further details but we will summarize some of the other insights: China and India, previous to European penetration/colonization,colonization had historically managed food shortages much better; for example, “there was no mass mortality from either starvation or disease from the 1743-44 climatic catastrophe” (— “the spring monsoon failed two years in a row, devastating winter wheat in Zhili (Hubei) and northern Shandong; scorching winds withered crops and farmers dropped dead in their fields from sunstroke”); relief was sufficiently well organized that many deaths were avoided (Davis 2001:280). Similarly, Bajaj and SrinivasBajaj and Srinivas (1996) document in their book Annaṁ Bahukurvīta how the dharmic ecosystem over the millennia functioned during emergencies for relief, valorising the act of giving food as a solemn vow (tad vratam) rather than expecting free market to work well during shortages. Shockingly, in contrast, Lytton's Anti-Charitable Contributions Act 1877 forbade, on pain of imprisonment, private relief donations that interfered with free market setting of prices during the faminefamine. Furthermore,

“in contrast to the rigidity and dogmatism of British land-and-revenue settlements, both the Mughals and Marathas flexibly tailored their rule to take account of the crucial ecological relationships and unpredictable climate fluctuations of the subcontinent’s drought-prone regions. The Mughals had “laws of leather,” wrote journalist Vaughan Nash during the faminefamine of 1899, in contrast to the British “laws of iron” (Nash 1900:92). Although the British insisted that they had rescued India from “timeless hunger,” more than one district official was jolted when Indian nationalists quoted from a 1878 study published in the prestigious Journal of the Statistical SocietyJournal of the Statistical Society that contrasted 31 serious famines in 120 years of British rule against only 17 recorded famines in the entire previous two millennia (Walford, 1878: 434–42).” (ibid).

To effect “balance of payments” of European powers (esp. British due to their massive war machine: “military expenditures never comprised less than 25 percent (34 percent including police) of [British] India’sBritish India annual budget”; compare with typical 3–5% defence budgets now), recourse was also taken to effect financial exchange rate manipulations that pauperized the ChineseChinese!exploitation of and Indian people as China and India were on silver standardsilver standard: the move to gold standardgold standard by major European powers (for eg, Germany in 1871), then by US, Japan caused silver to depreciate. It is said that “the gold standard stole one quarter of the purchasing power of India’s silver ornaments (Nash 1900:88)” (ibid.) this especially calamitous during the 4 major famines between 1875-1900. Taking just the Berar regionBerar region, “during the faminefamine of 1899–1900, when 143,000 Beraris died directly from starvation, the province exported not only thousands of bales of cotton but an incredible 747,000 bushels of grain (Satya 1994:148, 281–2, 296). Despite heavy labor immigration into Berari in the 1890s, the population fell by five percent and “life expectation at birth” twice dipped into the 15-years range before finally falling to less than ten years during the “extremely bad year” of 1900 (DysonDyson 1989:181–82).” Across British IndiaBritish India, “in the age of Kipling - that “glorious imperial half century” from 1872 to 1921 - the life expectancylife expectancy of ordinary Indians fell by a staggering 20 percent, a deterioration in human biology probably without precedent in the subcontinent’s long history (Davis 1951:8).”

More recent are the Bengal famineBengal famine during WWIIWWII (see, e.g., MukerjeeMukerjee, Madhushree (2011) that details the extraordinary racism of Winston ChurchillChurchill, Winston that resulted in the death of as many as 3 million Bengalis during WWII; for example, official records show that Churchill ensured that surplus grain in New Zealand would not be diverted to Calcutta during the famine but sent to godowns in Canada in spite of pressing entreaties of officials) and the 1971 genocidegenocide by Pakistan Army (deaths estimated to be between 1.5 to 3 million, a substantial number being Indic persons) in the now Bangladesh abetted by US/UK (US and British navies made a threatening pincer against India in December 1971 with nuclear submarines) and some European powers as they were busy looking elsewhere. As Pollock and his followers casually implicate Sanskrit's deep structuredeep structure and Mīmāṁsaka-s for genocidegenocide, it may be of interest to know that many in Germany looked up to the obvious and demonstrated skills, for at least 1 century, of the British on how to “pacify" native populations. For example, use of Maxim machine guns post 1880's turned British imperial conquest into a genocidal murder of a number of colonized groups of people in Africa. The German genocidegenocide in Namibia through mass starvation, dehydration and plain unconscionable murder during 1904-14 was an example of how well the “German student" had learnt the lessons from the “English teacherEnglish teacher". No wonder the Nazi Germans did not need much research into how to conduct a holocaustholocaust!Nazi barely two decades later.

The period just before the WWI can be said to be the period when Europeans and Americans had perfected the art of mass murdermass murder on native peoples worldwide in the name of convenient and unscrupulously applied “natural principlesnatural principles". No wonder that WWI saw mass barbarism on a scale not known before; it requires no stressing that the Europeans had by now learnt the art of indiscriminate warfare (including use of poison gaspoison gas and dropping of bombs on civilians using the new warplanes) except that WWI finally pushed the mindless violence mostly into the European continent itself.

Pollock quotes a part of GītāBhagavadgītāGītā|Bhagavadgita 2.63 at the beginning of his article:

(smṛti-bhraṁśād buddhi-nāśaḥ)
“When memory is destroyed, intelligence is lost.”

This is an apt quote: when memory of Namibia and other genocidesgenocide (either by Europeans or by Americans) or that of the Christian anti-Jewishanti-Jewish attitudes in history are erased, intelligent reasoning is a casualty.

Motives for Pollock’s Thesis

Given the brief listing of the above genocidesgenocide and the attendant discussion, it is clear that Pollock is wide off the mark. But the important question is why is Pollock raising such indefensible arguments?

First, it seems to require only a little thought to ascribe Indic influence on Nazism, namely use of swastikaswastika (used in Nazi circles post 1920 as its symbol and adopted from swastika's use in the German völkischvölkisch nationalist movements) or the use of “Aryan” racistAryan!race paradigmracist paradigm but one can argue that this is a reflection of lazy thinking. Considering the swastika, it is useful to make a deeper analysis. While swastika is used in an Indic context in an auspicious sense almost exclusively (svastikaḥ ⇒ svasti (śubhāya hitaṁ)+ka that which is good for auspiciousness), the swastika was used in the Nazi circles to project power or only in a political sense. The sense of “sacred” is completely absent. Moreover Nazi ideologues such as Alfred RosenbergRosenberg, Alfred came to Germany from Russia/Latvia/Estonia backgrounds where the swastika symbol was/is still a local cultural symbol; e.g., the Air Force AcademyAir Force Academy (Finnish Air Force) has a swastika in its emblem as of now while the Finnish Air force had it till 1944 (Tepora (2016:171)). Furthermore, the swastika has some resemblance to the Iron Cross, a military decorationIron Cross (Prussian military decoration) in the Kingdom of PrussiaPrussia, and later in the German Empire (1871–1918) except for an additional stroke at each end and the slant.

Similarly, the use of Arya in Indic context was always a term of respect, not power or race. Furthermore all the major Nazi ideologuesNazi!ideologues such as Rosenberg, HimmlerRosenberg, Himmler, or ChamberlainChamberlain, Houston had access to Sanskrit through translations and very unlikely that the “deep structuredeep structure" of Sanskrit or the Mīmāṁsā theories (as casually thrown in by Halbfass) was known to them. Furthermore, ElstElst, Koenraad (2004) writes that

“... in spite of Himmler'sHimmler, Heinrich openness to occult theories about the Aryan raceAryan!race, his plans to weed out the handicapped and to promote the procreation of superior Aryan types can very simply be derived from eugenicist ideas which were fairly widespread in the medical community of not just Germany but also of Scandinavia, the USA and other countries.”

So if Pollock is at all right about the connections between Sanskrit “deep structure" and Nazi genocidegenocide, then it has to be due to a sort of “butterfly effectbutterfly effect" in spite of the massive evidence against it (ie. a butterfly flapping its wings in, say, China causes a major hurricane in Midwest US as the weather system is a chaotic system and not amenable to easy mathematical analysis; a very small change in the initial conditions or state of a deterministic nonlinear system can result in large differences in a later state!). Or, is Pollock's explanation an ode to kākatālīya-nyāyakākatālīya-nyāyanyāya-s!kākatālīya (the maxim of the accidental falling of the palm fruit upon a crow flying as per its fancy)?

What is surprising is that Pollock does not use the Christian Church as the “deep structure" that could be a good explanation for the Holocaustholocaust!Nazi: its anti-semitismanti-Semitism can be said to be “in-born" in a deep way. The Church has survived for 2 millennia as a powerful force (fully 1/3 rd of the world's population now subscribes to this “axiomatic” belief system without any need for any substantiation); it is also likely to be the largest MNC worldwide as of now in terms of resources and people (e.g., bishopsbishops, Vatican appointment in India are appointed from VaticanVatican), and its imprint is everywhere (in the Arctic too!). Its “deep structure" should be impregnable as it has incorporated or “digested" Judaism (e.g., Old Testament), paganismpaganism (Greek, Roman or other European varieties), many native cultures worldwide (Native American, Ethiopian, Indian, etc). One can also argue that the English language fits the requirement for “deep structure", if not at the grammatical level, at the economic, social and political level; it is the global hegemon with many credits for subjugating hapless people worldwide. Contrast this with Sanskrit, whose “deep structure" that is said to have aided in genocidegenocide, is on its last legs having been systematically driven close to extinction by the Islamic and Christian military structures and now by the “modern secular" government in India itself. Its “deep structure"deep structure alone unfortunately does not seem enough to keep it alive (argued by Pollock himself!) given the brutal environment it finds itself in.

What is also surprising is that Pollock and his later followers casually invert what really happened: Romas or GypsiesRomas or Gypsies (of Indic extraction) were murdered in large numbers (half a million) in Europe by the Nazis. Instead of Indic world giving ideas for genocidegenocide to the Europeans, the inverse is true with the people of Indic extraction, the Gypsies as widely believed, getting genocided against! The victim is victimized in Pollock's analysis. Another example of this phenomenon is the following: Pollock writes

“The fact that the production of dharma-nibandhadharma!-nibandha discourse, as noted above, almost perfectly follows the path of advance of the Sultanate from the Doab to Devagiri to the Deccan (Lakṣmīdhara, Hemādri, Madhaya) suggests, on the one hand, that totalizing conceptualizations of society became possible only by juxtaposition with alternative lifeworlds, and on the other, that they became necessary only at the moment when the total form of the society was for the first time believed, by the privileged theorists of society, to be threatened.” (Pollock 1993: 105)

Here Islamic military structures who have gave no choice to large populations (Egypt, Persia, ...) except to accept Islamic domination (generously phrased as “alternative lifeworlds”!) are viewed as doing a “positive” favour; to resist is to accept “totalizing conceptualizations of society” by “privileged theorists of society”. ISIS may be happy to hear of such formulations. Interestingly, in spite of many examples of wanton destruction of life and property by the Islamic armies in India, there is hardly any credible example of the reverse historically.

So what is the explanation for Pollock's writings? The only explanation that I can advance is that many of us, not excluding Pollock, are consciously or unconsciously embedded in powerful propaganda systems, and Pollock’s writings, I believe, can only be explained on such a model. Consider the following feature that I came across in The “Hindu" newspaperHindu, The (newspaper) in 2012 (Basu 2012).

Here a very favourable report is given of a German woman, whose father was admittedly a Nazi soldierNazi!soldier but she now is an Indian convener of the National Alliance of People's Movements,National Alliance of People's Movements and working in Tamil Nadu Theological Seminary,Tamil Nadu Theological Seminary Madurai (having first come to India with her husband on a two-year study programme at the Christian Institute for Study of Religion and Society,Christian Institute for Study of Religion and Society Bangalore). She researches Dalit atrocities, issues affecting farm workers, tobacco workers, fisherfolk and construction labourers, women activists, and “has put her stamp on every movement radiating an uncomplicated spirit of affability".

What is surprising is her locus of work. When a massive tremor (Nazism) has struck Germany and one's own immediate father is involved (but “we were not aware of what was happening"), the most convenient thing is to study someone else's misdeeds, even if they are not on the same scale (compare with 50-80 million deaths in WWII). It sure makes you feel better! Not just that; there is livelihood available through the same complicit (worldwide) organization! While one is not arguing that she cannot do research on any topic of her choice, what is interesting is the choice made: a “concerned" person who escapes from family’s Nazi involvement and points fingers at others. It would have behooved her to do research and/or teach, say, on how Nazis came to powerpower!political, or how the VaticanVatican helped HitlerHitler!Adolf to assume dictatorial power etc (note that if the Catholic Centre party had votedHitler!Catholic Centre party voting for no or even abstained on the Enabling (“dictatorship") Act, HitlerHitler!Adolf would have been defeated but their leader Ludwig KaasKaas, Ludwig, a close friend and advisor to Eugenio PacelliPacelli, Eugenio, the future Pope Pius XIIPope Pius XII, endorsed the Enabling Act[7]) or even how Lutheran ChurchLutheran Church funds conversions,conversions etc in India resulting in severe social stress in rural and semi-urban communities and how foreign money supports the powerful Church establishment in South India (Malhotra et al 2011), etc.

Pollock's discourse is unfortunately not any better. Pollock's clear worldview is that “Hindutva"Hindutva is responsible for many ills that afflict India and, as a concerned person, it his duty to fight against such tendencies. But the Hindutva MovementHindutva!Movement has arisen precisely because the Indic people have been essentially without voice for the better part of seven decades after 1947 (tragically possibly due to Hindu Mahasabha’s Nathuram Godse murdering Gandhi and the Congress Party/Nehru familyCongress Party/Nehru family exploiting it to marginalize any serious Indic thinkingIndic!thinking). Given such a worldview but one without any serious basis in reality, only a propagandistic model makes sense to understand an eminent academic like Pollock; a more detailed look is given below.

By ignoring or not acknowledging recent research (e.g., the Namibian genocidegenocide of the Germans as a likely blueprint for Jewish genocidegenocide of the Nazis) and proposing the deep structuredeep structure of Sanskrit as a possible candidate, Pollock is precisely doing a needed exercise in a propaganda system. If an obvious truth has to be made to recede into the background, non-issues that cloud one's thinking has to be casually introduced, then carefully nurtured and repeated by others so that in a few decades non-issues can take centre stage. A good example can be seen in the demonization of ModiModi, demonization of since 2002; even if careful research shows the hand of vested or complicit interests (Congress Party, for example), the manufactured “facts" take a life of their own. This is a specific instance of a more general anti-Indicanti-Indic (or anti-BJPanti-BJP) propaganda. Madhu KishwarKishwar, Madhu in her book Modi, Muslims and Media documents these carefully but the propagandistic system present in the country does not yet allow for a careful examination of the truth (Kishwar 2013). It is interesting to know that Modi’s visit to US when he was the CM of Gujarat was thwarted by a collaboration between evangelical Christian Right in the US, the Indian (expat) Left and the Islamic interests even when not a single FIR was filed against him (and till today not filed) (Janmohamed 2013). Pollock was one of the signatories to this petition[8]; the surprise here is that, without evaluating the proper situation on the ground and going by prejudices, he seems to accept that a “genocide”genocide has taken place in Gujarat, while at the same time deflecting attention from the complicity of major genocidal actors such as Europeans/Americans or the Church with respect to what happened in Americas, Europe or Australia by targeting Sanskrit as a contributing factor. Modi was then and now is possibly seen as a threat as he is a symbol of a self-respecting nation and has proved many detractors wrong by his measured moves and hard work. When Swami Laxmanananda SaraswatiSaraswati, Swami Laxmanananda in Orissa was killed, it was again a surprising collaboration between MaoistsMaoists and evangelical ChristiansChristians. The United States Commission on International Religious FreedomUnited States Commission on International Religious Freedom, The (which is dominated by evangelical Christians) strangely concluded in 2009 that India and Afghanistan are in the same category (“watch list of countries of particular concern") when it comes to religious freedom (and that Pakistan is actually better).

Another good example is that of Mathias TierceTierce, Mathias, a German author, editor and yoga enthusiast (GhoshGhosh, Kali Charan 2012). His books include Yoga in the Third Reich: Concepts, Contrasts, Consequences. Probably influenced by Pollock-type writings, this yoga enthusiast here repeats unsubstantiated charges or unbalanced critiques; HimmlerHimmler, Heinrich carrying the GītāBhagavadgītā with him everywhere, or misusing or misunderstanding its complex contextual reasoning is used to taint Gītā with Nazism. Gītā's and Upaniṣadic messages are for a person who has already reached a high level of ethical conduct (as they equate the human self with the cosmic Self, a dangerous doctrine in the hands of immature persons) and not for someone who needs justifications for murderous deeds. Gītā's message is closer to “do your right or just duty without worrying about the rewards", but not to “do unjust (or murderous) acts with detachment (!) and expect to be free from that karma". However, this yoga enthusiast/author paraphrases supposedly one of Himmler's favourite śloka-s as “even if they commit evil acts, they can still remain untainted and unaffected by ones' own actions” which seems a clear fabrication. He uses this as an example of the amoral world of Gītā and HimmlerHimmler, Heinrich. Probably, he is referring to Gītā 4.36 where it is said that even the worst sinner can cross over all the wickedness with the raft of knowledge. Or, mixing Gītā 4.36 with 4.14 where Kṛṣṇa says that “actions do not taint Me as I have no hankering after the results of actions"! Or, wilfully misconstruing Gītā 5.7 where a karmayogin is said to be untainted even though performing action by not also quoting that he has to be pure in his heart, fully conquered his mind and mastered his senses, etc. Again, Tietke is clearly fulfilling one role in a propaganda system where mud is thrown widely by (preferably) disparate actors in the hope that something will stick even if known to be untrue. Another exercise (in the opposite direction!) that attempts to disconnect (“good”) Yoga from Indic tradition and making it Western-inspired is Mark Singleton’sSingleton, Mark book on Yoga (Yoga Body: The Origins of Modern Posture Practice); it is not discussed further due to lack of space.

Furthermore, Pollock has interpreted many Indic texts, such as the RāmāyaṇaRāmāyaṇa, as reflective of social oppression and Sanskrit as complicit. Koenraad ElstElst, Koenraad (2004) writes:

“Marxists never wonder whether a theory is true or not, they only care about what class interests a theory may serve. Lenin despised a concern for universally valid truth as “bourgeois objectivity”; in this respect, he was the forerunner of postmodern relativismpostmodern relativism.”

Thus, it probably matters little if there is sufficient truth in an analysis or interpretation; it matters only if such an analysis can be used to reduce “oppression" as refracted into the text. Thus, even such propaganda is legitimate, as the end goal is all that is important. Furthermore such propaganda is useful to reduce the discomfort sensitive souls steeped in “Western UniversalismWestern Universalism” would experience if informed that Nazi holocaustholocaust!Nazi “pre-formed” closer home (given already the sensitivity to oppression in Sanskrit textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic)). Hence, it is useful to look for Nazi holocaust precursors elsewhere to assuage conscience or as a part of dominant narrative (or equivalently, part of propaganda system) and to preempt the impact of works like StannardStannard, David E ahead of time. This provides implicit support to “western universalism” by whitewashing European genocidesgenocide!whitewashing European (of Africans/Blacks, Jews, Romas, ...) and explicit support to the demonization of Indic systemsIndic!systems, demonization of. Hence it is important to understand how the propaganda systems work.

Interestingly, Pollock discusses this as part of the same article under consideration in this paper:

“In German Indology of the NS era, a largely nonscholarly mystical nativism deriving ultimately from a mixture of romanticism and protonationalism merged with that objectivism of Wissenschaft earlier described, and together they fostered the ultimate “orientalist" projectorientalist project, the legitimation of genocidegenocide. Whatever other enduring lessons this may teach us, it offers a superb illustration of the empirical fact that disinterested scholarship in the human sciences, like any other social act, takes place within the realm of interests; that its objectivity is bounded by subjectivity; and that the only form of it that can appear value-free is the one that conforms fully to the dominant ideology, which alone remains, in the absence of critique, invisible as ideology." (Pollock 1993:96)

However, stating this does not mean Pollock himself is not serving a propaganda function, ie of tarring a local tradition with Nazism when its intellectual materials have been misconstrued by German Nazis or German Indologists for reasons of settling scores with their bugbears. Note that the word “orientalist" ideally should have been qualified as “European orientalist” here, as historically they were most proficient at genocide (Spanish conquestSpanish conquest of Americas, slaving/exterminationextermination of blacks or Africans, etc). Using the “orientalist" word colors the mind somehow into thinking that “orientals" are somehow responsible for genocide, hence serves a propaganda function outright. Another instance of this occurs as “In dissecting what accordingly has to be seen as the dominant form of Indianist orientalism...” (Pollock 1993:82); here he is actually discussing German indology and is therefore needlessly confusing.

A Propaganda Modelpropaganda model

A good model of a propaganda system is that of Herman and Chomsky (1988). While their model is with respect to mass media, the same analysis is broadly applicable to other manifestations of thought control such as in academia or how Indic systemsIndic!systems of thought are portrayed in intellectual circles. It will be helpful to examine the usefulness of this model, after making some of our own changes, for understanding the propaganda against Indic systems of thinking. They write,

“... based on many years of study of the workings of media, [that it] serve[s] to mobilize support for the special interests that dominate the state and the private activity, and that their choices, emphases, and omissions can often be understood best, and sometimes with striking clarity and thought, by analyzing them in such terms." (Herman and Chomsky 1988:1)

Their propaganda modelpropaganda model views “private media as businesses interested in the sale of a product—readers and audiences—to other businesses (advertisers) rather than that of quality news to the public.” The media's “societal purpose”, they write, “...[is to serve the] agenda of privileged groups" but the study of [the media] institutionsinstitutions!media and how they function must be scrupulously ignored, apart from fringe elements or a relatively obscure scholarly literature” (Chomsky 1989:40). The theory postulates five general classes of “filters"filters (in news media) that determine the type of news that is presented in news media. These five classes are: Ownership of the medium, Medium’s funding sourcesfunding sources, Sourcing, Flak and enforcers, Anti-communism and fear ideologyfear ideology [such as “War on Terror" and “counter-terrorism"]. Furthermore, (p.2) “these elements interact with and reinforce each other. The raw material of the news must pass through successive filters, leaving only the cleansed residue fit to print."

This theory has to be certainly modified for India with a different set of filters as I am not so much concerned with media exclusively as with thought or knowledge systems (such as Indic, Christian or Islamic) represented in books, academic talks and instruction, plays, blogs etc. here, so this also needs to be modified in the model.

The filters

First, for our purposes of understanding Pollock, one can replace “Anti-communism" with “Anti-Indic"anti-Indic as the concerned media’s (world-wide) funding sourcesfunding sources is mostly from anti-Indic forces (such as many foreign NGOs, Christian organizations, Islamic sources, etc.). To justify and put this in perspective, first note that funds available to Abrahamic faithsAbrahamic faiths, funds available worldwide dwarfs that available to Indic systemsIndic!systems. In India itself, as a point of comparison, note that India’s total defence allocation (2011-12) was 1,64,000 crores. Foreign-funded NGOs (FFNGOs) in 2011-12 received about 12,000 crores ie. about 7% of India's then defence budget. It is widely believed that the inflow is much larger if non-legal flows as well as funds that come through UN system are also added to these numbers. It is noteworthy that funds given by UN bodiesUN bodies, funds from or World BankWorld Bank are not under the purview of FCRAFCRA (e.g., World Bank funding to GoI in 2013-14 was $5.2 billion (Rs 33000 crore) compared to Rs 12,000 crore ($1.8 billion) received by NGOsNGOs). Note also that the majority of donors including the top three are church-based organizations. It is therefore not surprising that any malfeasance regarding foreign NGOs or Christian/Islamic organizations in India do not find a receptive environment and gets attenuated in public discourse very quickly while anything anti-Indic can be played and replayed till it becomes centre-stage. Hence replacing the anti-communism filter with an anti-Indic filter is justifiable with respect to topics under discussion in this paper.

Let us now consider other filtersfilters (in news media). First, “ownership/control of the medium”. Even to this day, the media, the judiciary, the NGO sector or the education sector in India are owned or populated by a substantial anti-Indic eliteanti-Indic!elite. A good illustration is the recent “Award-wapsi”Award-wapsi events (2015) or supposed attacks on Church properties (2014) where minor or not so important events were magnified to hog all mindspace in the print and TV media. On the contrary, substantial damage, destruction related to Indic sphere (a good example: templestemple!destruction of in KashmirKashmir), or killings/murders/exile of those in the Indic camp (again, Kashmiri panditsKashmiri pandits) are/were barely covered. At the international level, it is even more pronounced: all major newspapers in US/UK, e.g., NYT/BBCNYT/BBC[9], regularly write highly negative or stereotyped accounts of happenings in India.

Next, the funding sourcesfunding sources as filter. The model posits that the “people buying the media products (newspapers, magazines, TV) are the product that is sold to the businesses that buy advertising space; the “news” has only a marginal role as the product”. The situation is a bit different in India compared to US where private property is more important. In India, due to the domination of the Nehru family for a better part of the last 7 decades, and limited availability of advertisements or newsprint, only news that reflected this family’s interests or did not negatively affect it could be printed to continue to get Government advertisements, and journalists would also get privileged access (e.g., on PM’s plane on trips abroad) or freeloading in terms of 5 star hotel stays or food, or even plots of land at throwaway prices. Therefore, much of the news reported had to make the Nehru family look good at least in the first 3-4 decades after independence. Here, news could be said to be marginal product of making the political families look good.

Against this, funding related to Indic activities is either at a cottage industry level (highly localised or, worse, disorganized and possibly even harmful sometimes) or actually in the hands of the anti-Indicanti-Indic!elite elements. Much of the temple wealthtemple!wealth has been neutralized as the rich temples have been taken over by the Government and the temple ecosystemtemple!ecosystem has been run to the ground or actually to fund the anti-Indic forces. Additionally, Church-related or Saudi Arabian funds are highly visible; almost any drive across any major highway in South India should be sufficient visual proof. BollywoodBollywood seems to have been under some Dubai/Pakistan or other Islamic connections for some time; however, after the Vajpayee government declared it as an industry, bank loans have became possible and the role of tainted or black money is becoming a little less. Furthermore, many intellectuals seem to be under the grip of Western interests (either due to direct funding or indirectly through awards, scholarships, and such). Consider the recent award of Magsaysay awardMagsaysay Award to a Karnatic musician; the award citation specifically states that it is for ‘ensuring social inclusiveness in culture’, a surprise as many varṇa-svarṇa and jāti-sjāti (example, MS SubbulakshmiSubbulakshmi, M S, Dwaram Venkataswamy NaiduDwaram|see{Naidu, Dwaram Venkataswamy}Naidu, Dwaram Venkataswamy, K J YesudasYesudas, Rajaratnam PillaiPillai, Rajaratnam, Sheik Chinna MoulanaSheik Chinna Moulana, etc) are/were stars in the field in addition to the (demonized) Brāhmaṇa-s; the citation says further that “He saw that his was a caste-dominatedcaste!domination art that fostered an unjust, hierarchic order by effectively excluding the lower classes from sharing in a vital part of India’s cultural legacy” (See “Thodur Madabusi Krishna”Krishna, Thodur Madabusi). Such motivated awards are de rigueur now from Western-inspired agencies and serve to deepen social cleavages in areas where not noticeable before; note also the award winner’s use of the word “caste” in approved ways. No wonder that anti-Indicanti-Indic!elite stories get maximum play in print and TV media in India (this might be becoming just a bit less after 2 years of Modi’s government and the increasing untenability of the anti-Indic story line applied indiscriminately in news events and their consequent exposure in the social media).

With respect to the next filter (sourcing), “the mass media are drawn into a symbiotic relationshipsymbiotic relationship with powerful sources of information by economic necessity and reciprocity of interestreciprocity of interest.” In our case, US universities have dedicated departments to study Indic religions but, due to convenient concerns about “secularism", Hindu or Indic religions cannot be studied or encouraged to be studied as such in Indian universitiesIndian universities, religion studies in. This is probably due to the excessive caution of the executive as the Constitution of IndiaConstitution of India lists “to develop scientific temper” as one of the fundamental duties of Indian citizens (but surprisingly seems to be restricted only to the Indic community). Hence the sourcing issue is important as (small) armies of US scholars study Indic religions with all their biasesbias intact and fill up the intellectual space with their writings. Since the Indic scholars cannot be supported by the formal research organizations in India, research output in this sector in India resembles at the most a cottage industry with sporadic or poor quality writings. It is often said that Sanskrit study is better done outside India even when native scholars that remain are outstanding! The end result is that US universities decide the course of research on Indic issues and native Sanskrit/native language scholarship counts for nothing. As Rajiv MalhotraMalhotra, Rajiv and his colleagues have documented in Invading the SacredInvading the Sacred, native informants are used sometimes by European/American academics to extract information that end up being used in surprisingly twisted ways.

Next, the flak or enforcer filter employed against Indic systemsIndic!systems. “If flak is produced on a large scale, or by individuals or groups with substantial resources, it can be both uncomfortable and costly to the media". Here flak is what makes receptivity difficult to all shades of thought including Indic perspectives, and how flak is orchestrated for specific purposes. Specifically, flak here is essentially the hostility to the Indic perspective or showing it up for its non-“coolness”, or that squelches uncomfortable questions about received models of understanding (e.g., “Modi a butcher or murderer”). A good example is the invisibility and lack of positions in Indian academia for people with Indic focusIndic!focus in the social sciences area; flak ensures that they cannot survive in the hostile environment. Madhu Kishwar became persona non grata once she started research on understanding why Modi was being demonized incessantly and wrote the book `Modi, Muslims and Media'. As another example of flak, she found it difficult to find a publisher for her book (and had to publish it herself) or launch her book in Delhi (2013) as no Indian Government funded social research body would provide the venue or, having promised a venue, would invariably cancel at the last minute.

For fear ideologyfear ideology in the model, one can list RSS/BJP demonizationBJP!demonization ofRSS, demonization of, “Hindutva”Hindutva, “right wing fascismright wing fascismfascism”, human rights violations (atrocity literatureatrocity literature (Malhotra et al 2011)), academic Hinduphobia (Malhotra 2016) as exemplars.

Validation of the Model

While this is non-trivial, the last 2 decades has shown the issues in sharp detail. For the first time since 1947 political formations with sympathy for or support of Indic peoples are serious contenders for powerpower!political (in some states) or in power (at the centre or in some states). The propaganda system against the Indic people finds this unacceptable and has used every means available to contain it, the most notable example being the demonization of Modi starting from about 2002 and continuing even now. I discuss this briefly due to lack of space; there are also many published works on the subject (e.g., early works such as those by Dayanand SaraswatiSaraswati, Swami DayanandaDayananda Saraswati, VivekanandaVivekananda, Swami, Sita Ram GoelGoel, Sita Ram, and more recent works —such as by Rajiv Malhotra (Invading the SacredInvading the Sacred; Breaking India (with Arvind Neelakandan); Academic Hinduphobia); by Madhu Kishwar (Zealous Reformers; Deadly Laws: Battling Stereotypes; Modi, Muslims and Media), or the works of S N BalagangadharaBalagangadhara S N. Some well known issues are the following:

how Ishrat encounter caseIshrat encounter case was reported compared to Sadhvi Pragya’sSadhvi Pragya imprisonment and torture
temples under government controltemple!government control and their ruination. Once upon a time, temples were the centers of learning, culture and svādhyāya (study of self). Government control has made temples vacate its role in learning and culture, leaving only a shell under an unfriendly bureaucratic management and thus is so unsatisfactory that going to temples is now a chore, given the opportunistic developments and land grabbing around the templestemple!land grabbing of and the resulting noise and pollution. Propagation of Dharmic activity through the temples is no longer easy given that a parasitic bureaucracyparasitic bureaucracy decides what can be done.
the sorry state of Indic languagesIndic!languages, especially Sanskrit.
legal interferencelegal interference in many Indic traditions (e.g., Sādhu-sSādhu in principle could be classed as “vagrants” under still not-repealed British RajBritish Raj regulations and hence confined), Jain practice of santarasantara (voluntary death by fasting) declared illegal suddenly, patronizing judicial pronunciations against customary practices in places of worship.
given the “no-interference” or “no-go” policy of NehruvianNehru!policies of policies with respect to personal laws of “minorities” (an excessive caution given that the constitution of India recognises minority entitlementsminority entitlements with respect to educational institutionsinstitutions!educational only, minority being either linguistic or religious), NGOsNGOs and others have felt no restraint in proposing and effecting legal remedies for the Indic peoples without any balance (going against the principle of natural justicenatural justice where an accused has to prove his innocence rather than the accusing party) such as mindlessly stringent dowry lawsdowry laws that criminalizes the man’s side of the family without due process, attempted legislation with respect to rape in marriage or with respect to divorce, attempted legislation on communal violencecommunal violence, legislation on that makes only the “majority” community responsible, etc. The Indian state has been derelict in outsourcing legislative wisdom to favoured NGOs with its most egregious form during the UPA rule (2004-2014) through the National Advisory CouncilNational Advisory Council, initially not even a legal entity, that resulted in a dyarchydyarchy where power was exercised without responsibility.

Pollock and the Propaganda Modelpropaganda model

The following can be cited to show that the model is useful with respect to Pollock:

The Anti-Indicanti-Indic!elite perspective of Pollock is clear going by his writings. He has written about the oppression in the Sanskrit cosmopolis as well as being part of campaigns against HindutvaHindutva and other issues as a “concerned Sanskritist”. There is no sense of sacred in his view of Sanskrit philology as The Battle for SanskritBattle for Sanskrit, The by Rajiv Malhotra clearly shows. While he has opined that Sanskrit is dead, he still wants to flog a “dead horse” going by his enormous output; what for?
The sourcing aspect (availability of intellectual materials) is clear as the major visible centers of formal intellectual Sanskrit scholarshipSanskrit!scholarship has moved to the West (US, Germany) such as at Ivy schoolsIvy schools. Students from India go to these centers for higher studies without any serious connection with local Indic scholarly community.
The funding aspect is also clear: Government of India has for all practical purposes refused to fund “religion” based studies, especially Indic ones and the only funds available are dispersed/local. While funds for such studies are also not that easy in US/Europe, the funds available at Ivy schools are still much larger and more consistent than what are available in India.
The flak is contributed by many of Pollock’s supporters or his students, professional bodies like RISA/AARRISA/AAR, Left and Abrahamic supporters in the media in India and elsewhere. Note also the example of the two Yoga instructors (Mathias Tierce and Mark Singleton) given earlier.

The Reality of anti-Indic Propaganda and Its Counteranti-Indic!propaganda

Given the propaganda system in operation, it is clear that Indic systemsIndic!systems will be at the receiving end. There has been and will in future be disinformation, “digestion”digestion, defamation, victimization/intimidation, attempted starving of funds, etc. Given this reality, what are the options open to us now? There are some heavy handed approaches such as trying to pass anti-defamationanti-defamation[10], anti-hate lawsanti-hate laws just like anti-dowryanti-dowry laws, anti-SC/ST atrocities lawsanti-SC/ST atrocities laws[11], etc. but these are generally problematic and often indefensible (e.g., due to the burden of proof on accused, reversing standard jurisprudence). Getting sufficient support in the legislatures may also be quite difficult for the Indic case. Or one can use the country’s existing laws such as under Section 295A of Indian Penal CodeIndian Penal Code, which forbids “deliberate and malicious acts intended to outrage the feelings of any religious community,” just as Batra used it against Doniger’sDoniger, Wendy book; this is also problematic as such laws can also interfere with sincere and incisive discussions. While poison pillspoison pills (Malhotra 2014:300) and such other interesting ideas (just like copyleft in software) are useful in protecting one set of truth claims against another, they do not protect the replication mechanisms for such ideas themselves and hence need some complementary support.

One approach also could be the use of (IPR) laws on moral rightslaw!on moral rights (especially the part concerning right to the integrity of the work). These guarantee that a work cannot be “modified” (for example intentionally mistranslate a book) to bring the original author into disrepute. However, these do not work as the works in question, e.g., GītāBhagavadgītā, are typically many centuries old and we are also discussing a philological collection. Essentially, many Indic works/thought systems are in the public domain with no tangible “author”.

The best course seems to be to work with available means for redress (e.g., with the recent California text bookCalifornia text book hearings) but many systems may not be as open as necessary for redress in numerous cases. In such cases mobilization and protest remain the only choices.

Another approach is using the model available in the free software community. Here technical competence and meritocracy matter; if one is not able to produce the free software required for a particular purpose, that inability makes that person incapable of affecting further decisions viz “We reject kings, presidents and voting. We believe in rough consensus and running code” (Dave Clark). Since some model of effectiveness is available in the world of (computer) code to a reasonable extent across the world, this perspective is feasible. If such a model of effectiveness is available in matters largely affecting Indic persons, those with effective solutions can be said to have “adhikāraadhikāra”.

However, in the battle against anti-Indic propagandaanti-Indic!propaganda, we typically only have “truth claims". (If they involve only “facts”, standard methods may be good enough.) How do we judge effectiveness of an argument? When does criticism cross the line and become propaganda? Who can speak for or provide critical perspectives on Indic models? Could this be how well such perspectives or criticisms are received by Indic populace? Is this akin to the notion of adhikāra present already in the tradition? Or, does this mean those that help the Indic community in a significant way (e.g., Baba Ramdev, or Sri Sri Ravishankar) or those who are perceived to be effective widely have the “adhikāraadhikāra” and not others? If alternative communities without connection with “original" ones (for example, a Yoga school outside India) are in the picture, what right do they have in interpreting tradition? Is the adhikāra is to be negotiated, not asserted? Are the moral rights to be acknowledged? Given Rajiv Malhotra’s extensive documentation of “digestion”digestion of Indic systemsIndic!systems, digestion of by powerful forces outside the Indic sphere, these are not minor issues and such issues may well actually decide the trajectory of the Indic universe.

Note that in some other areas of IPR there has been movement already such as in geographical indicatorsgeographical!indicators (basmati ricebasmati rice is a good example; it can only be product from the Indian subcontinent) or in biodiversitybiodiversity (where there is some protection from exploitation of rare flora and fauna); misrepresentation attracts legal penalties. Note that this problem is also faced by traditional knowledge systems worldwide. While issues affecting traditional knowledge have been studied well in the last few decades, in India at least, some motivated researchers have minimized them or put these systems as existing in opposition to Indic systemsIndic!systems due to fears of “Hindutva”Hindutva and the like (for example, see Neelakandan’s discussion with respect to criticism against “Ayurgenomics”Ayurgenomics (Neelakandan 2016)). We may need to see how traditional knowledge (e.g., use of turmeric) has been protected and possibly explore extending an appropriate model to the Indic world also. This has major implications for Indic systems as many of them are in the informal domain and hence are subject to capture, disinformation or “digestion”. It is clear that the above questions need to be investigated carefully; we have only scratched the surface.

In Pollock’s case, does his political or ideological perspectives (e.g., Marxist-like or “Western Universalist” perspective) preclude any adhikāraadhikāra? Given the open-ended aspect of lived life, such a restrictive perspective or model also seems problematic. CarakaCaraka, for example, says

kṛtsno hi loko buddhimatām ācāryaḥ, śatruś cābuddhimatām
ataś cābhisamīkṣya buddhimatā’mitrasyāpi dhanyaṁ yaśasyam āyuṣyaṁ pāuṣṭikaṁ lokyam abhyupadiśato vacaḥ śrotavyam anuvidhātavyaṁ ceti (Carakasaṁhitā 8.14)

“...the whole world is teacher for the wise and an enemy for the foolish. Therefore, the wise, after careful examination, learn even from rivals about excellence, fame, long life, health, and of world affairs by listening to their words of instruction and assimilating them”.

A better approach or perspective may therefore be that already present in Taittirīya Upaniṣad (Śikṣā Valli, Anuvāka 11) that says (repeated here for emphasis),

yāny anavadyāni karmāṇi | tāni sevitavyāni | no itarāṇi |

Follow only such actions that `are untainted', not any other.

yāny asmākaṁ sucaritāni tāni tvayopāsyāni | no itarāṇi |

Whatever is good in us, follow those, not any other.

ye ke cāsmacchreyāṁso brāhmaṇāḥ | teṣāṁ tvayā’’sanena praśvasitavyam |

If there are any better brāhmaṇa-s, offer them a seat and “don't so much as breathe”!

Conclusions

In this paper, we have explored one paper of Pollock that touches on German Indology, Sanskrit and the Nazi ideology and attempted to show its connection with a propagandapropaganda (passim) system as the best explanation available. Further work is needed to empirically substantiate some aspects of the model (for example, funding, sourcing aspects from funding agencies as well establish the number and nature of “flak enforcers” in news media as well newer media such as social media). The intersection of propaganda, anti-Indicanti-Indic!elite biasbias as well as legal remedies also have been sketched briefly; this needs more serious work.

Bibliography

“ADL Welcomes Election of Cardinal Ratzinger as New Pope” (19 Apr, 2005) http://www.adl.org/PresRele/VaticanJewish_96/44698_96.htm. Accessed on 20 May 2016.
Alvares, Claude (2000) Collected Writings of Dharampal Series. Mapusa: Other India Press
Bajaj, J and Srinivas, M.D. (1996) “Annaṁ bahu kurvīta”. Madras: Centre for Policy Studies.
Bartrop, Paul R and Jacobs, Steven Leonard (2015) (eds) Modern Genocide: The Definitive Resource and Document Collection. Santa Barbara, CA: ABC-CLIO.
Basu, Soma (03 May, 2012) “From Germany. For India”. In The Hindu. http://www.thehindu.com/features/metroplus/society/from-germany-for-india/article3380644.ece. Accessed 15 May 2016.
Chomsky, Noam (1989) Necessary Illusions: Thought Control In Democratic Societies. Pantheon. ISBN 978-0-89608-366-0.
Coalition Against Genocide (24 Feb, 2005) “Faculty Letter to AAHOA”. http://www.coalitionagainstgenocide.org/press/support/faculty.aahoa.php. Accessed 06 Aug, 2016
“Colonial Genocides” http://www.cis.yale.edu/gsp/colonial/index.html. Accessed May 20, 2016. Now see under gsp.yale.edu.
Davis, K. (1951) Population of India and Pakistan. Princeton: Princeton Univ Press.
Davis, Mike (2001) Late Victorian Holocausts: El Niño Famines and the Making of the Third World. NY: Verso.
Dharampal (1971) Collected Works of Dharampal (Vol 1.) Indian Science and Technology in the Eighteenth Century. Mapusa: Other India Press.
Dirks, Nicholas B. (2001) Castes of Mind: Colonialism and the Making of Modern India. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.
Dutt, R C (1900) Open Letters to Lord Curzon on Famines and land assessments in India. London: Kegan Paul.
Dyson, T. (1989) “The historical demography of Berar, 1881–1980”. In T. Dyson (Ed.) India’s Historical Demography: Studies in Famine, Disease and Society. London.
Elst, Koenraad (12 Aug, 2004) “Hinduism, Environmentalism and the Nazi Bogey”. In The Koenraad Elst Site. http://koenraadelst.bharatvani.org/articles/politics/bogey.html. Accessed on 15 May, 2016.
Ericksen, Robert P (2009) “Christian Complicity? Changing Views on German Churches and the Holocaust”. In Holocaust Encyclopedia website. https://www.ushmm.org/m/pdfs/20091110-ericksen.pdf. Accessed on 20 May 2016
Fischer, Eugen; Baur, Erwin and  Lenz, Fritz (1921–1940) Principles of Human Heredity and Race Hygiene. Berlin.
Ghosh, Kali Charan (1944) Famines in Bengal, 1770–1943. Calcutta : Indian Associated Publishing Co.
Ghosh, Palash (26 Mar, 2012) “Nazi Germany’s Fascination With Ancient India: The Case Of Heinrich Himmler". In International Business Times. http://www.ibtimes.com/nazi-germanys-fascination-ancient-india-case-heinrich-himmler-214364. Accessed 15 May 2016.
Grünendahl, Reinhold (2012) “History in the Making: On Sheldon Pollock’s “NS Indology” and Vishwa Adluri’s “Pride and Prejudice””. International Journal of Hindu Studies 16, 2; pp. 189–257
Herman, Edward S. and Chomsky, Noam (1988) Manufacturing Consent: The Political Economy of the Mass Media. New York: Pantheon Books.
Hilberg, Raul (1961) The Destruction of European Jews. New Haven: Yale University Press.
Hildebrandt, Sabine (2016) The Anatomy of Murder: Ethical Transgressions and Anatomical Science during the Third Reich. Brooklyn, NY: Berghahn Books.
Horsman, Reginald (1981) “Race and Manifest Destiny: The Origins of American Racial Anglo-Saxonism” Cambridge: Harvard Univ Press
Janmohamed, Zahir (05 Dec, 2013) “U.S. Evangelicals, Indian Expats Teamed Up to Push Through Modi Visa Ban". In The New York Times. Accessed on 06 Aug, 2016.
Kevles, Danial (1994) “Eugenics and the Human Genome Project: Is the Past Prologue”. In Timothy F. Murphy, Marc Lappé (Ed.) Justice and the Human Genome Project. Berkeley: University of California Press.
Kishwar, Madhu (2013) Modi, Muslims and Media. Manushi Publications. New Delhi.
Madley, Benjamin (2004) “Patterns of frontier genocide 1803–1910: the Aboriginal Tasmanians, the Yuki of California, and the Herero of Namibia.” Journal of Genocide Research (2004), 6(2), June; pp. 167–192.
Madley, Benjamin (2005) “From Africa to Auschwitz: How German South West Africa Incubated Ideas and Methods Adopted and Developed by the Nazis in Eastern Europe". European History Quarterly July 2005 vol. 35 no. 3; pp. 429–464.
Madley, Benjamin (2016) “An American Genocide: The United States and the California Indian Catastrophe, 1846-1873” New Haven: Yale Univ Press.
Malhotra, Rajiv (2009) “American Exceptionalism and the Myth of the Frontiers”. In Rajani Kannepalli Kanth: The Challenge of Eurocentrism: Global Perspectives, Policy, and Prospects. NY: Palgrave Macmillan.
Malhotra, Rajiv (2014) Indra’s net. Noida: HarperCollins.
Malhotra, Rajiv (2016) Academic Hinduphobia. New Delhi: Voice of India.
Malhotra, Rajiv and Neelakandan, Arvind. (2011) Breaking India. New Delhi: Amaryllis.
Mukerjee, Madhusree (2011) Churchill's Secret War: The British Empire and the Ravaging of India During World War II. NY: Basic Book
Nash, Vaughan (1900) “The Great Famine and Its Causes” London: Longmans Green
Neelakandan, Aravindan (Aug 09, 2016) “What We Knew About The Genome”. http://swarajyamag.com/magazine/what-we-knew-about-the-genome. Accessed on Oct 1, 2016
Nicholls, William (1993) Christian Antisemitism: A History of Hate. Lanham, MD: Rowman and Littlefield Publishers Inc.
Pinkerton, Alasdair (2008). “A new kind of imperialism? The BBC, cold war broadcasting and the contested geopolitics of South Asia". Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television 28 (4); pp. 537–555.
Popper, Karl (1934) The Logic of Scientific Discovery. Vienna: Springer
Pollock, Sheldon (2006) The Language of the Gods in the World of Men: Sanskrit, Culture and Power in Premodern India. Berkeley: University of California Press.
“Pope Benedict XVI reflects on life under Hitler's Nazi Party” (31 May, 2011) http://www.catholic.org/news/international/europe/story.php?id=41597. Accessed 01 Jul, 2016.
Reilly, PR (1987) “Involuntary sterilization in the United States: a surgical solution”. The Quarterly Review of Biology. Vol 62 No. 2; pp.153–70.
Roelcke, V. (2002) “Mentalities and sterilization laws in Europe during the 1930s”. Der Nervenarzt. 2002 Nov; 73(11); pp. 1019–30.
Ross, Jeffrey Ian (2011) Religion and Violence: An Encyclopedia of Faith and Conflict from Antiquity to the Present. New York: Routledge.
Satya, L. (1994) “Cotton and Famine in Berar, 1850–1900.” Ph.D. Dissertation, Boston: Tufts University.
Sofair, A N and Kaldjian, L C (2000), “Eugenic sterilization and a qualified Nazi analogy: the United States and Germany, 1930–1945”, Annals of Internal Medicine 2000 Feb 15;132(4); pp. 312–9.
Stannard, David E (1993) American Holocaust: The Conquest of the New World. NY: Oxford University Press.
Tepora, Tuomas (2016) “Emotional war? Communicating the cultural histories of war to a wider audience." Journal of Belgian History XLVI, 2016,2. pp. 185-196.
“Thodur Madabusi Krishna” (2016) http://sandbox.mossesgeld.com/rmaf/awardees/thodur-madabusi-krishna-2/. Accessed on 06 Aug, 2016.
United States Holocaust Memorial Museum. “The German Churches and The Nazi State”. Holocaust Encyclopedia. https://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005206. Accessed on 20 May 2016
Walford, Cornelius (1878), 'The famines of the world: past and present', Journal of the Royal Statistical Society. No. 41, September 1878, pp. 433–526 and No. 42, March 1879, pp. 79–265.
Woodham-Smith, Cecil (1962) The Great Hunger: Ireland 1845–1849. NY: Harper and Row.

available at https://www.academia.edu/2242722/Orientalism_and_the_postcolonial_predicament_perspectives_on_South_Asia); note that this pdf file has some infirmities (word spacing problems, etc) but this is not a problem for the arguments in this paper.

See “Pope Benedict XVI reflects on life under Hitler'sHitler!Adolf Nazi Party”.

See “ADL Welcomes Election of Cardinal Ratzinger as New Pope”.

See also “The German Churches and The Nazi State”.

See also Sofair and Kaldjian LC (2000) and also Roelcke (2002)

See Davis(2001). Also see Dutt (1900), Paul (1900), Ghosh (1944). For Ireland, see Woodham-Smith (1962).

See “ADL Welcomes Election of Cardinal Ratzinger as New Pope”.

See Coalition Against Genocide (2005).

For NYT, for a good summary, see https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Indian_sentiment#New_York_Times (accessed Jul 28, 2016). For BBC see, Alasdair Pinkerton (Oct 2008). “A new kind of imperialism? The BBC, cold war broadcasting and the contested geopolitics of South Asia". Historical Journal of Film, Radio and Television 28 (4): 537–555. This is a peer-reviewed article that analyses BBC Indian coverage from independence through 2008; it concludes that BBC coverage of South Asian geopolitics and economics has had a pervasive Indophobic slant.

The Indian legal system also has a defamation model but seems too stringent; hence, Subramanian Swamy’s recent attempt to make it more helpful with respect to freedom of expression. The Jewish Anti-Defamationanti-defamation League is a successful “pressure group” approach that might be useful to consider in the Indic context.

For example, if we need to develop a proper critique of Ambedkar or other leaders in SC/ST community, we have a big problem as of now. Due to 4 (v) of Jan 1, 2016 - NO. 1 OF 2016. [31st December, 2015.] An Act to amend the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes (Prevention of Atrocities) Act, 1989 (www.indiacode.nic.in/acts-in-pdf/2016/201601.pdf) passed only recently by both Rajya Sabha and Lok Sabha, if you “by words either written or spoken or by any other means disrespects any late person held in high esteem by members of the Scheduled Castes or the Scheduled Tribes” then it “shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to five years and with fine."

Chapter 3 Sheldon Pollock’s Idea of a “National-Socialist Indology”

Koenraad Elst

Abstract

Sheldon Pollock is by no means the first one to build on the mythology that has overgrown the factual core of a link between racism in general, National-Socialism in particular, and the study of Indo-European and Sanskrit. In his case, the alleged National-Socialist connection of Sanskrit is heavily over-interpreted and emphatically taken to be causal, as if the interest in Sanskrit has caused the Holocaust. We verify the claims on which he erects this thesis one by one, and find them surprisingly weak or simply wrong. They could only have been made in a climate in which a vague assumption of these links (starting with the swastika, which in reality was not taken from HinduismHinduism) was already common. Yet, even non-specialists could easily have checked that Adolf HitlerHitler!Adolf expressed his contempt for Hinduism, repeatedly and in writing.

Pollock’s attempt to even link the Out-of-India Theory with the Naziholocaust!Nazi worldview is the diametrical opposite of the truth; it was the rivalling Aryan Invasion TheoryAryan!Invasion Theory (which Pollock himself upholds) that formed the cornerstone and perfect illustration of the Nazi worldview. This linking could only pass peer review because of the general animus against Hinduism and Indo-European indigenism in American academe. The whole forced attempt to associate HinduismHinduism with National-SocialismNational-Socialism suggests a rare animosity against Hinduism.

Sheldon Pollock’s Idea of a “National-Socialist Indology”

Sheldon Pollock, professor of Sanskrit at Columbia University, links Sanskrit with the Holocaust, no less. Or at least, his critics (Malhotra 2016, Paranjape 2016) cite him to that effect. But according to Tony JosephJoseph, Tony (2016), one of Pollock’s declared defenders, “the anti-Pollock campaign is based on quotes stripped out of their context”. Be that as it may in general, in the present paper we will take care to put Pollock’s utterances on the links between the Sanskrit tradition and National-SocialismNational-Socialism (NS, Nazism) in context. As it happens, in this case, there is simply no context that could possibly render Pollock’s position harmless, for it is the single worst allegation possible in contemporary Western culture, viz. responsibility for the Nazi Holocaustholocaust!Nazi. Nevertheless, we will give due attention to this context.

A somewhat frivolous element from the immediate context was that NS Germany was hosting Indian freedom fighter Subhas Chandra BoseBose, Subhas Chandra. (“Jana Gana Mana, independent India’s national anthemnational!anthem, was first performed in an imposing celebration at the inauguration of the Deutsch-Indische GesellschaftDeutsch-Indische Gesellschaft in Hamburg on 11 September 1942, for Bose had chosen it as free India’s national anthem”. (HartogHartog, Rudolf 2001:iv)) But that context can perhaps best be left undiscussed, for the regiment that Bose had formed, was anything but Hindu traditionalist. Far from inspiring caste hierarchycaste!hierarchy into their NS hosts, Bose’s soldiers were not organized by castecaste, unlike those in the British-Indian armyBritish-Indian army. Bose was a socialist, a progressive, on the same anti-caste wavelength as Pollock; but the Nazis never held that against him. So let us see what Pollock himself chooses to focus on.

The centuries before National-Socialism

In his overview of pre-Nazi German Indologypre-Nazi German Indology, Pollock only follows the received wisdom when he stereotypes 19th-century German scholarship. He credits the German Orientalists with the creation of WissenschaftWissenschaft, the scholarly canons that became normative in academe worldwide, with an ideal of objectivity (as in the definition of historiographyhistoriography by Leopold von RankeRanke, Leopold von, mentioned by Pollock (1993:84): reconstructing events “as they have been in reality”); but also with a frantic search for a German national identity. In that project, they used the Sanskrit tradition, viz. as partially preserving the “Aryan”Aryan identity that, through Indo-European (Indogermanisch or ArischIndogermanisch or Arisch) linguistic unity, could inspire any German cultural self-identification.

Like so many contemporary scholars of the field, including Hindus and Muslims, he assumes the conceptual framework of Edward Said’sSaid, Edward thesis Orientalism (1978). There, SaidSaid, Edward analyses the academic discipline of Orientalism (formally: “Oriental Philology and History”, as still on this writer’s diploma) as but an instrument for control, a method used by the colonial powers to dominate the natives of the Orient. This claim has been lambasted as riddled with factual errors and as conceptually a conspiracy theory by IrwinIrwin, Robert (2006), WarraqWarraq, Ibn (2007) and ElstElst, Koenraad (2012), but has taken academe by storm and is now cited as gospel.

Pollock (1993:114) gives a nod to the existence of a “pre-orientalist orientalism”pre-orientalist orientalism, a scholarship originating in the Catholic Church’sCatholic church late-medieval attempts to reconnect with the Oriental Churches and to study its Islamic rival, when Europe had no colonies yet. Yet he formulates his own career project in Saidian terms: “Moving beyond orientalism finally presupposes moving beyond the culture of domination and the politics of coercion that have nurtured orientalism in all its varieties, and been nurtured by it in turn.” (Pollock 1993:117)

The expression “orientalism in all its varieties” refers, among other things, to the special nature of Orientalism in its mainstay, German-speaking Central Europe. Unlike France and England, Germany had initially no colonies, and later only some colonies far from the Orient. This fact should refute Said’sSaid, Edward whole thesis, but he neutralizes it by keeping German Orientalism outside the purview of his book. (Later, this gap was filled by MarchandMarchand, Suzanne 2009 and, for Indology, by Adluri & BagcheeAdluri & Bagchee 2014) According to Pollock (1993:83), Germany practised its own Orientalism in an attempt to solve its “problem of identity”, and more consequentially, “to colonize Europe, and Germany itself, from within”, in a “German allomorph of British imperialismimperialism”. And here we see, with a big stretch, the connection between the proverbial German scholarship of the 19th century and the Nazi project of empire. Just as British Orientalism was evil by being a concoction in the service of empire-building, German Orientalism was evil by its connection with hyper-nationalism and genocidegenocide. That, at least, is Pollock’s message.

Nazi investment in Indology

Modern scholars devote a lot of time to studying every possible dimension of the NS polity and ideology, including the work of anyone thought to have NS ties, such as the philosopher and NS party member Martin Heidegger:Heidegger, Martin ‘Like the predicament of Indology, that of humanistic studies in general has belatedly seized the attention of scholars, as Der Fall Heidegger [“the case of Heidegger”] demonstrates.’ (Pollock 1993:112)

And so, Pollock includes his own specialism, Indology, among the culprits. The indictment:

“In German Indology of the NS era, a largely nonscholarly mystical nativism deriving ultimately from a mixture of romanticism and protonationalism merged with that objectivism of Wissenschaft earlier described, and together they fostered the ultimate ‘orientalist’ projectorientalist project, the legitimation of genocide.”genocide (Pollock 1993:96)

The allegation is extremely serious. Yet, he never quotes any of those Indologists as actually declaring they want genocide; or that the aim of their professional choice is genocide. Since, moreover, genocide is somehow declared to be the ultimate finality of Orientalism, this seems also to indict the French and British Orientalists. Alright, he fails to prove that rather unlikely point; but what does he prove?

He claims a “substantial increase in the investment on the part of the NS state in Indology and ‘Indo-Germanistik.’ Both [Heinrich] HimmlerHimmler, Heinrich and [Alfred] RosenbergRosenberg, Alfred sponsored institutes centrally concerned with ‘Indo-Germanische GeistesgeschichteGeistesgeschichte’.” (Pollock 1993:95) Note the sly cursory shift from Indology to “Indo-Germanistik”: the former deals with India and, as we shall see, received no increased interest from the NS regime at all; while the latter deals with Europe and especially Germany, the putative racial heir of the Indo-Europeans, and became the centre of NS attention.

In fact, the proof he himself adduces, proves something else than an increased German interest in Indology. He compares a total of 26 full professors of "Aryan" orientalismAryan!orientalism in Germany with just 4 in England, the colonial metropole – but for the year 1903 (detailed in Rhys-DavidsRhys Davids, T W 1904). This had nothing to do with a NS penchant for India, for this special German interest in the Orient existed since long before (and incidentally, makes mincemeat of Said’sSaid, Edward linking Orientalism with the colonial entreprise).

In support, Pollock refers to a primary source, the Minerva JahrbücherMinerva Jahrbücher, an annuary with academic data. But after thoroughly checking these, the contemporary German Indologist from Göttingen, Reinhold Grünendahl (2012:95), shows these data to confirm an uneventful continuity with pre-NS days:

“As was the case with the 1933/34 volume and Rhys Davids’s paper of 1904, none serve to corroborate Pollock’s presumptionspresumptions. The same holds for recent evidence-based studies that in any way pertain to such issues [...], all of which confirm that Pollock’s deep ruminations on ‘the political economypolitical!economy of Indology in Germany in the period 1800–1945’ (1993: 118n5) are entirely unfounded. Nevertheless, his attendant admonition that this is an `important question’ awaiting `serious analysis’ (118n5) has become a kind of gospel, recited by others [...] with increasing confidence, but with very little to show as yet in terms of substantiation. Yet, all this while, dozens of ‘histories of German Indology’ are built on the—still unfulfilled—promises of that gospel.”

In his researches, GrünendahlGrünendahl (2012:194) has checked Rhys-Davids’ writings and discovered a telling example of how the racialist “NS” worldview was already present in Britain earlier:

“However, a more important factor seems to me to be Rhys Davids’s racialist—or more precisely Aryanist—biasbias, documented, for example, in statements to the effect that Gautama BuddhaGautama Buddha ‘was the only man of our own race, the only Aryan, who can rank as the founder of a great religion’ and that therefore ‘the whole intellectual and religious development of which BuddhismBuddhism is the final outcome was distinctively Aryan, and Buddhism is the one essentially Aryan faith’ (1896:185), which ‘took its rise among an advancing and conquering people full of pride in their colour and their race... ‘(1896:187).”

But Pollock (1993:94) has a point when he notes that a number of Indologists were NS party members or SS officials, e.g. Walther WüstWüst, Walther, Erich FrauwallnerFrauwallner, Erich, Jakob HauerHauer, Jakob, Richard SchmidtSchmidt, Richard. He estimates these as one-third of the Indology professors. He admits that there was a silent opposition too, e.g. when Wüst became board member of the Deutsche Morgenländische GesellschaftDeutsche Morgenländische Gesellschaft (“German Oriental SocietyGerman Oriental Society”), “the aged Geiger [= Wilhelm Geiger, Wüst’s mentor] objected privately to the behavior of Wüst.” (Pollock 1993:123) And that may have been the tip of an iceberg, though we will not hazard a guess on the proportion of open resisters, silent resisters, fence-sitters and collaborators.

Functionalism

Pollock gives the impression of a rather shaky grasp on NS history. It is, after all, not his field. Rather than properly delving into it in preparation of this ambitious paper, he seems to have gone by the received wisdom prevalent in his own liberal circles. The charitable explanation is that, not being a historian of WW2, he simply overstepped the boundaries of his competence. The alternative is that he deliberately forged this claim about Indology and National-SocialismNational-Socialism as a weapon, in this case against the Sanskrit tradition. Some popular writers (e.g. Pennick 1981) have indeed done something similar, often after classifying Hindu ideas like reincarnation in the “occult” category. They have correctly sensed the windfall of benefits, whether political or commercial, guaranteed to whomever manages to instrumentalize references to National-SocialismNational-Socialism.

He claims that “the exterminationextermination of the Jews would seem to pose a serious challenge to any purely functionalistfunctionalist explanation of National Socialism.” (Pollock 1993:88) Perhaps there was still some room for doubt in 1993, and though marginal, the hypothesis of “intentionalismintentionalism/intentionalist”,hypothesis!intentionalism viz. that the genocidegenocide of the Jews was planned since the beginning of the Nazi movement, was still in existence in erudite company. This hypothesis would imply, in a maximalist interpretation (viz. that any supporter of National-Socialism wilfully supported all of its programme), that NS Indologists like Fauwallner or Hauer supported “genocide”.

Strictly speaking, Hindus have no reason to defend these Indologists, for none of them was Hindu, and they projected a non-Hindu NS framework onto Hindu textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic). Given the complexity of the reasons for a man’s inclinations, their interest in the Sanskrit traditions implies nothing at all about the Sanskrit tradition itself. Nevertheless, it is worth observing that even if these scholars were party members, this does not mean they supported genocidegenocide, for that item was not on the party programme. Anti-Semitismanti-Semitism is bad (and of that, they can certainly be held guilty) but genocidegenocide is something else again. Even when it was later decided upon, it was still carried out in secrecy because the top Nazis knew that it would offend the German population including many party members.

Today, no historian worth his salt takes this intentionalismintentionalism/intentionalist serious anymore, though it lives on in Hollywood stereotyping. Apart from being unsupported by facts, intentionalism also sins against the reigning postmodernist canon by being “essentialistessentialist”, i.e. positing an irreducible unchanging nature to NS ideology; when even that turns out to be historical and changeble under the impact of circumstances. The “functionalistfunctionalist” hypothesishypothesis!functional has won the day, viz. that the idea of genocidegenocide only came about in a chain of unforeseen decisions under war circumstances in 1940-41. Even then it was carried out in secrecy: as late as 1943, Jewish CouncilsJewish!Councils in occupied countries co-operated in the deportation of their own community, thinking AuschwitzAuschwitz was merely a labour camp. You could be a NS party member and support the idea of a Jew-free Europe (through emigration, as had happened in the 1930s) yet not support nor even know about genocidegenocide. To be sure, ethnic cleansingethnic cleansing is reprehensible too, but it is not genocidegenocide. Scholars ought to exercise a sense of proportion.

For political campaigners living in the relative comforts of the post-war era, it is easy to laugh at the German commoners’ 1945 profession: Wir haben das nicht gewusst (“We didn’t know about it”); but very often, it was formally the truth. Again, supporting the NS regime was bad enough; but it was something else than support for genocidegenocide. Pollock, voracious quoter that he is, can at any rate not cite any NS Indologist as expressing support for genocidegenocide.

But suppose, just suppose, that tomorrow, an incriminating statement by one of those Indologists gets discovered. Well, he is a human being, susceptible to all kinds of influences, not just those from his field of specialism. It would then still remain to be proven that the Sanskrit tradition which he studied, had given him this inspiration for genocidegenocide. Sanskrit writers can be accused of teaching inequality through castecaste!inequality, and Pollock does indeed do so, but it has not been quoted here (nor, as far as is known, anywhere else) that the VedasVeda or Śāstras preach genocidegenocide.

Now, if Vedic literature ever enjoined (not even just recounted, but actually enjoined) genocidegenocide, there is no doubt that the Dalit movement, the missionariesmissionaries, the “secularistssecularists”, the KhalistanisKhalistanis, the many anti-Hinduanti-Hindu India-watchersIndia-watchers see anti-Hindu, and perhaps Pollock himself, would gleefully quote it. Not that they ever quote the instances of genocidegenocide in the Bible or in the traditions about Mohammed, but for HinduismHinduism they would not be that polite. Indeed, it would have been logical to quote it very prominently in this very paper, as it would prove its entire point. But it seems not to exist.

Anti-Semitism and the Sanskrit Traditionanti-Semitism

While genocidegenocide entered the mind of some top Nazis only by 1941, another element always associated with the NS ideology was intrinsic to it since the beginning, and very prominent in its writings since ca. 1920 and in policies since 1933: anti-Semitismanti-Semitism. While Pollock takes as a matter of course that to the Nazis, “Aryan”Aryan!orientalism was the opposite of “SemiticSemitic”, he doesn’t furnish any fact or quote at all that would meaningfully link this with the Sanskrit tradition.

He correctly notes that the NS view of the VedasVeda was through an anti-Semitic lens:

“The Ŗg-Veda as an AryanAryan!orientalism text ‘free of any taint of Semitic contact’; the ‘almost Nordic zeal’Nordic!zeal that lies in the BuddhistBuddhist conception of the marga [way]; the ‘Indo-Germanic religion-force’ of yoga; the sense of raceNordic!race and the ‘conscious desire for racial protection’; the ‘volksnahe kingship’volksnahe kingship such is the meaning of the Indo-Aryan past for the National Socialist present, a present that, for Wüst, could not be understood without this past.” (Pollock 1993:89)

Yes, that is how the Nazis saw it because they were racist and anti-Semitic to begin with. But the knowledge of the Sanskrit tradition could add absolutely nothing to that. There was nothing in the VedasVeda themselves that suggested anti-Semitism, it was entirely in the eye of the beholder. Anti-Semitismanti-Semitism existed in Europe ever since the people became convinced, through Christianity, that the JewsJews had been responsible for Jesus’ death. Modern nationalism added an ideal of homogenizationhomogenization, so that JewsJews were wished away as an obstacle to this ideal. By contrast, Vedic literatureVedic literature doesn’t know of Jews at all, and Hindu history has only shown a pluralistic hospitality for the Jewish communities on the Malabar coast, complete with their distinctive traditions.

In fact, that pluralismpluralism and respect for different identities could be cited as a redeeming feature of the caste systemcaste!system targeted so systematically by Pollock. Hindu reformers, who deny the intimate link between caste and HinduismHinduism during the past twenty or so centuries, are wrong. But they might start by enumerating some redeeming features, such as the sense of belonging-to (rather than of being-excluded-from), and pluralism. Within the caste framework, nobody’s comfort or identity was threatened when a foreign community was added. At any rate, the really existing caste system did not include anti-Semitismanti-Semitism.

The only thing Pollock can come up with here, in a footnote, is this: “The ratio ārya : caṇḍālacaṇḍāla [outcaste, untouchable] :: German : Jew was made already by Nietzsche”. (Pollock 1993:119) Friedrich Nietzsche was popular among top Nazis, but they read him selectively, leaving out the positions that would not have endeared him to an NS regime. He disliked German nationalism and especially anti-Semitismanti-Semitism as, at least, vulgar.

Nevertheless, it is true that Nietzsche (Twilight of the IdolsTwilight of the Idols: The ‘Improvers’ of Mankind 3) speculated on the Jews’ origin as emigrated Caṇḍālas, Untouchables, based on more speculations by the amateur-Indologist Louis JacolliotJacolliot, Louis. We have discussed this question in full detail elsewhere (Elst 2008), but briefly, it all hinges on the mistranslation of the word dauścarmyadauścarmya, “having a skin defect”, from the enumeration of Caṇḍāla traits in the classical law code Manu Smṛti (10:52, but based on 11:49). This word was understood as “missing a piece of skin”, hence “circumcised”. In reality, Manu nowhere mentions circumcised ones, whether Jews or Muslims.

Moreover, Nietzsche’s account doesn’t fit the neat scheme given by Pollock. Nietzsche recognized that in some ways, Jews do not fit the dirty and submissive stereotype of outcastes at all, and have been characterized by AryanAryan!orientalism traits ever since their entry into history. They ennobled themselves by becoming warriors and conquering their “promised land”. They are stereotypically very money-savvy, like the trader caste, and their obsessive purity rules and book-orientedness remind one of the Brahmin caste. Whereas Untouchables do the dirty work at funerals, Jewish priests or Kohanim are expected to stay away from corpses. Jews were demonized by the Nazis, but not as low-castescaste!inequality.

Unlike the stereotype of Caṇḍālas (more applicable to the Gypsies, known to descend from Indian low-castescaste!inequality and despised by the Nazis), the Jews were considered as rich, powerful, manipulative and extremely clever. Jews definitely did not relate to Germans the way Hindu low-castescaste!inequality relate to the upper castescaste!inequality. And anyway, the NS policy regarding the Jews was not based on this Nietzsche quote.

The “Aryan” homeland questionAryan!homeland

The official birth of Indo-European linguistics by William Jones’sJones, William famous Kolkata speech in 1786 (set on a scientific footing by Franz BoppBopp, Franz in 1816, as recognized by Pollock 1993:84) set in motion the search for the original homeland of this language family. The initial favourite was India, as famously stated by Friedrich von SchlegelSchlegel, Friedrich von (cited by Pollock 1993:85). In the present context, it might be a significant detail that Schlegel “married the daughter of the Jewish philosopher Moses Mendelssohn”, for which he was reproached as “missing racial instinct”. (PoliakovPoliakov, Léon 1971:217) Many other scholars from this period can be cited to the same effect, e.g. in 1810, Jakob-Joseph Görres had Abraham come from Kashmir. (PoliakovPoliakov, Léon 1971:219)

In the next decades, the putative homeland was relocated westwards, but Pollock (1993:77) claims that the Germans “continued, however subliminally, to hold the nineteenth-century conviction that the origin of European civilization was to be found in India (or at least that India constituted a genetically related sibling)”.

This insinuates that the Nazis still believed in an Indian homeland whereas the British and their allies had long converted to the idea of a more westerly homeland. This much is true, that the NS state was intensely interested in the question of Indo-European origins: Communist states “employ myths of utopia, while fascist systems employ myths of origins”. (Pollock 1993:85) But then, Pollock artfully smuggles in a continuity between the earlier Out-of-India hypothesishypothesis!Out of India and the preferred NS location of the homeland. The NS state’s legitimation by “Aryan” origins “had been provided early in nineteenth-century Indian orientalism; a benchmark is Friedrich von Schlegel'sSchlegel, Friedrich von identification (1819) of the ‘ArierArier’ as ‘our Germanic ancestors, while they were still in Asia’ (SieferleSieferle R P 1987:460). In the later NS search for authenticity, Sanskritists, like other intellectuals ‘experts in legitimation’, as GramsciGramsci, Antonio put it, did their part in extrapolating and deepening this discourse.” (Pollock 1993:85; Antonio Gramsci was the Italian Communist leader who, ca. 1930, theorized the acquisition of cultural hegemony as a prerequisite for political revolution.)

Note also this adroit suggestion of Indian paternity in this quotation from the NS Indologist Walther Wüst:

“I know of no more striking example of this hereditary, long-term tradition than the ingenious synopsis contained in the brief words of the Führer and the longer confession of the great aryan personality of antiquity, the BuddhaGautama Buddha. There is only one explanation for this, and that is the basic explanation for components of the National-Socialist world-view: the circumstance, the basic fact of racial constitutionracial!constitution. And thanks to fate, this was preserved through the millennia... [through] the holy concept of ancestral heritage [AhnenerbeAhnenerbe].”(Pollock: 1993:90)

Note that in all Pollock’s quotations from NS Indologists, only one Hindu is mentioned by name, repeatedly: the Buddha. He tries to make the Mīmāṁsā thinkers with their chiseling of Śāstra law into an inspiration to the Nazis (as if they needed Mīmāṁsā to conceive of inequality), but never manages to find a Nazi quote about them. None, for example, about the 12th-century Śāstra commentator Bhaṭṭa LakṣmīdharaBhaṭṭa Lakṣmidhara, whom he himself drags in frequently as justifying societal hierarchy. On the other hand he presents the Buddha as an antidote to Vedic inequality, yet that same Buddha turns out to be very popular among the Nazis.

There was no NS belief in an Indian homeland at all, on the contrary. To be sure, there was a belief in a racial kinship with the ancient “Aryans”Aryan!homeland in India, freshly invaded from their more westerly homeland. Of NordicNordic!race origin, these Aryans brought their talents into India and gave expression to them in ancient writings, and these naturally showed a kinship with Greek thought and other “Aryan” achievements in Europe.

Thus, NS Indologist Erich FrauwallnerFrauwallner, Erich says, in Pollock’s account (Pollock 1993:93):

“Frauwallner argued that the special meaning of Indian philosophy lay in its being ‘a typical creation of an aryan people’, that its similarities with western philosophy derived from ‘the same racially determined talent’, and that it was a principal scholarly task of Indology to d emonstrate this fact. Reiterating an axiom of NS doctrine, that ‘WissenschaftWissenschaft in the strict sense of the word is something that could be created only by nordic Indo-Germans’, Frauwallner adds, ‘From the agreement in scientific character of Indian and European philosophy, we can draw the further conclusion that philosophy as an attempt to explain the world according to scientific method is likewise a typical creation of the Aryan mind.’"

India was important to the Nazis not because they saw it as their ancestral land (they did not), but because it illustrated the Nazi worldview:

dynamic white Aryans enter the land of indolent dark people;
they subjugate them in a racially-conceived caste system,caste!systema kind of Apartheidapartheid;
in spite of trying for racial purity, they succumb too often to the charms of native women, so they racially degenerate; and therefore,
they ended up overpowered by whiter races, first the TurksTurks and then, mercifully, their own purer AryanAryan!homeland cousins from Britain.

Since the mid-19th century, this worldview had already been promoted by Britain, meanwhile it had been fortified by the ascendence of DarwinismDarwinism (“struggle for life”, “survival of the fittest”) and finally acquired an extra intensity in NS Germany.

In the first years of the renewed debate on the Indo-European homeland, it was a common confusion that the Out-of-India theoryOut-of-India Theory, disappeared after SchlegelSchlegel, Friedrich von but now back in strength, had something NS about it, e.g. Zydenbos 1993. This confusion was deliberately fostered by some Indian “secularists”secularists trying to criminalize the Indian homeland hypothesishypothesis!Indian homeland, e.g. SikandSikand, Yoginder 1993. In reality, the NS theorists as well as the NS textbooks emphasized and highlighted the putative European homeland and concomitant invasion into India. Zydenbos and Sikand themselves were in Hitler’sHitler!Adolf camp.

The confusion centred on the word Aryan, of Sanskrit origin. In NS discourse, this was routinely interpreted in a racial sense, though raceNordic!race was here not just skin colour but also had a cultural component. Thus, both Sanskrit and German could only be such precise and structured languages because they emanated from racially predisposed nations (and the “degeneration” of Sanskrit to the much looser modern Indian languages is thus a consequence of racial degeneration). In vulgar propaganda, the linguistic, cultural and biological dimensions were completely confounded, but this even influenced high-brow discourse:

“An example of this more sophisticated orientalism is the work of Paul ThiemeThieme, Paul”, Harvard Sanskritist Michael Witzel’s revered teacher, esp. his “analysis of the Sanskrit word ārya, where at the end he adverts to the main point of his research: to go beyond India in order to catch the ‘distant echo of Indo-germanicIndo-germanic customs’.” (Pollock 1993:91)

From Adolf Hitler’sHitler!Adolf mouth, no words in praise of HinduismHinduism are known. A few expressions of contempt, yes, e.g. Subhas Bose’sBose, Subhas Chandra army: “Hitler himself ridiculed the 3000-man strong regiment of Indians.” (HartogHartog, Rudolf 2001:iii) But there is one statement of importance in the present context. Among Hitler’s rare utterances on the Hindus was a racial interpretation of the AIT. These are his own words (Jäckel & KuhnJäckel & Kuhn 1980:195, quoting Hitler 1920):

“Wir wissen, dass die Hindu in Indien ein Volk sind, gemischt aus den hochstehenden arischen Einwanderern und der dunkelschwarzen Urbevölkerung, und dass dieses Volk heute die folgen trägt; denn es ist auch das Sklavenvolk einer Rasse, die uns in vielen Punkten nahezu als zweite Judenheit erscheinen darf.” (“We know that the Hindus in India are a people mixed from the lofty AryanAryan!homeland immigrants and the dark-black aboriginal populationaboriginal population, and that this people is bearing the consequences today; for it is also the slave people of a race that almost seems like a second Jewry.”)

For GrünendahlGrünendahl, this is merely an example of how the primary sources of German history contradict the free-for-all that amateurs make of it. JosephJoseph, Tony (2016) dismisses Grünendahl’s many factual data as only to be expected from a “German”, an ad hominem against a whole nation, as well as a covert admission that he cannot refute even one of them. Grünendahl (2012:196) had noted the same inability in an earlier Pollock defender, Vishwa AdluriAdluri, Vishwa (2011): when challenging the many facts mustered by Grünendahl, Adluri neither shows Grünendahl’s data to be incorrect, nor does he bring other facts proving Pollock’s case: “a pitiable want of judgment as well as evidence.”

But the objective finality of Pollock’s thesis is more specific, viz. to blacken the Indian homeland hypothesishypothesis!Indian homeland by associating it with National-Socialism. Reality, however, is just the opposite: more even than other Europeans, the Nazis espoused and upheld a westerly homeland and the invasion hypothesishypothesis!invasion. This invasion happens to be a corner-stone of Pollock’s worldview, with invader castescaste!invader c. guilty of expropriating and subjugating the natives, who became the lower castes. HitlerHitler!Adolf-Pollock, same struggle!

To end this discussion on an element of nuance, however, we have to note an odd passage.Though Pollock repeatedly affirms NS belief in what is nowadays called the Out-of-India theory,Out-of-India Theory and assumes this throughout his paper, honesty demands that we mention how one time, very cursorily, he nods to the opposite (and true) scenario:

“From among the complexities of NS analysis of the Urheimat questionUrheimat!question it is worth calling attention to the way the nineteenth-century view expressed by SchlegelSchlegel, Friedrich von was reversed: the original Indo-Europeans were now variously relocated in regions of the Greater German ReichGreater German Reich; German thereby became the language of the core (Binnensprache), whereas Sanskrit was transformed into one of its peripheral, ‘colonial’ forms.” (Pollock 1993: 91-92)

Even this is not entirely true, for the dominant opinion was that the homeland was to the east or southeast of Germany, while even the SS research department AhnenerbeAhnenerbe explored locating the homeland in AtlantisAtlantis: fanciful, but at least outside Germany. Still, Pollock’s statement does justice to the NS worldview by denying India the honour of being the homeland. It explains why we often see a shift in the focus of NS Indologists from India to “Indo-European” or “Aryan”Aryan!homeland issues, racially identified with NordicNordic. Thus, in 1934 Jakob HauerHauer, Jakob still wrote on “Indo-Aryan” metaphysics of struggle, but in 1937 he published on the religious history of the “Indo-Europeans”. Pollock’s own enumeration of supposedly India-related activities usually confuses “Indian” with “Indo-European”, i.e. “Aryan” or essentially “Nordic”. It is only by confusing those two that an impression of a NS orientation towards India can be created.

National-Socialism and the Sanskrit tradition

Two factors of a seeming connection between HinduismHinduism and NS Germany are unavoidable: the swastikaswastika and the term āryaārya. About the swastika, the matter is simple: it does not come from India. It is a more widespread symbol, very prominent e.g. in Troy, excavated by a German, and part of Greek history which was a decisive inspiration to Germany’s academic culture. It was also very common in the Baltic area, where German army veterans formed Freikorps militias to defeat the Bolsheviks in 1918-20. When they came home, often to join nationalist parties, they brought the swastika with them. (More detail in Elst 2007) The NS view was that it was Nordic in origin, and that it only became common in India after having been imported by the AryansAryan!homeland.

As Sünner (1999:66) puts it: “the hooked cross, which the Nordic cult of light carried into the Orient”. Indeed, this was part of a general septentriocentric worldviewseptentriocentric worldview: “Unconcerned about historic truth, their builders were termed as ‘Indo-European Urvolk’Indo-European Urvolk and ‘heroes of the North’, who later co-founded the civilizations of Egypt, India and Persia.” (Sünner 1999:60-61) India was not in the picture, except as a distant horizon to be conquered and civilized by Norsemen.

As for AryanAryan!homeland: “The term āryaārya itself merits intellectual-historicalintellectual history study (and I mean diachronic analysis, not static etymology) for premodern India at least of the sort ArierArier has received for modern Europe.” (Pollock 1993:107) True, Hindus too might learn a lot from realizing that this term is historical, that it has gone through changes, and that the classical meaning “noble” (a meaning unattested in the Ŗg-Veda) has mundane roots too. Yet, Pollock does no more than focus on the Manu Smṛti,Manusmṛti fairly late and worn-out as a supposed repository of caste teachings and anti-egalitarian musings about āryaārya vs. anāryaanārya.

Moreover, Pollock (1993: 107-8) brings in the concept of race: “From such factors as the semantic realm of the distinction ārya/anāryaanārya and the biogenetic map of inequalitybiogenetic map of inequality (along with less theorized material, from Vedic and epic literature, for instance), it may seem warranted to speak about a ‘pre-form of racism’ in early India (GeissenGeissen, Imanuel 1988: 48ff.), especially in a discussion of indigenous ‘orientalism’, since in both its classic colonial and its National Socialist form orientalism is inseparable from racism.”

That is certainly the NS reading, but from a top Indologist, we might have expected an explanation of whether this was the Indians’ own intended reading. Pollock doesn’t go into this question at all but confidently assumes an indubitably positive answer. To exonerate him, we might take this as merely a logical application of the Aryan invasion scenario, firmly established since the mid-19th century: the Aryans came in, met a different race of aboriginals, and imposed a racial Apartheidapartheid on them: the caste systemcaste!system. So, in a way, the case against Pollock is the case against Western Indology as a whole.

His arguments about the inequality fostered by the Śāstras thus always has a racial dimension. Caste is too big a subject to argue out here, but let us notice that he has no problem mustering incriminating quotations excluding low-castes from Vedic knowledge. He does acknowledge feeble dissenting voices, such as the early Mīmāṁsā thinker BādariBādari, who argued that Śūdras too can build Vedic fires for sacrifice, since "the Śūdra desires heaven, too (...) and what is it in a sacrifice that any man can do but that the Śūdra is unable to do?" (Pollock 1993:109) But the over-all picture is decidedly inegalitarian. However, inequality is a nearly equally distributed good, and for that value, the Nazis could have found inspiration in other societies, if they needed any at all, such as the Arab or colonial slave systems.

Inequality yes, but racial, no. All this depends on the racial reading of Sanskrit concepts, starting with the enumeration of four social functions (without a word about how to recruit for them) in late-Vedic hymn RV 10.90, “the locus classicus in the Veda”Veda for caste division. Even “the biology” is said to be “of course latent in the RV passage”, though he does not say how and other readers cannot find a trace of it. (Pollock 1993:125) All this follows from the Aryan invasion scenario, and on this point, there is no chance of refuting Pollock unless the homelandAryan!homeland| debate is waged all over.

At any rate, none of these interesting musings about Indian society played any role whatsoever in NS policies. Pollock (1993:86-87) is only projecting his own focus when his Indologist’s eye recognizes caste phenomena in NS policies:

“The myth of Aryan origins burst from the world of dream into that of reality when the process of what I suggest we think of as an internal colonizationcolonization of Europe began to be, so to speak, shastrically codified, within two months of the National Socialists' capturing powerpower!political (April 1933). The ‘Law on the Reconstitution of the German Civil Service’, the ‘Law on the Overcrowding of German Schools’, and a host of supplementary laws and codicils of that same month were the first in a decade dense with legal measures designed to exclude Jews and other minority communities from the apparatuses of power (including ‘authoritative’ power, the schools and universities), and to regulate a wide range of social, economic, and biological activities.”

Finally, another point of difference between NS racismNS racism and caste societycaste!society is this. The relation between the Germans and the “inferior” races was conceived as hierarchical, but the NS conception of German society was not as a hierarchy: all members of the master race were deemed reasonably equal. HitlerHitler!Adolf himself had climbed up from down below; there was no objection against social mobility. Germans were not to be held inside the class they happened to be born into, unlike the low-caste Hindus in Pollock’s oft-stated view.

In this connection, Hitler himself objected to the idea of a hereditary priesthoodhereditary priesthood. Though he doesn’t name it, this could be applied to the Brahmin caste: “The Catholic ChurchCatholic church recruits its clergy in principle from all classes of society, without discrimination. A simple cowherd can become cardinal. That is why the Church remains combattive.” (Pierik 2012:83, quoting Hitler’s table talk of 2 November 1941) So, even in his anti-Brahminismanti-Brahminism, Pollock finds himself in Hitler’s camp.

The banalization of criminalizing HinduismHinduismHinduism!criminalizing

In his conclusion, Pollock digresses about the future of his scholarly discipine. There, he takes for granted the connection he has earlier posited between Sanskrit and the Holocaustholocaust!Nazi. In an entirely non-polemical tone, he off-hand builds on this putative connection: “How, concretely, does one do Indology beyond the Raj and Auschwitz in a world of pretty well tattered scholarly paradigms?” (Pollock 1993:114)

In the process of disinformationdisinformation, an idea is first launched and argued in high-brow papers like the New York ReviewNew York Review or the Economic and Political WeeklyEconomic and Political Weekly; subsequently it is presented as the received wisdom in more general media, like the Washington PostWashington Post or the Times of India; but the final stage is when the idea is presented as a matter of course, and conveyed through popular media, women’s magazines etc. That is what completes the instilling of false ideas in the popular mind.

Similarly, to promote an idea intended to become a fixture in our worldview, it is useful to repeat it, first as a topical proposal to be proven, then as a theorem deemed to have been proven, finally as a truism on which other proposals can safely be built.

Yet, we don’t hold Pollock as an individual guilty of this disinformation. Though his authoritative voice does its bit to determine the Zeitgeist, he was mainly surfing on an already-existing Zeitgeist.

Firstly, the tendency to project the Naziholocaust!Nazi episode onto something morbid and unique in the more distant German past, and particularly the exoticizationexoticization of 19th-century Germany’s supposed self-doubt and search for an identity, was already very common in the preceding decades (e.g. PoliakovPoliakov, Léon 1971), and still is to some extent.

Secondly, the link between HinduismHinduism (as well as LamaismLamaism) and Naziholocaust!Nazi culture had already been proposed by a number of writers. Moreover, it converges with a widespread revulsion among Westerners against the caste systemcaste!system, which they liken to slavery and identify, through the Aryan invasionAryan!Invasion Theory hypothesishypothesis!invasion, with racism. This misses the warlike element in National-Socialism, but that is slightly made up for by all the stories about Hindu riots and by the symmetry fallacysymmetry fallacy whenever Muslim violence comes in the news: “Ah, but all religions do it; HinduismHinduism must have a similar terrorism.” Even then, it still doesn’t have the element of “genocidegenocide”, but Pollock remains determined to read that into it.

Conclusion

It is one thing to hold a view that, upon analysis, turns out to be mistaken. To err is but human. However, one should become extra careful when the view one expresses, is an allegation. It becomes even more serious when it is the worst allegation one can possibly make, viz. the accusation of responsibility for the Holocaustholocaust!Nazi.

The situation with allegations is simple: either you prove them, or you yourself are guilty of slander. This then can be held against Pollock: he has made a grave allegation, yet has failed to buttress it with proof, though not for lack of trying.

The question which Hindus should contemplate, then, is this one. Should the Sanskrit tradition be given in care to a professor of Sanskrit who stands by such a grave though false allegation against it?

Bibliography

Adluri, Vishwa (2011) “Pride and prejudice: Orientalism and German Indology”, International Journal of Hindu Studies, 15, p.253--294.
Adluri, Vishwa and Bagchee, Joydeep, (2014) The Nay Science, A History of German Indology. New York: Oxford University Press.
Breckenridge, Carol A., and Van der Veer, Peter, (Eds.) (1993) Orientalism and the Postcolonial Predicament: Perspectives on South Asia. University of Pennsylvania Press.
Elst, Koenraad (2007) Return of the Swastika. Delhi: Voice of India.
Elst, Koenraad (2008) “Manu as a Weapon against Egalitarianism: Nietzsche and Hindu Political Philosophy”, in Siemens & Roodt (2008), p.543--582.
Elst, Koenraad (2012) “The Case for Orientalism”, in The Argumentative Hindu. Essays by a Non-Affiliated Orientalist. Delhi: Voice of India. p.442--455.
Geissen, Imanuel (1988) Geschichte des Rassismus. Frankfurt: Suhrkamp.
Grünendahl, Reinhold (2012): “History in the making: on Sheldon Pollock’s ‘NS Indology’ and Vishwa Adluri’s ‘Pride and prejudice’”. International Journal of Hindu Studies no.16, p.189--252.
Hartog, Rudolf (2001) The Sign of the Tiger. Subhas Chandra Bose and his Indian Legion in Germany, 1941--45. Delhi: Rupa.
Irwin, Robert (2006) For Lust of Knowing: the Orientalists and Their Enemies. London: Allan Lane.
Hale, Christopher (2003) Himmler’s Crusade. The true story of the 1938 Nazi expedition into Tibet. London: Bantam.
Hauer, Jakob Wilhelm (1934) Eine indo-arische Metaphysik des Kampfes und der Tat: Die Bhagavad Gita in neuer Sicht. Stuttgart: Kohlhammer.
Hauer, Jakob Wilhelm (1937) Glaubensgeschichte der Indogermanen, Vol.1. Stuttgart: Kohlhammer.
Hitler, Adolf (1920) “Warum sind wir Antisemiten?”, in Jäckel & Eberhard (1980), p.184--204.
Jäckel, Eberhard, and Kuhn, Axel, (Eds.) (1980) Hitlers sämtliche Aufzeichnungen, 1905--1924
Joseph, Tony (2016) “Battle against Pollock”. Business Standard. Delhi, 3 May 2016.
Malhotra, Rajiv (2015) The Battle for Sanskrit. Is Sanskrit Political or Sacred? Oppressive or Liberating? Dead or Alive?. Delhi: HarperCollins.
Marchand, Suzanne (2009) German Orientalism in the Age of Empire - Religion, Race and Scholarship. Washington DC/New York: German Historical Institute and Cambridge University Press.
Paranjape, Makarand R. (2016) “The deepest Orientalist”. Business Standard. Delhi, 29 April 2016.
Pennick, Nigel (1981) Hitler’s Secret Sciences. Suffolk: Nevile Spearmen.
Pierik, Perry, (Ed.), (2012, 1980^1) Hitlers Tafelgesprekken 1941-44 (“Hitler’s Table Talk”), Soesterberg: Aspekt.
Poliakov, Léon (1987, 1971^1) Le Mythe Aryen. Essai sur les Sources du Racisme et des Nationalismes. Paris: Editions Complexe.
Pollock, Sheldon (1993) “Deep Orientalism? Notes on Sanskrit and power beyond the Raj”, in Breckenridge & Van der Veer (1993), p.76--133.
Quinn, Malcolm (1994) The Swastika. Constructing the Symbol. London: Routledge.
Rhys Davids, Thomas William (1896) Buddhism: Its History and Literature. London: G.P. Putnam’s Sons (American Lectures on the History of Religions, First Series, 1894--1895).
Rhys Davids, Thomas William (1903-4) “Oriental Studies in England and Abroad”, Proceedings of the British Academy. London. pp.183--97.
Said, Edward (1995, 1978^1) Orientalism. London: Penguin.
Schlegel, Friedrich (1808) Über die Sprache und Weisheit der Indier. Heidelberg: Mohr.
Sieferle, Rolf Peter (1987) ``Indien und die Arier in der Rassentheorie". Zeitschrift für Kulturaustausch 37, pp.444--67.
Siemens, Herman, and Roodt, Vasti, (Eds.) (2008) Nietzsche. Power and Politics. Berlin: Walter de Gruyter.
Sikand, Yoginder (1993) “Exploding the Aryan myth”. Observer of Business and Politics, 30-10-1993.
Sünner, Rüdiger (1999) Schwarze Sonne. Entfesselung und Missbrauch der Mythen in Nationalsozialismus und rechter Esoterik. Freiburg im Breisgau: Herder Spektrum.
Thieme, Paul (1938) Der Fremdling im Rigveda. Leipzig: Brockhaus.
Warraq, Ibn (2007) Defending the West. A Critique of Edward Said’s Orientalism. Amherst NY: Prometheus.
Zydenbos, Robert (1993) “An obscurantist argument”, Indian Express, 12-12-1993.

Chapter 4 “Sanskrit is dead'', and that’s okay

Naresh P. Cuntoor

Abstract

In this paper a critical review of Pollock’s hypothesis of the deathdeath of Sanskrit is presented. Using a tenuous analogy with European languages and history, his hypothesis advocates Sanskrit’s symbiotic relationshipsymbiotic relationship with royal power as a means of ensuring power. It claims that Indian kings exploited aspects of Sanskrit such as grammargrammar and śleṣa to enhance their politicalpower!political status. In turn, royal patronagepatronage is said to favor Sanskrit over vernacular languages. As a result Sanskrit enjoyed a dominant status until vernacularvernacular languages grew in strength and acceptability. This narrative, he avers, is inspired by the European history of cosmopolis in attempting to establish a similar status for Sanskrit, and later for Kannada.Kannada Once Sanskrit ceded ground to vernacular languages, it faced precipitous decline to face death by the turn of 17th century CE, despite valiant revival effortsrevival effortsSanskrit!revival of made by the Muslim rulersMuslim!rulers in northern India, and later by the English colonialists, he opines. Further, Sanskrit’s death is considered insignificant by him because there was little original knowledge production in Sanskrit as it is. I shall describe several instances of empirical data being sacrificed seemingly because of the necessities of narrative-building. The paper raises a few questions for discussion as part of future work.

Introduction

One of the foundational languages of Indian civilization, Sanskrit continues to have a deep and wide influence in today’s India through language, culture and science. Its reach in all these dimensions have long transcended geographical boundariesgeographical!boundary of the Indian subcontinent. Lulled perhaps by the deep and continuing influence of Sanskrit or the self-evident nature of Sanskrit, Indian scholarship has failed to articulate the position of Sanskrit with sufficient clarity. Even when its position has been articulated in a manner which defies belief and evidence (Pollock 2006), the arguments have not been addressed thoroughly. In this paper, I shall present a critical summary of Pollock’s theory regarding the death of Sanskrit based primarily on the book The Language of the Gods in the World of MenLanguage of the Gods in the World of Men, The (Pollock 2006) and based on “The Death of Sanskrit” (Pollock 2001).

The Language of the Gods in the World of Men, The Language of the Gods in the World of Men as the title suggests, presents the death of Sanskrit, and argues that its death is not a significant loss as far as knowledge is concerned. This is for two main reasons: there was a vigorous exchange of ideas within India and with the larger ancient world. So Indian knowledge, if any, survives in various forms. Second, Indian knowledge, in large measure was non-existent till the advent of the modern era.

This paper is divided into four main sections:

Preliminaries: Here I shall discuss the form of language used in Pollock (2006) and its implications, and present a brief historical background of Greek and LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) development.
Sanskrit as a source of power:Sanskrit!as a source of powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of In this section, the language characteristics that are considered a source of power are described.
Sanskrit cosmopolis:Sanskrit!cosmopolis The concept of cosmopolis and its Sanskrit nature are summarized.
The death of Sanskrit: Finally, the manner of Sanskrit’s death is described.

1 Preliminaries

Before addressing the substance of Pollock’s arguments, his writing style deserves notice. In academic literature, the usage of complicated writing style may be completely natural, even if it is unnecessary. I am reminded of the editor R.H.FiskeFiske, R H (author of the Dictionary of Unendurable EnglishDictionary of Unendurable English) who considered such a style of writing as one that encouraged illiteracy. The reader seeks clarity when startling claims such as the death of Sanskrithypothesis!death of Sanskrit are made. One is interested in understanding the nature of the death being described, and the evidence presented in its support. Redundant words and meaningless tautologies (e.g., “when literature became literature”, Pollock (2006:4) hardly make the writing clear. Style cannot be ignored completely either, especially because Pollock’s writings merit serious consideration by traditional scholars who need to thoroughly understand the arguments before attempting an informed response. Using a convoluted writing styleconvoluted!writing style (as Pollock does) is hardly the best way of conducting a conversation.

It could be argued that making the writings accessible to traditional Indian scholars is the work of others including multilingual Indian scholars. There have been such attempts, e.g., K.V. Akshar’sAkshar, K V monograph in KannadaKannada (Akshar 2003), which describes two of Pollock’s papers that are relevant to the present discussion. At the end of the monograph, P. Chandrashobhi writes an epilogue which re-summarizes Pollock’s arguments and makes mild criticisms at the end. Now this is not to say that writing style is the only (or the main) factor preventing sharper academic discourse. But to the extent that it does, academic discourse has remained limited and bounded to western circles.

I shall now turn to Pollock’s hypothesis regarding the death of Sanskrit. The rather dramatic evocation of ‘death’ has been criticized by HannederHanneder using several examples from Kashmir, VijayanagaraVijayanagara and modern day India to show its untenability. I shall return to the metaphor of death later.

It is instructive to see a few examples of the immediate impact of Pollock’s work. Academic work by influential scholars inevitably creates amplifying echoes. For instance, even the title of Kaviraj(2005)Kaviraj, Sudipta makes it more dramatic by calling it “the sudden death.” The arguments quickly become accepted as “compelling” accounts of the “Sanskrit Cosmopolis” (CoxCox, Whitney 2011). The theory once completely accepted, becomes a foundation for further theorizing. Further work (GouldGould, Rebecca 2008) unabashedly praise the theory and its proponent as “brilliant”, “great” and in even more effusive terms which seem jarring in academic papers. These papers are mentioned as illustrative examples of how Pollock’s arguments have quickly become accepted theory (notwithstanding a few critical academic reviews). The theory never makes a pretense of being a hypothesishypothesishypothesis!death of Sanskrit that needs to be justified and vetted by knowledgeable peers. (Hypotheses are subject to empirical scrutiny. Those that withstand scrutiny become theories. Hypotheses that are contradicted by data are discarded. This norm seems to have been completely ignored in the present case).

Background: Greek and LatinGreekLatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church)

No discussion of the history of the West can ignore the importance of ancient Greece because of its contribution in the development of literature, science, rule of law and so on. In this section, I shall briefly summarize the history of Greek and Latin based on the description in FreemanFreeman, Charles (2004). In this paper, the description is superficial because the goal is limited to providing a comparative basis for the description of Sanskrit that follows.

The Greek or Hellenic ideal is perhaps best personified by Homer’sHomer epics the IliadIliad and the OdysseyOdyssey. Homer described the importance of virtue in citizens and its necessity for developing virtuous city-states. The Hellenic idealHellenic ideal placed great emphasis on virtue in all aspects of human life. At this stage of civilization, Greece was a collection of city-states (poleis). The Greek city-states retained their separate identity despite their close connection, as exemplified in Herodotus’Herodotus characterization of “the same stock and the same speech, our shared temples of the gods and religious rituals, our similar customs.”temple!customs

Among the Greek city-states, two groups of people, the Spartans and the Athenians are important because of their strength. Rivalry between the two groups resulted in the Peloponnesian WarPeloponnesian War in the 5th c. BCE in which AthensAthens was destroyed. Sparta emerged victorious as the pre-eminent force in the region. Shortly thereafter, the nature of city-states saw a dramatic change. Following long and persistent wars, the city-states could not live up to their earlier ideal. After seeing his own teacher murdered, even Plato saw a need for a reformulation of the idea of democracy.democracy City-states lost their identity and the new political entity that took their place was larger. Citizens, whose virtues were earlier celebrated, now became subjects. Greek became the common language (Koine)Koine. This was the nature of the GreekGreek cosmopoliscosmopolis which began around the time of Alexander’s death. Power and subjugation may be said to defining characteristics of the newly evolved cosmopolis.

About a century after Alexander,Alexander the Punic WarsPunic Wars were a series of three large wars between Rome and Carthage.Carthage During the course of these wars, Rome gradually established its supremacy, became the new dominant empire and absorbed Greece (among several other parts of Europe and Africa) within it. With Roman victory, Latin spread and became the common language in the empire. A language that was earlier largely confined to central Italy, Latin gradually became the dominant language of large parts of Europe and Africa - especially the western Mediterranean. Regions that previously had no common language became linguistically connected by Latin.

On the other hand, in eastern MediterraneanMediterranean (e.g., Syria, Egypt) the Roman EmpireRoman empire built strategic alliances with local kingdoms instead of establishing their own rule. In these regions, Greek had a much deeper root and would maintain its preeminence till the arrival of Islam. In this region, Latin did not make significant inroads compared to its western counterpart.

With the fall of the Roman Empire in 5th century CE, Latin lost its political backing. Lacking central control, regional variations took hold in Latin over the next 4-5 centuries. This phase of Latin, marked by its non-standard nature, is called Vulgar Latin.Latin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) Gradually different branches of Vulgar Latin evolved into Romance languagesRomance languages (the term refers to their Roman origin). These became today’s French, Spanish, Portuguese and other European languagesEuropean!languages. During this period of evolution of Vulgar Latin, another form of Latin, called Medieval Latin evolved mostly as a literary language. Its grammargrammar and syntax changed significantly as it had now become a scholarly language, rather than a spoken language. During the middle Ages, its usage declined further, as Romance languages began to flourish. Around this time, in the 13th century CE, DanteDante made a clean break, shunned the use of (Medieval) Latin which had become a language of the educated, and used Italian, the language of the masses, to compose poetry. Church Latin however, continued to be used in liturgy.liturgy

Thus Latin,Latin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) which began as a language in a small region in Italy, acquired dominant status with Roman victories and became the common language of the Roman Empire - especially in the western part of the empire. It did not (possibly could not) seek to displace or challenge the position of Greek in eastern Mediterranean. The eastern empire which became the Byzantine EmpireByzantine Empire continued to use Greek even though the official languageofficial language was Latin. (Latin’s official status in the Byzantine Empire was abolished in 7th c. CE, restoring Greek’s status). Much of this region would eventually yield to Islamic influence. In the western region, Latin eventually evolved into Romance languages because of a lack of central control.

2. Sanskrit as a Source of Powerpowerpower!Sanskrit as a source of

A recurring theme in Pollock (2006) is identification (or superimposition) of events in time that are marked by profound changes in the premodern Indian (South Asian) landscape. The terms “premodern India”premodern!India and “premodern South Asia”premodern!South Asia are used interchangeably, although the latter seems to be the preferred term in Pollock (2006) and Pollock 2001. Words, phrases and languages are an inherent source of power in Pollock’s writings. Sanskrit and English terms are re-interpreted as long as they allow for a predetermined conclusion. Two examples of re-interpretationre-interpretation are briefly described presently.

Sanskrit terms re-interpreted: Terms such as pāramārthika sat pāramārthika sat and vyāvahārika satvyāvahārika sat are introduced in the sense of “absolute perspective of science” and “traditions of language thought” (Pollock (2006:65) without providing any reason for forcibly re-interpreting these terms to ascribe notions that are not supported by their typical use in existing literature. The purpose of using these terms in the newly interpreted sense is clear enough. The Sanskrit terms - and their stated Latin equivalents (regardless of the correctness in equivalence) - provide a veneer of plausibility to support his explanation of Buddhists’Buddhist use of Sanskrit in scriptural textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) though it is not used in other non-scriptural texts. The two forms of sat take on new meaning, arthaartha becomes power (Section 3), and so on.
English terms re-interpreted: Terms such as aestheticization of poweraestheticization of power, orientalism,Orientalism (passim) cosmopolis, and so on are familiar to the Western audience. Aestheticization and orientalism have a long history in India-related discourse. For now, I will focus on the term cosmopolis.cosmopolis Pollock explicitly states that the notion of ‘cosmopolis’ in its usual sense of the word (i.e., in the European context) is nothing like the sense with which he uses it in the Indian context. However, the connotationconnotation of the term ‘cosmopolis’ as used in the European context is applied directly to support the hypothesis of Sanskrit as a source of power.hypothesis!Sanskrit as source of powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of In the description of Pollock (2006), power takes center-stage in the “Sanskrit cosmopolis”,Sanskrit!cosmopolis just as it did in the European (sociopolitical) cosmopolis. In other words, the disclaimer of terms having different meanings in the European and Indian contexts becomes a distinction without a difference. Just as in the case of pāramārthika sat and vyāvahārika sat, the wildly differing connotations of cosmopolis in two contexts as used make little difference.

After ascribing new meanings to existing terms, the original meanings of the terms are invoked to arrive at startling conclusions. For example, though the term cosmopolis is used in a very different sense from its usual meaning in the European historical context, its implication - of certain empires and languages establishing domineering influence - is stated as the result of creation of the cosmopolis. Sanskrit becomes the dominating force used by Hindu kings (e.g., kings of the VijayanagaraVijayanagara and ŚrīvijayaŚrīvijaya kingdoms) seeking to establish their political and social supremacy by quashing existing local languages. The form of domination and power also differs from what is observed in the European context. Several caveats of how the sense of cosmopolis and power differs in the Indian and European contexts are indeed described at length. Yet the conclusion strips the caveats away and presents a narrative of Sanskrit being “an oppressive power that had to die” before new or local languages had a chance to flourish.

In the remaining part of this section, I shall discuss the nature of power, the tools of power ascribed to SanskritSanskrit and the resulting implications.

2.1 Form of power in European and Indian contexts

Section 1 described the origin, spread and decline of Latin. Let us now turn to Sanskrit and the power ascribed to it. In this section, I shall first summarize related arguments made in a few different places in Pollock (2006) and then briefly discuss a few questions that arise as a result of the formulation of the hypothesis in Pollock (2006).

No single local source can be traced as the original home of Sanskrit, neither can any military-political or military-religious force be said to be responsible for its spread (Pollock 2006:262). Further, when Medieval LatinMedieval LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) faced a precipitous decline in literary production, no such fall can be detected in Sanskrit literature. Poets, philosophers and scientists continued to use Sanskrit in the second millennium. So, clearly, a straightforward equivalence between Sanskrit and LatinSanskrit!and LatinLatin!and Sanskrit is non-existent, and no attempt at establishing such equivalence is made in Pollock (2006). But power and rupture of a different kind is described.

The first written literature in Latin is traced to 240 BCE when a Greek play was adapted into Latin by a Greek slave, Livius Andronicus.Livius Andronicus A little later, Naevius composed an epic poem about the first Punic war. The Sanskrit equivalent offered here is as follows. Vedic literature has taken form in the first millennium BCE. With writing having been invented in the third century BCE, a new form of literature kāvya is said to take root. Until the first century CE, all literature is primarily Vedic, which retains an other-worldliness and isolation (Pollock 2006:39). No non-Vedic literature is allowed to take shape in Sanskrit because Sanskrit intellectualsSanskrit!intellectuals are “bounded and limited”. While SanskritSanskrit is a source of sacred power, PrakritPrakrit is used for political and other laukika (worldly) purposes. For example, the Brahmanical Sātavāhana kingsSātavāhana kings used Prakrit for administration and literature (e.g., GāthāsaptaśatīGāthāsaptaśatī). On the other hand, the Shakas, who were foreign rulers, used and promoted Sanskrit at the cost of Prakrit (Pollock 2006:72). In this sense, Sanskrit becomes a source of powerhypothesis!Sanskrit as source of powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of that a foreign ruler can appropriate to assert authority.

Now if Sanskrit was “bounded and limited” in its scope and confined to sacral rites, it needed a catalyst to infuse newness and broaden its appeal. Foreign rulers such as Shakas,Shakas and much later, the Vijayanagara kings provided such an impetus in the political sense when they sought to occupy power using Sanskrit as a means of establishing their supremacy. And rulers such as Rudradāman and Buddhist poetsBuddhist!poets provided the needed catalyst to liberate Sanskrit for its oppressive masters. Just as an outsider, Livius who was Greek and a slave, was responsible for the introduction of LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) literature, outsiders such as Shakas and Buddhists were responsible for introducing Sanskrit as a medium for kāvya.

I shall use ThaparThapar, Romila (2015)’s description of RudradāmanRudradāman to provide context. With the advent of Kushanas,Kushanas the Shakas had moved further south into western India. Here Rudradāman was a mid-second century BCE KshatrapaKshatrapa king. His Junagarh inscriptionJunagarh inscription in Sanskrit, the earliest of its kind that has been discovered, provides a detailed account of his activities. Instead of using Prakrit, why did he use Sanskrit in his inscriptions? Thapar’s account provides at least two reasons for Rudradāman’s use of Sanskrit, without suggesting a definitive answer. He could have used Sanskrit to endear himself to orthodoxy to establish his legitimacy as a ruler. Or he could have anticipated the winds of change which was bringing about parallel patronagepatronage in court circles. In Pollock (2006), no such hesitation is even hinted at in arriving at a conclusion that Rudradāman used Sanskrit to establish his legitimacy as a ruler. Similarly, Buddhist poets who had already composed the Jātaka talesJātaka tales in PaliPali, switched to Sanskrit to compose literature (e.g., Aśvaghoṣa’s BuddhacaritaBuddhacaritaAśvaghoṣa).

2.2 Praśasti and powerpraśastipower!Sanskrit as a source of

Rudradāman is important for another reason. The Junagarh inscriptionJunagarh inscription is considered an early example of praśasti. In this discussion, I shall juxtapose the discussion of praśasti in Pollock (2006) and Thapar (2015). According to Thapar (2015), praśasti was still evolving as a literary style at the time, and would find clearer form in Aśvaghoṣa’s Buddhacarita. A marginal activity initially, it “later” became important enough to “affect the structure of the political economy”political!economy (Thapar 2015:225). (Thapar’s account does not specify the time frame to which “later” refers). Pollock considers that praśasti attained final form by the time of PallavasPallavas (7th c. CE). It is interesting to note that praśasti as a form of literature is accorded significant importance in Pollock (2006), whereas the historical account in Thapar is less eager to embrace its importance (“...one hesitates to take it literally” -Thapar 2015:283-4).

Praśasti plays a central role in Pollock (2006) especially when trying to establish equivalence with Latin.Latin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) Moreover the occurrence of praśasti-s is portrayed as a “sudden”, “startling, nearly simultaneous” event not just in the Indian subcontinent but in Southeast Asia as well. On the other hand, ThaparThapar, Romila (2015) describes a gradual development of praśasti literature. In the absence of evidence of any large scale military intervention before that of the CholasCholas in 11th c. CE, mercantile and religious interactionsmercantile and religious interactions are said to be the basis for the spread of Sanskrit to South East Asia in early centuries CE. During this time, according to Pollock (2006), Sanskrit becomes the key to power because of the proliferation of praśasti.power!Sanskrit as a source of The historical description of politics and trade in Thapar (2015) mentions the presence of Indian merchants in Myanmar, Oc-eo (near the Gulf of Siam)Gulf of Siam and so on. More interestingly, similarities between pre-existing cultures in Southeast Asia and South India in activities such as rice cultivationrice cultivation and burial are described. Such exchanges “evolved into trade and incipient urbanism.” Again, a deeper, more long-lasting, connection is discussed in Thapar (2015) unlike Pollock (2006). Whereas Thapar (2015) discusses a measured, historical account of events in India and Southeast Asia, Pollock (2006) presents a larger narrative without describing alternative possibilities.

Let us briefly look at the case of praśasti in Kannada as described in Pollock (2006). The earliest evidence of writing in Kannada is available from the 5th c. CE, but the earliest praśastipraśasti, earliest and earliest literature is said to be from the 9th c. CE - both intimately tied to the royal court. In other words, analogous to the case of Sanskrit, kāvya and praśasti is said to emerge at the same time. In the description of the praśasti of KrishnarajaKrishnaraja (Pollock 2006:334), it is said that this is the first of its kind in Kannada. Among the king’s titles, three types of words are seen: (1) Kannada compound words, (2) Sanskrit compound words and (3) words that are formed by compounding a Kannada word and a Sanskrit word by means of an ari-samāsaari-samāsa which is generally frowned upon. This mixing of form of titles is made out as a “careful balancing” of “globalizing and localizinglocalizing registers”.

A late 9th c. CE inscription of King ErayappaErayappa (King) is then discussed as an example of path-breaking vernacularity in Kannada country. The quoted passage of long Sanskrit words interspersed with Kannada words is described as an example of a new lexicon, a new “mode of representation” (Pollock 2006:335). The discussion does not mention however that part of the phraseology …nirmala-tārāpati… is reminiscent of the earliest available Kannada inscription (i.e., the Halmidi inscriptionHalmidi inscription). (I shall briefly return to the Kannada writing discussion in Section 2.4.)

In Pollock (2006), the description of the development of Kannada language and power may be summarized as follows:

Though evidence of writing in Kannada is available from the 5th c. onwards, the earliest works of Kannada literature in a distinctly recognizable form is not available till the 9th century.
In the 9th century, two forms of literature arose almost simultaneously – kāvyakāvya and praśasti.
Kannada literary development and its royal patronagepatronage had a symbiotic relationship.symbiotic relationship

2.3 Tools of Power

As discussed above, Sanskrit is presented as a source of legitimizing power. The nature of its powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of is further described by the following characteristics:

Lack of geographicalgeographical groundinggeographical!grounding
Written literatureliterature
Aestheticsaesthetics in Sanskrit literature
Grammargrammar
śleṣaśleṣa

These factors are briefly explained next.

Sanskrit,Sanskrit it is said, was “at home everywhere, and nowhere.” It has no single, traceable place of origin. This meant that no single group of people can claim ownership of Sanskrit. But those who want power use it where and when needed. In this sense, Sanskrit finds a home everywhere. Without a clearly identifiable geographical localization,geographical!localization on the contrary, it finds a home nowhere.

Writing plays a crucial part in Pollock’s theory. To begin with it, a new term, literizationliterization is introduced to describe the phase when a language acquires a written form. (Literarizationliterarization, on the other hand, refers to the phase when a language starts producing literature). Three reasons are described in the introductory chapter of Pollock (2006): (a) Writing claims an authority that orality cannot. Speaking is natural, but writing is not. (b) Writing is richer than oral,oral tradition and allows for the examination of language itself, (c) “Writing makes possible the production of history of a sort the oral is incapable of producing”. All this is stated without elaboration.

Using an idea that was promoted in the 1930’s, Pollock (2006) opines that Sanskrit - specifically works such as Kālidāsa’s RaghuvaṁśaKalidasaRaghuvaṁśa and various praśastis - attracted power because of their aesthetic nature. The theory of aestheticization of poweraestheticization of power and politics has been criticized on several grounds (Jay 1992).Jay, Martin A general criticism of the theory however, is insufficient to test the validity of the theory as applied in the specific contexts of Sanskrit and Kannada.

For a language to acquire power,power!Sanskrit as a source of in addition to written status, grammargrammar is said to be a prerequisite. Sanskrit managed to attract power because of its highly developed grammar. In turn the political power was interested in ensuring grammar’s place. Bhoja’sBhoja/Bhojadeva patronagepatronage of poetry and grammar is described in detail to imply that his strength and position of power was at least in part because of the patronage. Statements such as “ rājani kavau sarvo lōkaḥ kaviḥ syāt” are quoted as examples of kings using proper language as a means of power. Further, Patañjali’sPatañjali adage of “ekaḥ śabdaḥ saṁyak jñātaḥ śāstrānvitaḥ suprayuktaḥ svarge lōke kāmadhuk bhavati” is used to justify the relevance of proper language to dharmadharma (and hence power) (Pollock 2006:183). Languages acquire such political power when their grammar reaches maturity.

The use of śleṣa attained an impressive level of sophistication in Sanskrit. Its evolution is then connected to the power of politics using arguments that echo the theory of aestheticization of poweraestheticization of power. Similarly `alaṅkāra'alaṅkāra becomes equally powerful in their ability to influence political power through their use in praśasti-s. Sanskrit then becomes a tool to enhance reality through its unique abilities in ślēṣa, other alaṅkāra-s and so on. The king then exploits this power to legitimize and maintain his power.

2.4 Some Questions

In the analysis in Pollock (2006) described above, several factors are completely or largely ignored. I shall mention a few items below. The discussion in this section will be brief in order to limit the scope of the paper to pūrva-pakṣa and not expand it into an uttarapakṢa. The questions are raised here because they are an extension of the pūrvapakṣha arguments themselves.

2.4.1 A long tradition of oral literature

Only written literature is recognized by him as literature for consideration, and not orally transmitted literature. Three reasons are stated for this treatment (Section 2.3) – authority, richness and ability to produce history. Pollock (2006) states that writing possesses these three faculties whereas oral tradition does not. If writing is to be accorded such primacy over oral literature, then it is natural for the reader to expect a careful and reasoned justification of the stated position.

Authority: It is difficult to understate the impact of the Vedas, RāmāyaṇaRāmāyaṇa and MahābhārataMahābhārata in the Indian context. All these forms of literature continued to be transmitted orally for several generations before they were written down. Did their stature or authority change in the minds of people after they were written down? Pollock (2006) does not address this question.

Richness: In addition to the richness of story-telling in the itihāsa-s,itihāsa the sūtra literaturesūtra literature – especially those of Pāṇini, can hardly be faulted for lack of richness, imagination or creativity.

Ability to produce history: The argument that writing, unlike oral tradition, can produce history is stated without elaboration in Pollock (2006). It would be interesting to explore this aspect more thoroughly especially in the light of attempts at building history through narratives. For example, songs of the bhakti movement in the Dāsa traditionDāsa tradition provide a glimpse of the society of their time. DonigerDoniger, Wendy (2009) is another example of historical perspective-taking which relies on oral traditionoral tradition such as the Veda-s.Veda

2.4.2 Mahābhāṣya references to existing literature

A central tenet of the thesis of Pollock (2006) is that Sanskrit kāvya literature began around the 1st c. CE. References to older traditions of literature described in the MahābhāṣyaMahābhāṣya are stated in the book, but quickly set aside citing difficulties in dating the Mahābhāṣya itself. Whatever difficulties there may be regarding its dating, even taking the late estimates of its period, we are left with more than a century and a half between references in Mahābhāṣya to kāvya, and to the starting period of kāvya as per Pollock (2006). This large difference is difficult to reconcile.

The question of whether older traditions of kāvya to which Mahābhāṣya alluded are to be considered as literature in the sense of Pollock, remains unresolved.

2.4.3 Pāṇini’s reference to drama

In addition to Mahābhāṣya’s literary references, Pāṇini sūtra-s contain references to dramaturgydramaturgy (KrishnashastriKrishnashastri, A R 2002:28). These do not appear in the analysis in Pollock (2006). Bharata’sBharata NāṭyaśāstraNāṭyaśāstra which is the earliest extant work in its field is discussed in Pollock (2006) and its impact on development of literary analysis in Indian languages is described. Several post-Bharata treatises and their influence on analytical textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) of vernacular language are discussed as well.

However the silence on references to older texts is somewhat perplexing. For the purposes of establishing the age of beginning of a field, even if the details of the older texts’ discussion are unknown, can the older texts be summarily dismissed, as advanced by the necessities of narrative-building?narrative-building

2.4.4 Regional variations in Sanskrit and Prakrit

Sanskrit as described by Pāṇini,Pāṇini KātyayanaKātyayana and `Patañjali', showed regional variations. From their descriptions, it is clear that the regional differences were not a hindrance to the development or usage of language itself. Similarly, the variety of PrakritsPrakrits, variety of are well-documented, e.g., in Śṛṅgāraprakāśa.Śṛṅgāraprakāśa This long-standing diversity within SanskritSanskrit and Prakrit does not support a centralized, uniform view of the language. Further, Vedic SanskritSanskrit!Vedic exhibits even greater diversity in forms, as recognized by all-encapsulating descriptions such as “bahulam chandasi” by the grammarians.grammar Given this diversity and equal importance accorded to different usages, the analogy of LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church)Latin!analogy of is puzzling as far as power and politics is concerned.

If indeed language is to be seen through a European lens,European!lens with a strong powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of attribute, how does Pollock (2006) reconcile the absence of attempts to assert dominance of one form of the language over another?

2.4.5 Parallel literary traditions of Sanskrit, Prakrit and ApabhramśaParallel literary traditionsApabhramśa

As seen in dramas and bilingual poems, poets did not hesitate to simultaneously employ several languages. And we see that Sanskrit,Sanskrit PrakritPrakrit and ApabhramśaApabhramśa flourished simultaneously. So we are left to reconcile conflicting factors. On the one hand, we observe fluidity in language usage from early times. On the other, Pollock (2006) seeks to identify rigid events of birth and death in fairly dramatic terms.

Even in modern times, music compositionsmusic compositions exhibit an interesting linguistic fluidity. Compositions that are generally categorized as Kannada or Telegu compositions (e.g., several compositions of Muttayya BhāgavatarMuttayya Bhāgavatar and Mysore Vāsudevācārya),Mysore Vāsudevācārya are primarily in Sanskrit, except for a stray verb or so. Further, renditions of Prakrit text into Sanskrit have traditionally be called chāyāchāyā rather than anuvādaanuvāda (or translation). Given this fluidity between languages and their usage, one would anticipate a much more difficult task in trying to identify events such as birth and death of their usage. Such nuanced discussion is largely missing in Pollock (2006).

Similarly, the Kannada/Sanskrit ratiosKannada/Sanskrit ratios regarding epigraphs of various dynasties (footnote in Pollock 2006:332) requires further elaboration. How are epigraphs classified as Kannada vs Sanskrit? Does the occurrence of a single Kannada word make it a Kannada epigraph?Kannada!epigraph

2.4.6 A long history of Prakrit literature

Pollock (2006) considers that the creation of vernacular literature was “intimately related to new conceptions of communities and places”. And its creation is treated as a significant shift that is difficult to explain. It is necessary to better understand the premise of the quest in this regard. If one is to approach the problem of identifying beginnings of literature in a particular language in fairly binary terms, it is necessary to examine the background first. Was the prevailing literature fully in Sanskrit prior to the hypothesized break in literary tradition? This question when posed in the European context seems easier to answer because European literature before Dante,Dante was composed in Latin.Latin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) In the Indian context, was literature mono-linguistic before the so-called vernacular millennium?

Besides the parallel usageparallel usage of Sanskrit and Prakrit in literature, there have been several PrakritPrakrit texts (as mentioned in Pollock (2006) as well), e.g., Vimalasūri’sVimalasūri PaumacariyaPaumacariya (2nd-4th c. CE), Guṇāḍhya’sGuṇāḍhya BṛhatkathāBṛhatkathā (earlier than 3rd c. CE). Given this tradition, the reason for treating literature in Kannada or other vernaculars as a startling enterprise is difficult to understand.

2.4.7 Influence of Prakrit and Apabhramśa on SanskritSanskrit!influence of Prakrit and Apabhramśa on

Pollock mentions that Prakrit and Apabhramśa influenced Sanskrit (Pollock 2006:65). If Sanskrit’s powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of emanated from its “proper”ness and geographic transcendence or Latinesque uniformity,Latinesque uniformity and further, if, Sanskrit intellectualsSanskrit!intellectuals were “bounded and limited” - it seems contradictory to expect Sanskrit being influenced by Prakrit or other languages. In the context of Khmer languageKhmer language for example, this is the argument presented - Sanskrit influenced Khmer language, but not the other way around (Pollock 2006:127). If the rulers were indeed trying to find legitimacy through language, they could have allowed for Khmer’s influence on Sanskrit. These factors have not been articulated.

2.4.8 Śṛṅgāraprakāśa’s silence on praśastiŚṛṅgāraprakāśapraśasti

In its detailed discussion of different types of literature, Śṛṅgāraprakāśa (which is referenced in Pollock (2006) as an authority text), does not treat praśasti as an all-too serious form of literature. (Neither does the historian Thapar,Thapar, Romila as mentioned above). If one is to understand praśasti as a form of literature that deserves the kind of categorization that Pollock (2006) demands, then the same could be said of other forms of literature, e.g., bhakti stotra-s.bhakti stotra After all stotrakāra-s in their phalaśrutiphalaśruti take themselves as seriously as praśastikāra-spraśastikāra do!

2.4.9 Early writing in Kannada

It is surprising to see that a discussion of vīragal is almost completely absent from the discussion of writing in KarnatakaKarnataka in Pollock (2006). (It appears once in the book as a footnote (Pollock 2006:330)). Naik and Naik(1948) considers such stone inscriptions to be peculiar to Karnataka, and mentions that almost all inscriptions of its kind are found in Karnataka. The form and composition of vīragal-s tend to follow certain structure as described in Naik and Naik. An early form of writing that is so completely distinctive in style and geography would surely merit a longer discussion when considering the history of writing and literature in a region. One is left to wonder if this omission is to suit the necessities of narrative-buildingnarrative-building rather than empirical data.

2.4.10 Knowledge systems such as mathematics and science in Sanskritknowledge systems

Literary knowledge begins and ends with kāvya and praśasti according to Pollock (2006). Surely śāstra literature is a valid form of literature too. Varāha-mihiraVarāhamihira is briefly mentioned in Pollock (2006). But long traditions of maths literature, their contributions and impact is largely ignored. For example, the Kerala school of mathematicsKerala School of Mathematics itself had a long tradition that spanned several centuries during the middle ages. The influence of science and maths is arguably quite important when one considers the longevity and sustainability of societies and civilization. In fact, one could argue that access to scientific and technological texts and practices could be beneficial to a king.

Pollock (2006) does not discuss scientific literatureSanskrit!scientific literature in any detail as it may apply to creation and consolidation of power.

2.4.11 Rāmāyaṇa’s non-conformity with Pāṇinian formsRāmāyaṇaPāṇinian forms

If grammargrammar is considered a prerequisite for literary development, and if the Rāmāyaṇa took its final literary form in the 1st c. CE much after Pāṇini’s grammar,grammar why did the upholders of orthodoxy, the Sanskrit intellectualsSanskrit!intellectuals who rendered RāmāyaṇaRāmāyaṇa not correct the many non-Pāṇinian forms in the text?

2.4.12 Early Indonesian kingdomsIndonesian kingdoms

In the discussion of Sanskrit’s interaction with Southeast Asian languages, a historical account of kingdoms of the region and their relation to the ancient world is missing. Just as the historical account (e.g., Thapar’sThapar, Romila account discussed at various points here) can add additional clarity in the Indian context, it is reasonable to expect historical analysis to better illuminate the status of languages and their relationship in Southeast Asia.

As stated at the outset, the above list is not intended to be detailed or comprehensive because of limitations of scope of this paper. However the questions suggest that the necessities of narrative-building in Pollock (2006) seem to propel the consideration of empirical data, instead of allowing empirical data to guide the narrative and subsequent conclusions.

3 Sanskrit Cosmopolis

It is true that the Sanskrit world had a kind of universalism that deserves to be studied. Pollock (2006) uses the term cosmopoliscosmopolis to describe this, despite the limitations of the term (and its historical meaning). Historically, cosmopolitancosmopolitan referred to “a community of free males” (Pollock 2006:12). The Sanskrit cosmopolisSanskrit!cosmopolis had no such characteristic; neither does Pollock (2006) seek to argue from that position. But the term Sanskrit cosmopolis is used to represent three factors:

Geographic expanse:geographic expanse The influence of Sanskrit transcended regional and national boundaries.
Political dimension: The assumption is that a global identification required a political dimension.
The role of Sanskrit: In establishing the political and cultural universalismcultural!universalism (to whatever extent), the thesis is that Sanskrit was a critical lynchpin.

Ancient Indians’ concept of geography shows some degree of diversity, but some boundaries like the HimalayasHimalayas recur (Pollock 2006:191). Apart from Indians who self-identified as a people of a common land (despite living in different kingdoms), foreign visitors such as the Greeks and ChineseChinese!travellers too, recognize this common identity. Literary sources ranging from the Mahābhārata to KāmasūtraKāmasūtra display an awareness of cultural unity and diversity across the country. The image of the Kāvyapuruṣakāvyapuruṣa which recognizes the holistic nature of different styles and media by giving it an anthropomorphic formanthropomorphic form is described in detail (Pollock 2006:202-3). While it readily recognizes the universal nature of the Kāvyapuruṣa depiction, Pollock (2006) considers it to be “finite” and limiting in the sense that “no other exists outside it.” This description is reminiscent of the “limited and bounded” characterization of Sanskrit intellectualsSanskrit!intellectuals (section 2.1).

Across the country, despite the geographical diversitygeographical!diversity in which there were differences in Sanskrit usage as attested in the Mahābhāṣya,Mahābhāṣya Pollock (2006) argues that the uniformity in the mārgamārga discourse is striking. For example, the vaidarbhī stylevaidarbhī style in the north was no different from the vaidarbhī style in the south. It is not clear why language usage in the sense of preference for certain word forms / verbs as discussed in the Mahābhāṣya should affect stylistic choices in composition. A poet using vaidarbhī style in a certain part of the country could use word forms which would be distinct from another poet using vaidarbhī style in a different part of the country. Pollock (2006) does not seem to make this distinction.

Indian classical musicalcompositions, classical musical compositions provide another example of how geographical proximitygeographical!proximity may not be necessary or sufficient to influence composers’ works. The MysoreMysore king Jayachāmarajendra Wodeyar’sWodeyar!Jayachāmarajendra compositions (20th c. CE) bear a strong resemblance with Muttusvāmi Dīkṣitar’sMuttusvāmi Dīkṣitar who preceded him by a century. The similarity is apparent in the lyrical senselyrical sense (e.g., preference for long compound words), and in the musical sensemusical sense (e.g., keeping the sāhityasāhitya quite tightly bound unlike say, Tyāgarāja).Tyāgarāja This style is recognizably different from Mysore Vāsudevācārya’s,Mysore Vāsudevācārya who was the resident musician in the Mysore royal court, and stylistically more strongly related to Tyāgarāja.

Let us return to the second feature of Sanskrit cosmopolis in Pollock (2006) - the political dimension.political!dimension The discussion uses MahābhārataMahābhārata as an example to describe the political powerpower!political that characterized the Sanskrit cosmopolis. It quotes half a verse from the BhīṣmaparvanBhīṣmaparvan to illustrate the paradox of power. To provide clearer context to this line, two verses are quoted below (SukthankarSukthankar, V S 1942):

arthasya puruṣo dāso dāsas tvartho na kasyacit |
iti satyaṁ mahārāja baddho'smy arthēna kauravaiḥ|| 6.41.36 ||
atas tvāṁ klībavad vākyaṁ bravīmi kurunandana |
hṛto'smyarthēna kauravyayuddhād anyat kim icchasi ||6.41.37||

Pollock (2006:225) translates the first line as “man is slave to power, but power is slave to no one.”

Now, BhīṣmaBhīṣma utters these words after YudhiṣṭhiraYudhiṣṭhira has explained the reasons for fighting against him, and seeks his blessings to vanquish him. Bhīṣma recognizes the necessity and propriety of Yudhiṣṭhira’s fight and gives his blessing. In doing so, he explains his commitment to DuryodhanaDuryodhana alluding to his prior oath to the throne. In that context (or indeed even in a general context), translating artha as power seems rather odd. Especially because Bhīṣma says “hṛtō'smi arthena,” which may be translated as “I am compelled by artha.” Bhīṣma was not compelled by political power to act - but Bhīṣma's own earlier commitment. Or, arguably it could be translated as wealth, in the sense that Bhīṣma earned his livelihood (though this does seem to be a rather weak and excessively literal translation). In short, Pollock seems to use a line from the Mahābhārata and attributes a meaning that is textually and contextually difficult to sustain.

This is of course, not to deny that there is a political dimensionpolitical!dimension to the central conflict depicted in the Mahābhārata, or in the ancient or medieval Indian kingdoms (or for that matter in modern India). The connection to Sanskrit is not clear, especially when it is justified by questionable translations.questionable translations

Another aspect of the political dimensionpolitical!dimension described is the support for recitation and propagation of the Mahābhārata provided by rulers across the country. The Pollock (2006) itself describes the Mahābhārata as “a veritable library of the world” because of its impact and content (Pollock 2006:225). So it would seem natural for rulers to promote such story telling (and perhaps encouraging story tellers in their kingdom to add their stories to the library). Further, the RāmāyaṇaRāmāyaṇa has also seen several variations - so much so that some of the South-east Asian versions diverge significantly from Vālmīki’s version.

In other words, this version of the cosmopolis seems to have little or no similarities in the political sense with its existing usage. I am not suggesting that Pollock (2006) attempts to use cosmopolitan in its usual sense when applied to Sanskrit, but it would be more helpful to use words which do not require an elaborate justification of why the usual meaning is not the intended meaning for a given term. Incidentally, Hastināpura is translated as the “City of Elephants”City of Elephants (Pollock 2006:362). Sources such as the ŚabdakalpadrumaŚabdakalpadruma explain the word (using an aluk-samāsaaluk-samāsa) as a city founded by Hastin, a king of the Candravaṁśa lineage.

Next, let us consider the third aspect of Sanskrit cosmopolis in Pollock (2006) - the role of Sanskrit. Having already described the tools of powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of ascribed to Sanskrit, this aspect is perhaps discussed in relation to vernacularvernacular languages, and Sanskrit’s interaction with them. I shall pick Kannada as an example because Kannada is discussed more extensively compared to other languages in Pollock (2006). The earliest writing in Kannada is available from the 5th c. CE. The first works of kāvya in Kannada appear almost five centuries later with PampaPampa who is called the ādikaviādikavi (Kannada) in Kannada. In the intervening five centuries, literature was confined to Sanskrit, Prakrit and Apabhramśa. This, it is argued, was because Sanskrit asserted its power and suppressed literature in vernaculars.

Later, when Sanskrit “cedes literary power to vernaculars”, it provides the framework for not just literary creativity, but also provides the basic structure for Kannada grammarKannada!grammar (vibhakti-s, etc.).vibhakti And the two languages shared a two-way exchange.

Quoting NāgavarmaNāgavarma (Pollock 2006:370), he translates the passage as “...metrical speciesmetrical species [of Kannada and other vernaculars] have arisen from the three languages Sanskrit, Prakrit and Apabhramsha, and from the half language Paishachi.” Attributing the correct analysis of this passage to TV Venkatachala Sastry,Sastry, TV Venkatachala Pollock says that it has long been misunderstood. From a plain reading of the phrase “sarva-viṣaya-bhāṣā-jātigaḷu,”sarva-viṣaya-bhāṣā-jātigaḷu a translation of “metrical species” seems worthy of discussion.

While he admits the tatsama-tadbhava relationshiptatsama-tadbhava relationship between Sanskrit and Kannada, it seeks to portray a much more strident break between the two languages in the emergence of Kannada literature. To that end, borrowing “metrical species” born from Sanskrit counterparts allows for a dramatic break which the older translation in which “languages born” from the three and a half languages, do not. The self-conscious note with which Kannada creates its own position is then further explained using the examples of KavirājamārgaKavirājamārga and ŚabdamaṇidarpaṇaŚabdamaṇidarpaṇa (SMD). Here the self-aggrandizing statement of the SMD is treated seriously, just as praśasti statements are.

Further, Sanskrit’s power in VijayanagaraVijayanagara is extolled. Though KannadaKannada and TeluguTelugu were used extensively for administrative purposes (in their respective areas of usage), Pollock (2006) says that the Vijayanagara kings promoted Sanskrit literature and not Kannada literature. Now it is true, many works of Sanskrit were produced in that period - no less than the SāyaṇabhāṣyaSāyaṇabhāṣya of the VedasVeda themselves. But Kannada literary works seem to be ignored (Desai 1936) - e.g., Timmanna’s Kṛṣṇarāya BhāratakathāmañjarīKṛṣṇarāya BhāratakathāmañjarīTimmaṇṇa(kavi) (which is considered a landmark work of Kannada pride), VīraśaivaVīraśaiva poets MallaṇṇāryaMallaṇṇārya (Vīraśaivapurāṇa),Vīraśaivapurāṇa VirūparājaVirūparāja (poet) (Tribhuvanatilaka),Tribhuvanatilaka NanjarājuNanjarāju (Kumāravyāsana kathe).Kumāravyāsana kathe

Sanskrit is thus presented as the dominant powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of in the cosmopolis, the power which stifled literary production in vernacular languages.

4 The Death of Sanskrit

Finally, I shall briefly summarize Pollock’s theory of the death of Sanskrit under five main points:

Sanskrit’s death in KashmirKashmir
Its steady decline in Vijayanagara kingdom
The last Sanskrit poet
Death before colonialism,colonialism not because of it.
All of useful knowledge in Sanskrit was because of the West anyway.

In Kashmir, it is said that Sanskrit effectively died in the 12th c. CE, and failed to find a strong voice again, despite the efforts of Zain-ul-'abidinZain-ul-"'abidin in the 15th c. CE. The possible influence of Islamic invasionsIslamic invasion is not considered seriously. However, the historical account in Thapar, RomilaThapar’s book tells a different story where Mahmud GhazniGhazni, Mahmud (Muhammed) is described as the “champion iconoclasticonoclast looted the richest templestemple!loot at an unprecedented scale” (Thapar 2015:427).Thapar, Romila Mahmud GhuriGhuri, Mahmud (Muhammed) followed in his footsteps in the 12th c. CE not to plunder, but to establish a potential kingdom.

Pollock (2006) briefly mentions the possible influence and accepts a southward shift in reaction to Islam development in the north. However, even if Islam rulers occupied powerpower!political (the word invadersinvaders is not used in Pollock (2006) in this context), Pollock (2006) does not expect any adverse impact on traditional Sanskrit pundits. The strong learning tradition it is argued, should have persisted in literary endeavors.

In the case of Vijayanagara,Vijayanagara Pollock (2006) and Pollock (2001) do not consider any Sanskrit works of this era to be original work, but merely reproductive in nature. Moreover, “the Vijayanagara cultural world seems to have produced few if any Sanskrit works” that transcended time or geography (Pollock 2001:401). Here the discussion seems a bit unclear. First, it is said that a large body of Vijayanagara literature is yet to see the light of day - because they are available only in unpublished manuscripts.manuscript Pollock (2006) echoes a wish for a change in this state of affairs and the publication of manuscripts. At the same time, Pollock (2001) asserts that Vijayanagara has not produced Sanskrit works that have stood the test of time. As a means of substantiating this line of reasoning, examples of Kannada and TeluguTelugu manuscripts that have survived since their creation during the Vijayanagara period are given. In the absence of a record of similar manuscripts in Sanskrit, it is said that literary production of Sanskrit during the Vijayanagara period was not especially impactful. The main thrust of the argument relies on three factors: availability, publishing and subjective assessment of manuscripts.

The first two factors of availability and publishing of manuscripts are somewhat related. Without a full catalogue and publication of manuscripts, it is difficult to assess the validity of the argument. More publication, research and writing regarding works of this period would help to better understand the contributions of Vijayanagara. Sadly, this field of study seems to have been a victim of modern day Indian politics. On the third factor regarding the subjective assessment of quality and whether works are primarily derivative, it perhaps merits a larger discussion. Hanneder’sHanneder review discusses the shortcomings of relying excessively on qualitative assessment to decide the status of language vibrancy.

Kṛṣṇadēvarāya’sKṛṣṇadevarāya JāmbavatīpariṇayaJāmbavatīpariṇaya is discussed as an example of a Vijayanagara work with limited literary value (Pollock 2001:402-403). After briefly describing the premise of the work, Pollock (2001) dismissively insists that the dramatic adaptation of the tale contains “nothing new”. The tale is then seen through a politico-military perspectivepolitico-military perspective by relating the work to the king’s Orissa campaign. As in the case of earlier kings who used Sanskrit to assert their powerpower!Sanskrit as a source of (Section 2), Kṛṣṇadēvarāya’s work too is recognized for its “mytho-political representation”mytho-political representation of the king.

At this stage, Pollock (2001)Pollock!shifting of goalposts turns to the lack of personal experience reflected in Sanskrit works from the Vijayanagara period as a sign of Sanskrit’s decline. Hanneder calls out the shifting of goalposts as “a surprising statement produced by the necessities of argumentation, rather than through evidence”. The notion of personal experience as a poetic tool is further elaborated by Pollock in his discussion of Jagannātha.

According to Pollock (2001), the last Sanskrit poet was JagannāthaJagannātha, Paṇḍitarāja of the 17th c CE. The reasons stated for this are as follows. He was the last great poet to travel the length and breadth of India. His was the last great work that found transregional acceptance. His praśasti of the kings of Udaipur and Delhi, though rooted in the literature’s historical past, had a certain newness to it. The form of newness attributed to Jagannātha in this regard is not clearly described in Pollock (2006). Finally, his own personal life story finds resonance in his works. And the interest in his life story is enhanced because of the romantic love (and agony) he found in a Muslim woman.Muslim!woman With his death, original Sanskrit literature of any appreciable value, in Pollock’s estimation, died.

The death of Sanskrit was despite the Mughals’Mughals attempt at sustaining it. Examples of Akbar’sAkbar court are offered as examples of a deliberate attempt at nurturing Sanskrit knowledge production. Sanskrit learning and schools, it is said, continued well into colonial rule. And the British RajBritish Raj records show the proliferation of schools in the 19th c. CE. Yet despite this, Sanskrit literary production had ceased long before. Despite the continued presence of an informed readership which was well-versed in vernaculars and Sanskrit, 17th c. CE saw the death of Sanskrit.

Interestingly - and this aspect is not discussed in Pollock (2006) or Pollock (2001) - 17th c. CE saw the disappearance of the Kerala school of mathematicsKerala School of Mathematics too. Starting with MādhavaMādhava (mathematician) (14th c. CE), a school of mathematics which made path-breaking contributions ends in 17th c. CE.

Finally, as Pollock (2006) says, “Westernization is a permanent and global phenomenon.” A long list of items are offered as example of forms of knowledge or practice that India borrowed from the West - astronomy from the Greeks, Ashoka’s “very idiom of rule” from Achaemenid Persia,Achaemenid Persia architecture from Vetruvius, even RāmāyaṇaRāmāyaṇa could arguably come from Homerian source (Pollock 2006:265). (On Rāmāyaṇa, Pollock (2006) does not offer a conclusive statement, but states that Rāmāyaṇa possible origin in the Greek tales is a question worthy of consideration). Now, this idea of Western origin of all Indian or Sanskrit knowledge is made in the context of denying indigenism. It is argued that one can make a similar case for Easternization,Easternization in the sense that Greek’s influence on Europe would count as Easternization of Europe. A constant exchange of ideas and knowledge is the crucial element. The implication is that even if Sanskrit died, it is not something that should especially concern Indians.

This denial of any indigenous knowledge, while extolling the virtues of constant contact and exchange of ideas, is perhaps best seen in the following context. First, a long list of items are presented as contributions of the West, unlike other regions or cultures. Even if geographically accurate, it strains credibility to think of GreeceGreece as the East in the context of knowledge creation and transmission. Second, mathematics, grammargrammar or other forms of knowledge which were far more advanced in India than their western counterparts, do not find mention in this supposed equivalence in knowledge. Third, Pollock (2006) quotes extensively from Hegel. It is not difficult to see Hegel’s ideas resonating in Pollock (2006) and other Pollock’s writings on aesthetics (not discussed here). HegelHegel, G W F considered the “chief defect” of ancient Indians was that “they cannot grasp either the meanings themselves in their clarity, or existing reality in its own proper shape and significance.” This idea is further expanded in denying any possibility of Indian knowledge in Pollock (2006) and elsewhere. Moreover Hegel thinks the Indians “refer each and everything back to the sheerly Absolute and Divine, and to contemplate in the commonest and most sensuous things a fancifully created presence and actuality of Gods” (Pollock 2006:352-3).

Thus, Pollock (2006) argues that a series of important events occurred in geographically distinct areas such as Kashmir and Vijayanagara, which led to the death of Sanskrit across the country, despite the attempts of Muslim kings of Kashmir and the Mughals in preventing it. In 17th c. CE, with the last Sanskrit poet Jagannātha, Sanskrit’s death was sealed.

5 Conclusion

The theory of birth, growth and death of Sanskrit is certainly interesting to any student of Sanskrit. In this paper, Pollock’s hypothesis of the role of languageshypothesis!role of languages – particularly, Sanskrit and Kannada – in building and sustaining political powerpower!political are described. Per Pollock, Sanskrit’s linguistic, literary, grammatical and analytical maturity in ancient India became a source of power for kings who exploited it for their political gain. Having recognized its ability to accrue power, they nurtured Sanskrit literary production. This gave rise to a new literary form of kāvya. The Sanskrit poets returned the favor by composing praśasti, a new form of literature to praise the power of kings. This mutually beneficial ecosystem was disrupted by the rise of vernacular languages. Some vernacular languages such as Kannada then followed a similar pattern of royal patronagepatronage and power accrual using Kannada. Gradually literary production in Sanskrit declined despite efforts by Muslim rulersMuslim!rulers and later by British colonialists to revive it.

Throughout the process, Pollock employs three main techniques to form the hypothesis:hypothesis!formation of

Selective data sampling:data sampling As shown in Section 2.4 and in HannederHanneder(2002), empirical dataempirical data is selectively employed to suit the narrative, rather than let a comprehensive analysis of data guide the formation of the narrative. Hanneder uses the term “necessities of argumentation” to describe this characteristic. In my opinion, the selectivity has a stronger purpose. It not only serves the purpose of supporting a particular argument, but forms the basis of forming the narrative itself.
Jargonization:jargonizationmisinterpretation,!techniques of,!jargonization Terms such as literization and literarization are described in detail. Creating new terms to describe certain phenomena is certainly important. Contextual discussion however is often lacking. Understanding whether a term which has a clear utility in the European context continues to have a clear connotation in the Indian context would help in better appreciating the hypothesis.hypothesis!formation of
Re-interpretive analogy-making:misinterpretation,!techniques of,!reinterpretive analogy-making Terms and historical events which may have a superficial resemblance (if any), are identified by fully stating caveats about their limited sense of similarity. The ensuing discussion however, quickly sacrifices the stated caveats in favor of building a narrative.

Finally, it hardly needs re-emphasis that Pollock’s ideas merit serious discussion. It is unfortunate that the papers have not been addressed in similar depth or breadth. I shall conclude with some thoughts on the nature of future work that may add greater clarity to the questions raised in Pollock’s papers. A tempting form of response may be comprised of two forms: (a) a careful and detailed discussion and rebuttal of the points raised in Pollock’s writings, and (b) building a different, well-justified narrative that can explain the observed facts over the years.

But this response may face similar challenges and shortcomings. Instead, the field may benefit by taking a more systematic, data-drivendata-driven approach in first building up a large dataset of literature, their themes and cross-dependencies and strive to build detailed, quantified analysis of the questions of interest. Creation of such a dataset could be carried out through a joint effort, and by developing automated techniques to check for biasesbias in the data annotation. Then questions such as birth, growth, influence and death can be posed and analyzed more definitively.

Bibliography

Akshar, K.V. (2003) Viśvātmaka Deśabhāṣe (Kannada). Translations of Sheldon Pollock’s works. Sagara, Karnataka: Akshara Prakashana.
Cox, Whitney. (2011) “Saffron in the Rasam." In Y. Bronner, W. Cox, & L. McCrea (Eds.), Language, culture, and power: New directions in South Asian studies; pp. 177–201.
Desai, P. (1936) Vijaya Sāmrājya (Kannada). Dharwar: Vijayanagara Smarakotsva Samiti.
Doniger, Wendy. (2009) The Hindus: An Alternative History. New York: Penguin.
Freeman, Charles. (2004) Egypt, Greece and Rome: Civilizations of the Ancient Mediterranean. New York: Oxford University Press.
Gould, Rebecca. (2008) “How newness enters the world: The methodology of Sheldon Pollock." Comparative Studies of South Asia, Africa and the Middle East 28, no. 3; pp. 533–557.
Hanneder, Jürgen. (2002) “On “The Death of Sanskrit”." Indo-Iranian Journal 45, no. 4; pp. 293–310.
Hegel, Georg Wilhelm Friedrich. (1975) Hegel's aesthetics: Lectures on fine art. New York: Clarendon Press.
Jay, Martin. (1992) ““The Aesthetic Ideology” as Ideology; or, What Does It Mean to Aestheticize Politics?.” Cultural Critique 21; pp. 41–61.
Kaviraj, Sudipta. (2005) “The sudden death of Sanskrit knowledge.” Journal of Indian Philosophy 33, no. 1; pp. 119–142.
Krishnashastri, A.R. (2002) Saṁskṛta Nāṭaka (Kannada). Bengaluru: Hemantha Sahitya. (Original work published 1957).
Naik, A. V., and A. N. Naik. (1948) “Inscriptions of the Deccan: an Epigraphical Survey (circa 300 BC-1300 AD)." Bulletin of the Deccan College Research Institute 9, no. 1/2; pp. 1–160.
Pollock, Sheldon. (2001) “The Death of Sanskrit." Comparative Studies in Society and History 43, no. 02; pp. 392–426.
Pollock, Sheldon. (2006) The Language of the Gods in the World of Men: Sanskrit, Culture, and Power in Premodern India. Delhi: Univ of California Press.
Sukthankar, VS (ed.) (1942). The Mahabharata. Poona: Bhandarkar Oriental Research Institute.
Thapar, Romila. (2015) The Penguin history of early India: From the origins to AD 1300. London: Penguin UK.

Chapter 6 On “Feeding Tubes and Oxygen Tanks” for Sanskrit: In the light of the First Sanskrit Commission Report (1956–57)

Jayaraman Mahadevan

Abstract

This paper focuses upon one statement from the paper “The Death of Sanskrit” (2001) of Prof. Sheldon Pollock which is- “Government feeding tubesGovernment feeding tubes and oxygen tanks may try to preserve the language in a state of quasi-animation, but most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead.” (Pollock 2001: 393) There are two clear implications from this statement. Firstly – he implies that without the sponsorship of the Government, even the perceived ‘quasi-animate’ state of Sanskrit would not have been possible. Secondly – that the public and non-governmental players did not have any role at all in safe-guarding Sanskrit as Sanskrit has been never the language of the masses.

The First Sanskrit Commission report, hereafter, the Commission, assumes significance in this context. The Commission was constituted by the Government of India in 1956 with Dr. Suniti Kumar Chatterji as its chairman. Seven other scholars of repute from various parts of the country were its members. The Commission crisscrossed the length and breadth of the country. In the words of the Commission’s report “…to consider the question of the present state of Sanskrit Education in all its aspects” (Sanskrit Commission of IndiaSanskrit!Commission of India Report Report 1957:1). What does the study of the Sanskrit Commission’s detailed report reveal? Nearly five decades prior to the statement of Pollock in question (and its implications), one finds well researched facts and observations that render Pollock’s statement redundant, or rather, ridiculous. It is also interesting to note that Pollock has taken care not mention this report in his paper. Thus, this paper endeavors to juxtapose various observations from the overlooked First Sanskrit Commission Report, that fly in the face of Pollock’s aforementioned statement, and allow the readers to see for themselves the flaws and blemishes of Pollock’s understanding of the status of Sanskrit.

1 The Trigger

The article “The Death of Sanskrit” (2001) by Sheldon Pollock offers various elements of pūrva-pakṣa for a Sanskritist. But, this paper focuses upon just one statement from the paper which is -

“Government feeding tubesGovernment feeding tubes and oxygen tanks may try to preserve the language in a state of quasi-animation, but most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead.” (Pollock 2001:393)

This statement is found in the third paragraph of the said article. Why just one statement and why this statement? To answer this straightaway - firstly, it has to be noted that the paper “Death of Sanskrit'' appears in the year 2001. In the beginning of the paper Pollock states–

“The state’s anxiety both about Sanskrit’s role in shaping the historical identity of the Hindu nation and about its contemporary vitality has manifested itself in substantial new funding for Sanskrit education, and in the declaration of 1999–2000 as the “Year of Sanskrit,” with plans for conversation camps, debate and essay competitions, drama festivals, and the like.” (Pollock 2001:392)

Though aimed at throwing light on the anxiety of the State, eventually unease in the mind of Pollock gets exposed caused by the apparent spike in funding for Sanskrit and related activities in 1999–2000. And soon after, this triggered Pollock to conceptualize and eventually pen this paper in the year 2001. As can be observed, the above “Government feeding tubes oxygen tank” statement, directly indicates that trigger, which is at the root of the paper.

Secondly, it is also the first statement in the article in which Pollock unceremoniously states Sanskrit is dead. If this trigger-indicating statement is shown as untenable, it will symbolically indicate the relative strength of the superstructure that has been erected upon this by Pollock in the later part of his paper. Furthermore, it can also be stated that recourse has been taken to sthālīpulāka-nyāya–sthālī-pulāka-nyāyanyāya-s!sthālī-pulāka examining one grain of rice to see whether rest of the rice in the boiling pot is cooked - in evaluating Pollock’s paper.

2 About the First Sanskrit Commission

The First Sanskrit Commission Report, passim, naturally assumes significance in this context. The Commission was appointed by the Government of India in 1956 with Dr. Suniti Kumar ChatterjiChatterji, Suniti Kumar as its chairman. Seven other scholars of repute from various parts of the country were members. The objective of the Commission was, in the words of the Commission’s Report :

“…to consider the question of the present state of Sanskrit Education in all its aspects. To this end (p.8), “the tour programme of the Commission, was carried out in five laps, covered all the [then] 14 States of India and visited 56 centres and interviewed over 1,100 persons, representing various shades of opinion.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:1)

A study of the Sanskrit Commission’s report reveals that nearly five decades before Pollock’s statement in question already, the First Sanskrit Commission’s report effectively presents appropriate “responses” to this statement and its implications. It is highly improbable that he is unaware of this report of 1957. In fact he mentions the year 1949 regarding the inclusion of Sanskrit in the Eight Schedule of the Constitution.Constitution, Eighth Schedule He also makes a note of the awardees of the Sahitya Akademi since its inception in the year 1955. But conspicuously missing in this article is the mention of the Sanskrit Commission’s report of 1957 which is an important and unique document regarding the status of Sanskrit in India. Our paper endeavors to juxtapose various observations from the First Sanskrit Commission’s report and help the readers see for themselves the flaw in Pollock’s understanding of the status of Sanskrit.

3 Analyzing the statement

Pollock’s statement is analyzed in its two parts in this paper.

Part 1: “Government feeding tubesGovernment feeding tubes and oxygen tanks may try to preserve the language in a state of quasi-animation…

Part 2: “...but most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead.”

There are two clear implications for the first part of the statement. Firstly – he implies that without the sponsorship of the Government, even the perceived ‘quasi-animate’ state of Sanskrit would not have been possible either. Secondly – that the public and non-governmental players did not have any role at all in safeguarding Sanskrit, as Sanskrit, has been never the language of the masses.

The second part of the statement is very plain and is discussed as such.

3.1 First part of Pollock’s Statement, implications and Response

3.1.1 The First Implication and its response - Oxygen Tanks or Slow Euthanasia?Sanskrit!slow euthanasia of

Has the governmental aid really helped the survival of Sanskrit since whenever it was given? To this statement one finds a remarkable answer in the Sanskrit Commission's Report. It states

“As pointed out already, the authorities did not allow the traditional system either to die out or to flourish, but, by a process of nominal assistance, retained it alongside of modem education, in an unhealthy condition, ever subject to difficulty-always, open to criticism.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:28)

This state of affairs is as regards the attitude of the authorities of the pre-independence era, is quite understandable. Even during the post independence years, we may note that in all these seven decades, there is no substantial change in this approach.

The Commission records that the status of Sanskrit post independenceSanskrit!status of has not been any better than during the British rulers. It states -

“This Commission, in the course of its tours, could see a feeling of regret and disappointment among the people that, while no positive steps had been taken for helping Sanskrit, the measures undertaken in respect of other languages have had adverse repercussions on it. The ultimate result of this has been that Sanskrit has not been allowed to enjoy even the status and facilities it had under the British Raj.”British Raj (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:7)

The Sanskrit Commission report goes further to add a powerful imagery by quoting a verse in Sanskrit regarding the Government’s attitude towards Sanskrit post-independence. It states -

In this connection, the Sanskrit Commission would like to quote an old verse, which many Sanskritists referred to and which graphically pictured their real feeling: “ `The night will pass and the bright day will dawn; the sun will rise and the lotus will bloom in all its beauty' While the bee, imprisoned in a closed bud, was thus pondering over its future, alas, an elephant uprooted the lotus-plant itself." (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:8)

Further, it is important to note the fact that the Commission also makes it clear that the step-motherly attitudeSanskrit!step-motherly attitude towards of the Government towards Sanskrit does not necessarily reflect the feelings of the people at large towards Sanskrit. It states –

“On the one hand, Sanskrit scholars, members of the public, educationists and authorities were keenly alive to the importance of Sanskrit studies; and, on the other, there was one kind or another of official and administrative difficulty or lack of practical assistance which produced a sense of frustration.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:9)

Has the Government’s indifference towards Sanskrit undergone any change now - five decades after the first Sanskrit Commission? The answer is an unfortunate no. It is evidenced by the following statement from the committee set up by Ministry of Human Resource Development,Ministry of Human Resource Development Government of India, recently (2016) to evolve a “Vision and Roadmap for the Development of Sanskrit – Ten year Perspective Plan" –

“It is a fact that during the British period salary of Sanskrit teachers was half the salary of the salary of the teachers of other subjects due to which Sanskrit was looked down upon for long. Even today, in most of the states Sanskrit teachers who teach at Secondary and Higher Secondary level Vidyalayas are given Primary level teachers’ salary, teachers who teach at UG and PG level Sanskrit Mahavidyalayas are given the salary of Secondary grade teachers’. Hence these Vidyalayas and Mahavidyalayas do not attract the talented teachers and students” (Vision and Road Map for the Development of Sanskrit:Vision and Road Map for the Development of Sanskrit Report: 2016:5)

Wantonly or unwittingly, successive Governments in independent India trod the path of the erstwhile British masters. This observation of the committee puts in perspective the role of government in regard to the protection and promotion of Sanskrit.

As revealed by the above statements from the Sanskrit Commission report, the motive behind the minimal support to Sanskrit by successive governments has been brought to light. When the Governmental support has such motives as that of making Sanskrit appearing sick (though it might not be so), it leads us to the inevitable conclusion that governmental support or the lack of it cannot be taken as a correct indicator of the real status of Sanskrit. Hence it can be safely stated that Pollock has, on the basis of his above statement, allowed himself to be misled into assessing the real status of Sanskrit through the t(a)inted glasses of Governmental support.

3.1.2 The Second implication and its response:

This brings us to the second and more serious aspect as to the role of people and agencies other than the government in supporting and continuing the unbroken tradition of Sanskrit learning in the country.

A perusal of the Sanskrit Commission’s report brings out the fact that even more than the role of the Government, it is the people of the country who are keeping the flame of Sanskrit knowledge burning. The Sanskrit Commission’s report states that Sanskrit is associated with the ‘cultural consciousness’cultural!consciousness (Sanskrit Commission of India ReportSanskrit!Commission of India Report 1957:67) of the country and that the love of Sanskrit is “next only to that of patriotism towards Mother India” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:p.65). Though the Sanskrit Commission states that the state of Sanskrit in the country leaves much to be desired – yet far from being ‘dead’ as speculated by Pollock - the Commission states that “About the enthusiasm of the people of India as a whole for Sanskrit, we have received,..., the most convincing evidence.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957: ii)

Following are the non-governmental playersnon-governmental players and factors that can be identified from the report of the First Sanskrit Commission–

(a)
The MaharajasMaharajas of the Princely States
(b)
Hindu religious institutionsHindu religious institutionsinstitutions!religious
(c)
People belonging to non-Brahmin castescaste!non-Brahmin c. and other religions
(d)
Individual Traditional Pandits
(e)
Nationalistic Spirit
(f)
Role of voluntary Academies and Organizations
(g)
People in General

The list pertains to the Pre-independent as well as post-independent eras. It is to be noted that the seeds sown in the pre-independent era have sprouted later. For example, the role of the kings is a pre-independent era factor, but it would be seen in the words of the Commission itself as to how those pre-independence traditions helped in the preservation of Sanskrit in the post-independence era.

The seven factors listed above are now to be considered one by one.

3.1.2.a The MaharajasMaharajas

The Commission records that –

Apart from honouring Sanskrit Pandits and musicians in their Darbars and on occasions of domestic celebrations, and national festivals, the Maharajas did two important pieces of service to Sanskrit studies - one, the organization into libraries of their Palace collections of Sanskrit manuscripts, and two, the setting up of Sanskrit colleges.Sanskrit!Colleges (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:22)

The Commission enlists the Princely states that supported Sanskrit –

“Darbhanga,Darbhanga Vizianagaram, Baroda, Nagpur,Nagpur Jaipur,Jaipur Indore, Gwalior,Gwalior Mysore,Mysore Travancore,Travancore Kapurthala, Patiala,Patiala Jammu and KashmirJammu and Kashmir - to mention only the more prominent States - started their Sanskrit Colleges.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:22)

When one looks at the above list of princely states, it becomes evident that since the pre-independence era, even while under the British RajBritish Raj, it is these princes and kings who truly supported Sanskrit studies. Pre independence British Government was indifferent, and the attitude of post-independence governments has already been pointed out.

The role of the Maharajas in fostering Sanskrit education inspired other wealthy individuals too. The Commission records - “Inspired by the example of the Princes, the ZamindarsZamindars and smaller landlords and merchants also founded Sanskrit Colleges.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:22)

It is the Sanskrit organizations set up by the kings which were later converted into Government Sanskrit Colleges and Government manuscript repositories.Government manuscript repositories

3.1.2.b Hindu Religious institutionsHindu religious institutions

The role played by Hindu religious institutionsinstitutions!religious comes next. HinduismHinduism is often ridiculed for its mind boggling multiplicity of schools of philosophy and religious tenets. Though all these divergences exist among these religious denominations, they still were united in preserving Sanskrit which is the common thread. The Commission observers–

“Maths, templestemple!activities of and other religious institutions established similar Colleges; and affluent individuals and public leaders and associations also followed, founding their own Sanskrit Colleges,Sanskrit!Colleges or, by administrative direction, helping old religious and cultural endowmentsendowments, religious and cultural to start such colleges.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:22)

3.1.2.c People belonging to Non-Brahmin castes and other Religionsnon-Brahma(i)n!castes

Based on the first two points some may criticize that the kings and the priests had their own motives, i.e. dominating the others in society in promoting Sanskrit. But the Commission’s report makes it clear that even Muslims and ChristiansMuslim!and ChristiansChristians in certain parts of the country actively participated in the learning of Sanskrit. Nor was it the case that the Brahmin community alone was learning and preserving Sanskrit. Cutting across the barriers of castecaste and religion, Sanskrit was embraced by all people in India. Neither was gender a barrier in learning Sanskrit. The following statements of the Commission testify to this –

“That Sanskrit does not belong to any particular community is proved by Andhra and Kerala where the entire non-Brahman classesnon-Brahma(i)n!classes are imbued with Sanskrit, and speak a language highly saturated with Sanskrit. In Kerala, even Izhavas,Izhavas Thiyas,Thiyas MoplasMoplas and ChristiansChristians read Sanskrit. In Madhya Pradesh, we were told, a paper in Sanskrit was compulsory at the School Final Examination and even 66 Muslims took it. In a Lucknow Intermediate College, there are Muslim girls studying Sanskrit; in Gujarat, ParsisParsis study it; in Panjab, there are several Sikhs among Sanskrit students and teachers, and Sastris and research scholars in Sanskrit. The Director of Public Instruction of Madhya Pradesh, who is a Christian, told us that he advised the Anglo-Indian students also to read Sanskrit. It was necessary that, as future citizens of India, they gained an insight into the mind and the culture of the bulk of the Indian people. And this, he added, was possible only through the study of Sanskrit.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:64)

This patronagepatronage of Sanskrit by Muslims and Christians is not a new phenomena. The Commission opines that it is part of the historical continuityhistorical continuity of the interest of the non-Hindu communities in Sanskrit. To quote –

“This aspect of Sanskrit, that it was not exclusively religious, was appreciated even by some of the Muslim rulersMuslim!rulers of India, who patronised Sanskrit literature, and, in some cases (as in Bengal and Gujarat),Gujarat had their epigraphicepigraphy records inscribed in Sanskrit. It was the scientific and secular aspect of Sanskrit literature that made the Arabs welcome Indian scholars to BaghdadBaghdad to discourse on sciences like Medicine and Astronomy, and to translate books in these subjects into Arabic. The AyurvedaAyurveda system of medicine, until recently, was the truly National Indian System, which was practised everywhere, and access to this was through Sanskrit books, which even Muslim practitioners of the Ayurveda in Bengal studied.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:79)

This is yet another statement from the Commission’s report which is relevant to be quoted here–

“In the course of our tours in South India, we interviewed several non-Brahmans in high position and active in public life, business, etc., and we found them all favourable to Sanskrit. In Madras City itself, we found that, both in the recognised schools and private classes, non-Brahmans, and even a few Muslims and Christians,Christians studied Sanskrit. In one of the High Schools of Chidambaram, a Muslim student was reported to have stood first in Sanskrit; and in another School, there were HarijansHarijans among the Sanskrit students. In Chidambaram we were glad to find a group of leading non-Brahman merchants of the town who appeared before us for interview as staunch supporters of Sanskrit education and culture.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:65)

The Commission further adds –

“In TanjoreTanjore also, we were told by the Headmasters and Sanskrit teachers of local schools that non-Brahmans, Muslims and ChristiansChristians freely took Sanskrit. It was again the non-Brahmans, particularly the great benefactors belonging to the Chettiar community,Chettiar community who had, in the recent past, endowed many Pathasalas for VedaVeda and Sanskrit.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:66)

Thus it becomes evident from the above excerpts that all religious groups and castecaste groups patronized Sanskrit. Moreover, it also becomes evident that there is also no north-south dividenorth-south divide in promoting Sanskrit.

From the Commission’s report it was shown that cutting across religious, caste divisions people learn and love Sanskrit. It is very educative to note, when we see the Sanskrit Commission state that, even in the creation of Sanskrit literature over the ages, it was not the case that it was just one community was involved. The Commission notes –

“It must be further pointed out that the large mass of literature in Sanskrit was not produced by any particular community. Several instances can be quoted of non-BrahmanSanskrit!non-brahmana authors and non-Hindu authorsSanskrit!non-Hindu authors who have made significant contributions to Sanskrit literature. It is definitely wrong to assume that Sanskrit represents only the religious literature of the Hindus.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:79)

3.1.2.d Individual Traditional Pandits

Apart from various non-governmental organizations it was finally the individual scholars who stood for the protection and perpetuation of Sanskrit. The Commission states that –

“In addition to these two agencies, namely, the Government-organised Sanskrit Colleges,Sanskrit!Colleges such as the Banaras and Calcutta Colleges, and the different Colleges of the Princely States and the private and religious agencies, there was also the third channel through which the Sanskrit tradition continued to flow, namely, the one-Pandit schools.one-Pandit schools In fact, this tradition of one-Pandit schools was alive in all regions of India in a greater or lesser degree, according to the past history of each place. The tempo of modernisation had not fully swept away the Pandit of the traditional type and his institutions.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:22)

The Commission truthfully records the level of scholarshiplevel of scholarship among those Pandits. It states –

“We specially enquired whether the Pandits still carried on the tradition of writing new commentaries or dialectical works. We were sorry to note that the number of outstanding Pandits of the old type was generally not large; in some States, they could be counted on one's fingers. Some Pandits, however, did continue their literary activity; a few of them have, under the inspiration of modern research, produced critical and expository treatises in Sanskrit or in the regional languages on Sastraic and other general philosophical subjects.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:45)

It becomes evident from the above quote that the level of scholarship certainly has come down. But it has not died down completely.

Further, in the context of revival of Non-formal Śāstra Learning Systemnon-formal Śāstra Learning System the recent 2016 MHRD Committee states the following -

“Under this stream, Gurukula systemGurukula system will be revived and the expertise of traditional scholars who still adhere to their traditions and do not leave their place of residence will be utilized. Each such traditional Scholar of Shastric excellence will teach traditional Shastras in a traditional way maintaining their way of living and transmitting such knowledge”. (Vision and Road Map for the Development of Sanskrit: Report: 2016:26)

This quote also clearly testifies to the existence of traditional scholars with high level of erudition in Śāstra-s even today. The Sanskrit Commission also records the following regarding the existing level of scholarship during its period –

“We also found that the Sanskrit Muse was still an inspiration and that the Pandits everywhere wrote poems and plays in Sanskrit. Of course, Sanskrit was very freely used as a means of communicationmeans of communication and for the expression of all current ideas. We actually met some Pandits who could employ Sanskrit with eloquence and oratorical effect.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:45)

On the question of how the pandits maintain their level of scholarship and even refine it amidst the gloom of discouragement all around, the Commission states that–

“Among the activitiestemple!activities of, which keep up the scholarly interest of the Pandits and also afford them some encouragement and help, are the Sabhas or the Sadas (learned gatherings), which are held from time to time by rulers, Zamindars,Zamindars rich men, Acharyas and public associations. The former Princely States used to hold such gatherings once a year on the occasion of some festival, like the Dasara. The religious Teachers, Acharyas, still hold such gatherings of Pandits; also whenever any Pandit from a different part of the country visits an Acharya, he is engaged in a Sastrarthaśāstrārtha or is asked to lecture, and is honoured with presents and cash-gifts. There are also some private endowmentsendowments, private which arrange for such Pandit Sadas,Pandit Sadas once a year, on Rama-navami, Krishna-jayanti, and similar occasions. In some of the temples, Pandits are similarly invited to give expositions and are honoured. In fact, it was these public debates in Sastras which had been the main inspiration for the growth of the thought and literature in the field of Sanskrit. And it would be by their resuscitation that the old intensity of Sastra-learning could be retained and promoted.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:45)

The Commission records that along with the Traditional Pandits, ‘Sanskritists of the modern type’ had the capability to converse in Sanskrit. The following is the relevant quote from the report regarding this –

Just as many of the replies to the Questionnaire received by the Commission were in Sanskrit, quite a number of interviews also took place in Sanskrit. It was not the Pandits alone who gave their evidence in Sanskrit; many Sanskritists of the modern type also freely discussed with the Commission through the medium of Sanskrit. This once again proved that Sanskrit still continued to be the lingua francalingua franca of Sanskrit scholars of this country, irrespective of the different regions to which they belonged. (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:9)

Thus the Commission not only brings to light the contribution of individual Sanskrit scholars in the survival of Sanskrit but it also records the level of their knowledge as well as the modus operandimodus operandi by which sound scholarship is maintained. As vouched by recent MHRD Committee, such observations hold good even after almost five decades of the preparation of the first Sanskrit Commission Report.

3.1.2.e Nationalistic spirit – A catalyst to Sanskrit preservation

The Sanskrit Commission notes that the nationalistic spirit during the pre independence era also served to protect our culture and the language. The following are the words of the Sanskrit Commission in this regard –

“Two circumstances averted the rot to some extent: one, the Princely States and the native patterns of life there; and the other, the new awakening in the country of a nationalistic spiritnationalistic spirit which sought to make up for the drawbacks in the scheme of education on the cultural side by founding institutionsinstitutions!educational of cultural importance. Thanks to both of these, a network of Sanskrit collegesSanskrit!Colleges of a quasi-modern set-up came into being.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:28)

This indicates how Governmental support, or the lack of it, does not by itself settle something. The emotional bonding people have towards Sanskrit is what has sustained Sanskrit. The above quote might lead to an understanding that Sanskrit rides on the nationalistic spirit. But the Commission notes that the relation between Sanskrit and the nationalistic spirit is symbiotic.symbiotic relationship It states that Sanskrit has the potential to strengthen the solidarity of our nation. It observes –

“...a distinguished group of India's thought-leaders that Sanskrit can very well be rehabilitated as a pan-Indianpan-Indian speech, to strengthen the solidarity of Modern India. Indeed, to emphasise this point, a witness, appearing before the Commission, suggested that if the Sanskrit Commission had come before the States Reorganisation Commission, many of the recent bickerings in our national life could have been avoided.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:81)

3.1.2.f Role of NGO-Academies in keeping up popular interestNGOs

The following observation by the Sanskrit Commission regarding the active role played by non-Governmental, voluntary organizations, deals a decisive blow to the ‘governmental oxygen tank’ supposition of Pollock. The Commission’s report reads -

“In all regions there are now Sanskrit Academies, Associations, Sabhas, Parisads, etc., which organise the celebration of Sanskrit Poets' Days;Sanskrit!Poets' Days lectures on Sanskrit subjects; Sanskrit classes; competitions in Sanskrit essay-writing, Sanskrit elocution, and original composition (Short Story, Poem, Play); Sanskrit Recitals and Dramas; and publication of cheap booklets in Sanskrit. All of these keep up popular interest in Sanskrit. The names of many such associations, whose representatives met us, may be seen in the lists in the Appendices.” “The Sanskrit Sahitya Parishad,Sanskrit Sahitya Parishad, The Calcutta, the Sanskrit Academy,Sanskrit!Academy Madras, the Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan,Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan Bombay, the Samskrita Visva ParishadSamskrita Visva Parishad which has now over 500 branches all over India, the Brahmana Sabha,Brahmana Sabha Bombay, which has a Sanskrit dramatic troupe, the Akhil Bharatiya Samskrita Sahitya Sammelan, Delhi, may be specially mentioned among the bodies which have been doing sustained work of more than a local provenance. Recently, in Nagpur and Ujjain, societies have been established for the study and propagation of Kalidasa'sKālidāsa works, and we were pleased to note that the respective State Governments were helping these societies. The Kalidasa SocietyKalidasa Society at Ujjain, we were told, had a fund of Rs. 1 1/4 lakhs of its own. There are several organisations in the country whose object is to popularise the study of the GitaBhagavadgītā. Establishments like the Svadhyaya Mandal,Svadhyaya Mandal, role of Pardi, and the Veda-Dharma-Paripalana-Sangham,Veda-Dharma-Paripalana-Sangham, role of Kumbhakonam, take interest in the popularisation of Vedic thought and literature. Among the modern neo-Hindu movements, the Arya SamajArya Samaj and the Ramakrishna MissionRamakrishna Mission are doing excellent work for the spread of interest in Sanskrit and its knowledge. Many Sanskrit CollegesSanskrit!Colleges and the Sanskrit Departments of Colleges have Associations, which organise regular lectures on Sanskrit subjects, and sometimes also produce Sanskrit dramas.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:46)

The Commission also observes in this regard–

“For outside these educational institutions,institutions!educational there is in the country a network of voluntary organisations. The number and the extent of planned activities of these private bodies only underline the need for supplementing what is being done for Sanskrit through the official set-up.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:67)

The above comment is also an eye-opener. The government is required to supplement the work of voluntary organizations. This means that the zeal and impetus to preserve and perpetuate Sanskrit is already present in the people.

Going by the information currently available in the website of Rashtirya Sanskrit SansthanRashtirya Sanskrit Sansthan (for the year 2009-2010), 767 voluntary Sanskrit Institutions receive financial assistance from the Government. This is to give a pointer to the probable number of voluntary Sanskrit organizations that still exist in this country. This implies that there might be more organizations which do not receive or require governmental support for their activities.

3.1.2.g People in General – The Undercurrent

Apart from various agencies which operate in an organized manner, the Sanskrit Commission indicates the presence of an undercurrent of love for Sanskrit among the people of the country which keeps alive the tradition of Sanskrit learning and dissemination.

The Commission states that–

“it is possible for an Indian or a foreigner knowing no other language than Sanskrit to be able to find throughout the whole of India some persons everywhere who can communicate with him in Sanskrit”. (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:81)

Apart from indicating the pan-Indian presence of Sanskrit, the above statement may also imply that speakers of Sanskrit may be far and few in between. But regarding the undercurrent of love towards Sanskrit in the heart of people of this land, the Commission makes this remarkable observation–

“Generally speaking, the people of India love and venerate Sanskrit with a feeling which is next only to that of patriotism towards Mother India. This feeling permeates the common man, the litterateur and the educationist, the businessman, the administrator and the politician. Everybody realises its cultural importancecultural!importance and knows that whatever one cherishes as the best and the noblest in things Indian is embedded in Sanskrit.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:66)

Another noteworthy observation of the Commissions about the general feeling of people regarding Sanskrit comes during the discussion of national languagenational!language status for Sanskrit, a race which it lost to Hindi. It states –

“After Independence, the Constituent Assembly decided that the official languageofficial language of India was to be Hindi written in Devanagari script, and this was put in the Constitution. But the proceedings of the Constituent Assembly on this question were anything but smooth, and though there was a tacit agreement in this matter, Sanskrit never ceased to loom in the background. A general feeling was there that if the binding force of Sanskrit was taken away, the people of India would cease to feel that they were parts of a single culture and a single nation. The readiness with which Hindi received the support of a large section of the Indian people was because Hindi appeared to make a stand for Sanskrit. The support of Hindi in a way meant laying stress on the unity of India through Sanskrit, even if it were through the intermediacy of Hindi. The aspirations of a free Indian people, it was thought, could be best expressed through Sanskrit, functioning through the Modern Indian Languages.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:70)

Many state governments appointed Commissions prior to the first Sanskrit Commission to assess the interest of people in Sanskrit. These Commissions have time and again established the innate love among the masses towards Sanskrit. To quote the words of the Commission as an example -

“The old Madhya Pradesh Government had appointed in 1955 a Committee to go into the question of Sanskrit institutions,institutions!Sanskrit and here again, we would like to emphasise, the verdict of the public opinion had been in favour of preserving the traditional style of Sanskrit Education with the introduction of the necessary elements of modern knowledge.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:42)

The Commission makes an interesting remark which gives a sense that English education has inadvertently sparked off renewed interest in Sanskrit and culture. The lack of imparting of cultural educationcultural!education in the traditional set-up itself seems to have suggested to the educated people to turn to their roots. The Commission observes -

More recently, owing to a new awakening among the educated middle class and also owing to the interest of some of the leading citizens in the locality, expositions of the epics, the GitaBhagavadgītā, the Upanisads, Vedanta, Dharma,dharma etc., have become a regular and organised activity in some places. These expositions are arranged as public lectures to large audiences or as private classes to select groups. They have, indeed, proved a great source of help to the Pandits. The Pandits are in demand also for individual tuition in the Gita or Vedanta which some well-to-do persons desire to have. This appears to be an expanding activity and augurs well for the revival of interest in Sanskrit. (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:45)

In the same vein the Commission further observes that –

“In the course of our tours, we noticed everywhere an unmistakable awakening of the cultural consciousness of the people. There was a keen awareness of the importance of Sanskrit among people at large; and we soon realised that a complete picture of the situation regarding Sanskrit could not be had only by visiting Schools, Colleges, Universities and Pathasalas.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:67)

Thus, if the pāṭhaśāla-s, schools and colleges themselves cannot be the true indicators of the real situation of Sanskrit in the country, then it is very clear that the government, as has been shown above, which has not so favourable an attitude towards Sanskrit can never be the indicator of the situation of Sanskrit in the country. And Pollock’s statement that only the government oxygen tank helps survival of Sanskrit is grossly incorrect and his pronouncement of death of Sanskrit based on it is untenable.

Finally, regarding the role of general masses in the revival of Sanskrit the Commission states –

“These voluntary public activities in the field of Sanskrit are all-comprehensive - general and special, popular and learned, scholastic as well as artistic, literary as well as organisational. In fact, it was these activities among the general public which struck us as the most encouraging circumstance. They definitely pointed to the recapture of that spirit and atmosphere, which would help Sanskrit again to emerge with a fresh vitality and force.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:67)

3.1.3 What then is the role of the Government in promotion of Sanskrit?

The seven real factors for the perpetuation of the Sanskrit as brought to light by the Sanskrit Commission Report were presented above. Will this then mean that the Government has no role to play in the promotion and preservation of Sanskrit? The detailed report of the Commission indeed is full of recommendations to the Government in that regard. But the Commission is of a considered view that Sanskrit in no way, needs government ‘oxygen tanks’ or ‘feeding tubes’.Government feeding tubes Rather, to quote the words of the Commission -

“Already there are large endowmentsendowments and other resources in the country which, with the help and direction of the Government, can be properly harnessed for the purposes set forth by us.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:293)

Hence Pollock’s ‘government oxygen tank’ statement appears highly unwarranted and unrealistic. The Commission’s report implies that facilitation and not mere funding is what is required from the government towards preservation of Sanskrit. This is with regard to the first half of the statement of Pollock which is the main focus of this paper.

3.2 The Second part of Pollock’s Statement and its Response - Some observers who won’t agree!

Let us also consider the second half of Pollock’s statement and the Sanskrit Commissions “responses” to that briefly before concluding this paper. The second half of the statement of Pollock reads –“…but most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead”. (Pollock 2001: 393).

3.2.a Observers - 1

At the outset, it is obvious that the highly qualified members of Sanskrit Commission are not part of the team of Pollock’s brand of ‘observers’. It is to be noted that the members of Sanskrit Commission were not mere scholars, but they were ‘observers’ too, but in a real sense. As has been stated in the introduction, the members of the Commission travelled the length and breadth of the country. The itinerary of the various scholars, by the day and by the hour even, is available as official documents. In the course of their work, they keenly “observed” not only the state of Sanskrit but also the stature of Sanskrit. Further they clearly indicate that Sanskrit is not dead. Hence there is no question of its revival. It’s just an issue of modernizationmodernization of Sanskrit. The following quote captures the Sanskrit Commission’s take on whether Sanskrit is dead-

“Sanskrit at that time permeated all aspects of Indian life, and so there could be no question of reviving it. Only there was an attempt to modernise its study. The place of Sanskrit in Indian life and in the Indian set-up was taken for granted by the nationalist workers before Independence. When Bankim Chandra ChatterjiChatterji, Bankim Chandra composed his National Song Vande MataramVande Mātaramnational!song about the year 1880, he could not have foreseen what an importance this song would later on acquire in the national movement, of which the two words, Vande Mataram, practically became the basic mantra, the Rastra-Gayatri,Rastra-Gayatri if we may say so. He composed this song in Sanskrit (with a few Bengali sentences within) as the most natural thing. The place of Sanskrit was so obvious that no one gave any special thought to it.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:69)

The following quote from the Commission’s report is even more powerfully direct on whether Sanskrit is dead or alive –

“Even at the present day Sanskrit is very very living, because a large number of people use Sanskrit in their conversation, when they come from different parts of the country, and composition in Sanskrit, in both prose and verse, goes on almost unabated. It has been possible to write a history of recent Sanskrit literatureSanskrit!literature, recent as it has developed, say, during the last century and a half. Entire conferencesconferences are conducted wholly or at least to a very large extent through the medium of Sanskrit.Sanskrit!medium of In the popular Purana recitations, the reciters who have all the art of telling a story dramatically use by preference a highly Sanskritised Bengali, Telugu, Oriya, Kannada or Panjabi, which is largely understood even by the unlettered masses. It is not uncommon to find religious lecturers giving discourses in simple Sanskrit, and they are generally understood by people possessing a slight education in their own mother-tongues. And above all, there is a tremendous love, which is something very close to veneration, for Sanskrit.Sanskrit!veneration for And when Sanskrit is now being used even to express modern scientific or political ideas in essays or discourses on various modern subjects, it cannot be said to have closed the door to further development - it has still life in it. All these things would go to establish that Sanskrit is still a living forceliving force in Indian life. It would be almost suicidal to neglect and gradually to relegate into oblivion as something dead and useless this very vital source of national culture and solidarity.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:88-89)

3.2.b Observers - 2

The Commission quotes University Education Commission (p.3) (December 1948 - August 1949) and states that – “Sanskrit was best suited for spiritual trainingspiritual training, Sanskrit in as it embodies the element of morality in the larger sense.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:3)

Again, the esteemed members of University Education Commission who seem to envisage a futuristic role for Sanskrit in moral and spiritual education, also are not part of Pollock’s ‘observers’ team.

3.2.c Observers - 3

The members of Official Languages CommissionOfficial Languages Commission (OLC) (June 1955-June 1956) of the Government of India, quoted in the First Sanskrit Commission report also do not seem to be in Pollock’s ‘most observers’. Because, they state (p.4)-

“It is hardly necessary to add that, besides the current regional languages, there is an immense amount of work which needs to be done in respect of Sanskrit, Pali, Prakrits, Apabhramsa, etc. The Sanskrit language pre-eminently and the other ancient languages in different degrees have powerfully influenced current Indian speeches and a study of these has an obvious' bearing on the study of contemporary forms of speech" (p. 218). The OLC observations quoted by Sanskrit Commission further states that (p.4) "All our languages, including what are known as the Dravidian languages,Dravidian languages have through all the centuries habitually drafted, in a greater or less degree, to meet every new situation and requirement for expression of a new idea or shade of meaning, upon that vast and inexhaustible treasure-house of vocabulary, phrase, idiom and concept comprised by the Sanskrit language and literature. The RamayanaRamayana and the Mahabharata,Mahabharata the Puranas and the Sastras, the Classical poems, dramas and literary masterpieces of Sanskrit have served throughout those centuries not only as the reservoir of ideas, sentiments and parables to be drawn by all for the embellishment of their literary output, but also as benchmarks of literary excellence, as standards for social conduct, as examplars of morality, and, in short, as the repository of wit and wisdom of all the Indian peoples throughout the ages..." (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:4)

3.2.d Observers – 4

Interestingly, even Jawaharlal NehruNehru!Jawaharlal does not agree that Sanskrit is dead. The Commission quotes independent India’s first prime minister in this regard. It states–

“When Jawaharlal Nehru made the following observations about the importance of Sanskrit in India, he only reiterated the general belief of the Indian people, and the considered views which have been expressed not only by the greatest thinkers and leaders of India, but also by foreign scholars and specialists in Indian history and civilisation who are in a position to appraise objectively the value of Sanskrit: “If I was asked what is the greatest treasure which India possesses and what is her finest heritage, I would answer unhesitatingly it is the Sanskrit language and literature, and all that it contains. This is a magnificent inheritance, and so long as this endures and influences the life of our people, so long the basic genius of India will continue".” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:71-72)

The Commission’s report also brings in another quote from the Jawaharlal Nehru to imply that Sanskrit is not only alive, but it is the language that has the potential to even out the balance in education which is leaning towards only the sciences. The report reads –

“And specially in modern times when a sort of dangerous over-weightage is being given to Sciences and Technology, the Humanities in Sanskrit will prove greatly helpful in restoring the proper balance. It is, indeed, highly significant that, as Prime Minister Shri NehruNehru!Jawaharlal told this Commission, Professor Oppenheimer,Oppenheimer the great American atomic scientist, spends considerable time in reading Sanskrit and Pali.” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:76)

3.2.e Observers - 5

It seems that even (most) Western Universities and its academia are not part of “the observers” of Pollock who declared Sanskrit as dead. The Commission’s report states - “...the West knows India as “Sanskrit India",“Sanskrit India” and whenever an Indian University celebrates its jubilee, a Western University normally sends its felicitations in a Sanskrit address...” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:89)

Adding a contemporary dimension to this, even in 2007 when the then president of India APJ Abdul Kalam visited Greece he was greeted by his Greece counterpart Karolos PapouliasPapoulias, Karolos in Sanskrit. A news report on this states –

“It was a pleasant surprise for President A P J Abdul KalamKalam, APJ Abdul when his Greek counterpart Karolos Papoulias greeted him in Sanskrit at the banquet ceremony hosted in honour of the visiting dignitary. “Rashtrapati Mahabhaga, Suswagatam Yavana deshe Bhawatam (Mr President, welcome you in Greece)", thus began the Greek President his speech at the banquet hosted at the Presidential palace on Thursday night much to the delight of the Indian delegation” (Times of India, Apr 27, 2007)

Thus it becomes evident from the above that, like the first part of Pollock’s statement, the second part too, to state in the language of Tarka (Indian Logic), seems to have a sat-pratipakṣasat-pratipakṣa (a valid counter-example) in the light of the First Sanskrit Commission Report.

4 Conclusion:

Based on the views gleaned from the Sanskrit Commission’s report (1957), it could be seen that, considered whether in parts or as a whole, one of the very initial statements of Pollock in his paper Death of Sanskrit (2001), has been rendered null and void decades prior to his statement.

With respect to this statement, this redundancy might be attributed to the non-serious and frivolous outlook of Pollock, if the following might be taken as an inadvertent admission towards that end in his article “The Death of Sanskrit”. In the sentence that precedes ‘oxygen tank’ statement he states - “Its cultivation constitutes largely an exercise in nostalgia for those directly involved, and, for outsiders, a source of bemusement that such communication takes place at all.” (Pollock 2001:393)

True. For an outsider (like Pollock) Sanskrit might be a “source of bemusement”. But the insiders, whose views have been adequately presented in Sanskrit Commission’s report, look at Sanskrit as (p.279) - “…one of the bases of our national culture and solidarity” (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:279) and as the source that “will provide a base for the promotion of International Understanding in the East and the West”. (Sanskrit Commission of India Report 1957:279)

Bibliography

“Greek Prez greets Kalam in Sanskrit” (2007, Apr 27), Times of India,Times of India (newspaper) http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/world/europe/Greek-Prez-greets-Kalam-in-Sanskrit/articleshow/1965800.cms Accessed on 21 March 2017.
Pollock, Sheldon (April 2001). “The Death of Sanskrit" (PDF). Comparative Studies in Society and History. 43(2): 392–426.
Sanskrit Commission of India (1956-57): (Report accessed from the website of Information Repository of Education in India:)Information Repository of Education http://www.teindia.nic.in/mhrd/50yrsedu/u/45/3Z/Toc.htm. Accessed on 09 January, 2017.
Vision and Road Map for the Development of SanskritVision and Road Map for the Development of Sanskrit – Ten year Perspective Plan: (Report accessed from the website of Rashtriya Sanskrit Sansthan:) http://www.sanskrit.nic.in/016_02_12_Vision_and_Road_Map_or_the_Development_of_Sanskrit_Ten_year_perspective_Plan.pdf. Accessed on 09 January, 2017.

Chapter 7 Sanskrit: the Phoenix Phenomenon

K S Kannan and H R Meera

Introduction

The stalwarts of Western Indology have been held in great esteem for a long time now and in many instances their word has been taken as final on various topics. The extensive studies that they have made, the intense interest they have shown in learning about an alien culture, and the inter-disciplinarity they have brought into the studies have all been, rightly, respected. This bespeaks, though, of a scholar subjecting a specimen to scrutiny where the specimen is passive, at the receiving end of the attention.

For a true intellectual exchange to happen, however, it is necessary for both the parties – the examiner and the examined - to interact as equals, subjecting each other and each other’s methods to scrutiny. The current paper is one such attempt - to return the attention by considering the claim of “death of Sanskrit” made by Sheldon Pollock, a leading American Orientalist, in his paper of 2001.

This paper aims to

(a)
summarize the points made by him in as dispassionate and accurate a manner as possible,
(b)
analyse the same from various angles,
(c)
discuss the propriety of the data selected and analysed by him,
(d)
discuss the general methodological idiosyncrasiesmethodological idiosyncrasies betrayed in his writings, and
(e)
provide pointers to the uttarapakṣin-s – as to where further work is necessary to possibly uncover more data, and do greater justice to the issue.

In the following section (1), we briefly present the issues (that Pollock touches upon) more-or-less as bullet points in order to capture their essence (words within double quotes “ ” are the ones cited verbatim from Pollock).

1 Synopsis of the thesis

The introductory portion of the essay gives us a picture of Pollock’s take on the political scenariopower!political (viz. the ascent to power of BJPBJP) which makes Sanskrit as the main actor in its identity politicsidentity politics. In sum, his take is that Hindus are being fed a distorted picture of their past (“HindutvaHindutva propagandists have sought to show...that Sanskrit is indigenous to India...Sanskrit is considered...the source and sole preserver of world culture” (Pollock 2001:392)). He traces its “melancholy” roots to the early days of independence when Sanskrit was included as one of the recognised languages of the Republic of India. Even though this has ensured that Sanskrit UniversitiesSanskrit!Universities and institutionsinstitutions!Sanskrit have received a lot of funding, Sanskrit literature does not show any growth. Even with all the awards, grants, and promotion via All India Radio, school curricula etc, Sanskrit is as good as being in a coma, kept alive artificially “as an exercise in nostalgia”. And hence “in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead”.

Pollock points out that the long history of Sanskrit makes it difficult to have one measure of vitalitymeasure of vitality given “the different historical rhythms” (Pollock 2001:394) but he decides on a measure in that very paragraph – viz. the production of kāvya, since “it is in itself often an argument of how language is to be used , indeed, about how life is to be lived” (Pollock 2001:394)implying that he will decide on the life of Sanskrit based solely on the quality[1] and quantity of the production ofkāvya.

After quoting a Gujarati poet who talks of the ‘death of Sanskrit’ in 1857, he terms that this story is “only part, and only intuition”, which implies that he is about to provide the full story, sans an intuitional approach, and with hard evidence.

In order to prove his avowed thesis of the death of Sanskrit literary culture as a historical process, he selects 4 points in history where we see disappearance or degeneration of Sanskrit literature – viz

(a)
Kashmir after 13th century CE
(b)
Vijayanagara after 16th century CE
(c)
Mughal court in mid-17th century CE
(d)
Bengal in the 19th century CE

We will summarize the essential points for all the four stages in history (sections 1.1 to 1.4) followed by the summary of his conclusion as the fifth part (1.5).

1.1 Kashmir:

1.1.1

Pollock gives a detailed picture - of the presentation of Śrīkaṇṭha CaritaŚrīkaṇṭhacarita by MaṅkhaMaṅkha in the royal assemblage in the presence of several preeminent scholars. The description of this peak of brilliant scholarship is followed by the denouement that this was the last of Kashmir’s generation of Sanskrit poets of note. He narrates in detail how the production of literature “reduced to stotra-sstotra literature”, and how nothing innovative by way of literary theories got produced at all after the 11th century.

1.1.2

The nearly dead Sanskrit tradition (during the reign of Hindu kings) is revived during the reign of the Muslim ruler Sultan Zain-ul-'abidinZain-ul-"'abidin who established peace after a long period of tumult. Here did get composed Jonarāja’sJonarāja RājataraṅgiṇīRājataraṅgiṇī!(Jonarāja) along the lines of Kalhaṇa’sKalhaṇa, “only, much less aesthetic”, in the words of Pollock and the work of ŚrīvaraŚrīvara continuing that (again, a barer chronicle than its predecessor). Pollock also mentions that even though there was no serious original work from Śrīvara, his SubhāṣitāvalīSubhāṣitāvalī implies a “reasonably accomplished curatorial study of Sanskrit at the Sultan’s court or had a substantial library”. A significant conclusion of Pollock here is this: even though Śrīvara’s anthology mentions a number of poets regarding whom much is not known (and hence could have lived and produced work during that 300 year period - where Pollock claims not much work was done), the samples in the anthology do not prove that anything of significance got produced in the literary field between the 12th and 15th centuries

1.1.3

Pollock lists the possible reasons for this literary collapse viz. (i) loss of important texts (ii) Mongol invasionMongol invasion of 1320 (iii) simple non-availability of textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) to modern editors. He then dismisses them all in one stroke that they do not seem likely. His reasoning is this: important textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) were getting written and transmitted out of Kashmir for several centuries and for the centuries under question, there is nothing such that has happened; hence, nothing got produced during the time. According to him, the textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) of the works that have been preserved, date to 12th century or even earlier, which strengthens the case that nothing got produced after 12th century.

1.1.4

For the singular death of the literary culture, Pollock traces the reason to the changes in socio-political sphere. His argument goes thus: It was because of the royal patronagepatronage (what he calls “courtly-civic ethos”) that Sanskrit sustained its vitality; during this period, however, there was no royal patronage,patronage and this caused Sanskrit literature to die. The Hindu kings who have been described by Kalhaṇa were breaching the limits of degeneracy and situations got much worse as time passed. He substantiates the evidence of deterioration by citing a paucity of any mention of good works, or indeed, any poets, in Jonarāja’s RājataraṅgiṇīRājataraṅgiṇī!(Jonarāja).

1.1.5

Concluding, Pollock draws attention to a passage in Jonarāja’s work which describes how the Sultan longed to have “an epiphany” with Goddess Śāradā, but how he ended up breaking Her image. Pollock quotes Jonarāja “This no doubt occurred...because of the presence of the barbarians. A king is held responsible for the transgressions of his underlings”.

1.2 Vijayanagara

1.2.1

The second sample chosen is the multilingual empire of Vijayanagara which had inscriptions issued in Kannada, Telugu, Sanskrit and Tamil. He states that the 350 years of the empire saw literary productions in Telugu, Tamil and Sanskrit. His accusation here is that even though the rulers were of Tulu or Kannada lineages, they did very little to promote courtly literature in Kannada

1.2.2

The example he picks up is, of course, of KṛṣṇadevarāyaKṛṣṇadevarāya (who ruled from 1509-1529 CE). According to Pollock there was only TimmaṇṇakaviTimmaṇṇa(kavi) as the Kannaḍa court poet whose only accomplishment was the completion of Kumāravyāsa’s BhārataBhārata (of Kumāravyāsa). KṛṣṇadevarāyaKṛṣṇadevarāya himself wrote his work Āmukta-mālyadaĀmukta-mālyada in Telugu. While the courtly poetry in Kannada was so limited, the Kannada literature outside the court was thriving – with the saint-poets like PurandaradāsaPurandaradāsa and KanakadāsaKanakadāsa, and poets like LakṣmīśaLakṣmīśa whose Jaimini BhārataJaimini Bhārata is very popular even to this day. The contrast, he says, is very stark.

1.2.3

He then comments on the paradoxes in the Sanskrit literature of the time. In his opinion, while there was phenomenal scholarship in Sanskrit (“almost industrialized magnitude” p401), the literary creativity was exhausted. The administrators of the kingdom were very learned in terms of cultural literacy as well, but according to him, their learning was only reproductive and not original.

1.2.4

The Sanskrit compositions that were produced in that period did not get, according to him, much circulation. They saw some immediate productions and were read during their time but didn’t attract much attention – no commentator glossed on them, nor were verses selected for an anthology, nor did they become a part of some curriculum. He surmises that “much may have been lost when the city was sacked in 1565 but works of major court poets and personalities do survive”. He expresses his curiosity in learning why these survived at all.

1.2.5

He reasons that much was written with “vital literary energies” in the vernaculars. He compares the two Bhārata-sBharatavarsa that were created viz. the Kannada production of KumāravyāsaKumāravyāsa, which did not receive any royal patronage,patronage and the Sanskrit production of DivākaraDivākara, which did. The former was quite popular, while the latter lay mostly unread[2]

1.2.6

He then examines the titles that KṛṣṇadevarāyaKṛṣṇadevarāya had – kāvya-nāṭaka-marmajña, kavitā-prāvīṇya-phaṇīśa and sakala-kalā-bhoja – and mentions the Jāmbavatī-pariṇaya that Rāya composed as being much praised by the erudite scholars who were present for its performance (p 402). He gives a brief sketch of the story which is originally from Bhāgavata-purāṇaBhāgavata Purāṇa and goes on to critique that there is nothing new literarily in the adaptation. However, he finds that this work is of interest to him because of how this fits, according to him, the political narrative of Vijayanagara Empire.

The play in Sanskrit (with the female characters therein using the Prakrit language) is as usual, but the Sanskrit was no longer associated with sacredness (“sacrality...associated with Sanskrit had been neutralized centuries before”, to cite Pollock). So he considers the question as to why Kṛṣṇadevarāya chose to compose in Sanskrit while the vernacular was the more powerful. His conclusion is that the kāvya is “profoundly historicist-political” – more so than the previously composed carita-s, vijaya-s and abhyudaya-s that gave poetic accounts of military conquests; and for the reason that it was so closely tied to the history of its day, it ceased to be of interest at a later date.

1.2.7

He concludes with the note that Sanskrit as a mode of personal expression was on its death-bed, and what it could express was only the concerns of the empire. So, when the empire disappeared, that sounded, he says, the death knell for Sanskrit as well.

1.3 Mughal Court

1.3.1

Choosing an individual for anecdotal evidence (rather than a period as he does in the aforesaid cases) Pollock calls Jagannātha PaṇḍitarājaJagannātha, Paṇḍitarāja (circa 17th century CE) (Sarma 1994:6-8) “the Last Sanskrit Poet”, and embarks on tracing his life and times (“very close to us in time, and yet we have almost as little concrete evidence about him as we have about the fourth-century master KālidāsaKālidāsa” (Pollock 2001:404)).

1.3.2

In Pollock’s opinion, the output of Jagannātha in his capacity of a court poet is much like any other court poet’s. RasagaṅgādharaRasagaṅgādhara, Jagannātha’s famous work on Alaṅkāra-śāstraAlaṅkāra-śāstra, has all “the same assumptions, procedures and goals” as its predecessors in the field (implying it has added nothing new to the space). Likewise do the “panegyrics to the kings of Udaipur and Delhi and Assam which remain largely indistinguishable from centuries of such productions” (Pollock 2001:404).

1.3.3

However, Pollock says “one senses in his lyrics and even in his scholarly works some very new sensibility, which...might fairly be called a modern subjectivity” (2001:404-405). Tracing the story of Jagannātha - of breaking away from orthodoxy and falling in love with a Muslim woman,Muslim!woman and finally ending his life by drowning in the GaṅgāGaṅgā - Pollock asserts : “Something very old died when Jagannātha died, and also something very new.”

1.3.4

He then brings in the data about paṇḍits who called themselves ‘navya’ and presented works with new terminology, style, and modes of analysis that was radically different from the earlier ones. He however raises a question as to whether this radical change was merely a question of details or whether it pertained to the structure. Recounting the works of Bhaṭṭoji DīkṣitaBhaṭṭoji Dīkṣita, Nīlakaṇṭha CaturdharaNīlakaṇṭha Caturdhara, and Gāgā BhaṭṭaGāgā Bhaṭṭa, he also draws attention to the change of the political scenario of the time viz. the rise of MarathaMaratha power.power!political

1.3.5

He then talks of how the past and the present (i.e. mid-17th century CE) subtly but clearly got separated though there was no overt schism between the “prācyaprācya” and “navya”prācya and navya. To look at the socio-political milieu of scholarship, Pollock picks up two traditional scholars viz. SiddhicandraSiddhicandra (1587–1666 CE), a Jain monk in the court of AkbarAkbar and JahangirJahangir, and Kavīndrācārya SarasvatīKavīndrācārya Sarasvatī (1600–75), a leading paṇḍit of VārāṇasīVārāṇasī – and contrasts them with Jagannātha.

1.3.6

Siddhicandra,Siddhicandra a man of great personal beauty and for that reason a favourite with the two Mughal emperors, was a Jain monk. He has written an autobiography which is the basis for the conclusions drawn by Pollock. Writing about the general socio-political atmosphere of the day, Pollock paints it as being very open to new ideas. The evidence forwarded are : the writings of Abul FazalAbul Fazal and the attitudes of AkbarAkbar himself; large scale translations that were happening from Sanskrit to PersianPersian; Mughal courtiers like Abdur RahimRahim, Abdur who were themselves experimenting with writing in Sanskrit; and lastly, Sanskrit intellectuals, including young Siddhicandra, who were learning Persian.

Even with such exposure to cosmopolitan life, the writings of Siddhicandra stay, according to Pollock, intellectually at the 12th century instead of in the 17th century. In his Kāvyaprakāśa-khaṇḍanaKāvyaprakāśa-khaṇḍana, critiquing Mammaṭa’sMammaṭa work, he calls himself ‘navya’ and yet the intellectual content is the same (Pollock 2001:406). Pollock generalizes next about the “newness” of the “new” intellectuals:

“They certainly strove for ever greater precision and sophistication of definition and analysis (in imitation, in fact, of the New Logic), but these matters of style were far more striking than any substantive innovation... Beyond such innovations in analytic idiom, however, what may be most importantly new here is the self-proclaimed newness itself, and its intimation that the past is somehow passed, even if it will not go completely away.” (Pollock 2001:407)

1.3.7

Turning his attention to Siddhicandra’s autobiography (which Pollock sees as centering around Siddhicandra’s celebration of his maintenance of the traditional moral vision of his own self) Pollock expatiates on the “dramatic core” of the text. To sum it up, it is how the king and queen try to persuade Siddhicandra to renounce his celibacy, and how steadfast Siddhicandra is in his adherence to his monastic vows. Pollock finds it “especially suggestive of the nature of Sanskrit literary culture at this moment that all innovation—the narrative and literary and discursive novelty—should be in service of the oldest of Jain monastic ideals” (Pollock 2001:407).

1.3.8

Next comes Kavīndrācārya Sarasvatī in whom, Pollock bewails, even radical alteration of social environment produced no commensurate transformation of cultural vision. The scholar earned fame for persuading Shah JahanShah Jahan from levying jizyajizya tax on the pilgrims to VaranasiVārāṇasī and PrayagPrayag. He was patronized by Prince Dara ShikohDara Shikoh and later accompanied the French traveller François BernierBernier, François for over three years. Yet, his literary production, according to Pollock, was very conventional: his Sanskrit work was, glossorial and hymnal while his Hindi production was of greater value. He also owned a big library ($>2000$ manuscripts) (which was probably due to the pension from the Mughal emperor, Pollock is so quick to point out).

With this, Pollock comes to the judgement part :“What Sanskrit learning in the seventeenth century prepared one best to do, one might infer from the lives and works of Siddhicandra and Kavīndra, was to resist all other learning.” (Pollock 2001:408)

1.3.9

The contrast by way of Jagannātha is presented next. He too had similar exposure to cosmopolitan life; he too enjoyed the patronagepatronage of Dara Shikoh like Kavīndrācārya. But, Pollock points out, the effect of these on Jagannātha’s literary production was different – that Jagannātha got inspirations from vernacular textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic). Unlike Siddhicandra who was steadfast in his celibacy, Jagannātha had a personal life where he was linked to a Muslim womanMuslim!woman. Pollock sees the verses written by Jagannātha regarding this beloved as being like nothing else before or after. He forwards the opinion that it was all because Jagannātha’s poetry was informed by Persian literature through social interactions, and that this is a manifestation of the theme of the ever-unattainable ‘mahbūbmahbūb’, the unattainability exaggerated by ethnic difference.

Similarly, Jagannātha introduces a personal tone in his scholarly as well as poetic works, Pollock opines. Be it responding to the scholar who insulted his guru, or providing demonstrative examples for various tropes in his Rasa-gaṅgādhara, Jagannātha brings in an individual element. Pollock asseverates that though other poets earlier have shown individuality and projected distinctive selves, there is “still something new in what Jagannātha is doing”. Jagannātha writes about “the death of his child”, while no one has written of such personal sorrow before.

Pollock however cedes that there is difficulty in painting a naive picture of Jagannātha putting out his emotions thus – that there is inconsistency in merging the emotional poet who is venting his lament in the poem, and the detached scholar who is clinically dissecting the same poem in Rasa-gaṅgādhara. Pollock admits that he is stumped with “the discontinuities in Jagannātha’s poetry and theory”. He considers the possible explanations – that Jagannātha considered it inauspicious to have written about the death of his wife; and are we not supposed to consider them “the expressions of his true self?”; that he had forgotten that these were the verses on the death of his wife. Pollock discards all these possibilities and concludes that the philological method, by way of critically editing Bhāminīvilāsa, is the only way to analyse this. “Or did a stupid editor mix verses up after Jagannātha’s death?” – Pollock muses.

He concludes that the. greatest Sanskrit literary critic and poet of the age composed verses on the death of his wife, who happened to be a Muslim – and even if it was not Jagannātha who wrote those verses, whoever wrote those did a ‘first’ in Sanskrit. This newness, he says, “was born - and died”.

1.4 Bengal

1.4.1

For the fourth period, Pollock gives a report that the British RajBritish Raj did of the census of institutionsinstitutions!educational of learning in Bengal. While students who studied various śāstra-s in the 353 Sanskrit schoolsSanskrit!schoolsSanskrit!Colleges were all brahmins, those studying Persian at Muslim schools had a mixture of Hindu and Muslim students of whom a fraction were brahmins. The curricula at the Sanskrit schools which popularly taught NyāyaNyāya, VyākaraṇaVyākaraṇa and other śāstra-s with some students pursuing literature, had textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) from 4th to 12th centuries, and only one work from contemporary Bengal.

1.4.2

Even though a lot of Sanskrit literature was being produced, no kāvya situated itself, Pollock says, in the world of early colonialismcolonialism, whereas Nyāya tradition thrived by addressing the issues at hand (Viśvanātha Tarkapañcānana’sViśvanātha Tarkapañcānana Siddhānta-muktāvalīSiddhānta-muktāvalī reorganized received wisdom and found acceptance all over the subcontinent). Hence Pollock concludes that the network which worked with Sanskrit intellectuals across the nation was intact but no one inserted literary textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) into this network (hence they were not worth inserting). He points out that Sanskrit imagination saw nothing new even when the production of literature was thriving. Be it in TanjoreTanjore or JaipurJaipur or MysoreMysore, the court-patronized productions never left the court, and the court-produced literature ceased to make history.

1.4.3

Pollock notes that whatever was necessary to impact people even outside of literature, be it the struggles against Christian missionizing or the anti-colonial pamphlets of Ishwar Chandra VidyasagarIshwar Chandra Vidyasagar (who was the founder of the Calcutta Sanskrit CollegeCalcutta Sanskrit College), it was the vernacular that was used. Hence, Pollock says, Sanskrit can hardly be called alive if it was not a ‘vehicle for living thought’.

1.4.4

Pollock’s final word on this is: Yes, Sanskrit paṇḍits aspire to create a literary-cultural realm where KālidāsaKālidāsa would have been at home; someone who does not have this 2000-year legacy (such as William AdamAdam, William who conducted the aforementioned census in the 1830s) will not feel the weight of dead poets and scholars still being quite alive for them. But there is no point wasting criticism on them like Adam did. All the things that Adam criticized about the culture are actually central values of Sanskrit literature, which can only be appreciated by those who have the necessary cultural training.

However, Pollock asserts that the question is actually why and when Sanskrit literature became a practice of repetition and not renewal, and why the capacity to reimagine the world was lost to Sanskrit for ever.

1.5 Conclusions

1.5.1

That there can be no straightforward narrative to fit the above four moments into a plausible single historical narrative, Pollock readily recognizes; but he wants to recognize, in general terms, how a great tradition can die – implying that the when of the death of Sanskrit tradition is a given and is in the past, and that we only have to figure out the how and why.

1.5.2

He brings in the comparison with other dead languagesdead languages like Greek and Latin. Greek is ruled out straightaway, but Pollock sees the later history of LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) as showing great similarities to that of Sanskrit. Slow death, first losing out as the vehicle of literary expression while continuing to be expression for learned discourse; periodic renewals or forced rebirths, sometimes connected with “politics of translocal aspiration”; the way it “ever more exclusively associated with narrow forms of religion and priestcraft, despite centuries of secular aesthetic” (Pollock 2001:415) – these points are common to both. The contrast is with regard to communicative competence which was lost for LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) with vernacularization, whereas Sanskrit continued to be known and studied - by the very people who promoted the vernacularsvernaculars.

1.5.3

Acknowledging the difference between LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) and Sanskrit, he wants to locate the cause of the death of Sanskrit in the “South Asian historical experience”. He dismisses outright the decline of Sanskrit culture with Islamic ruleIslamic rule, saying that it is historically untenable even though the contemporary climate (implying the political atmosphere of today) favours the theory. It is his firm conviction that it was the “barbarous invader” who was trying to revive Sanskrit, while “a set of much long-term cultural, social, and political changes” caused the death.

1.5.4

Paraphrasing his thoughts on the last-mentioned changes: It was the court that took care of Sanskrit, and when there was internal enfeeblement there, it naturally affected Sanskrit. Then there was the competition between vernacularsvernaculars and Sanskrit for recognition. These factors did not act in equal force everywhere. In Kashmir it took a toll on Sanskrit because of eroded ethos. By 13th century, before the Turkish rulers established themselves, it had already died and hence they can’t be held responsible for it. In Vijayanagara, the literature produced was predictable and hollow. Anything which was literarily important was said in Telugu or, outside the court, in Kannada or Tamil. Those who didn’t have such content wrote in Sanskrit and were never read. The same was the case in the North, where vernacular held the sway. Whatever was important and urgent had to be said in the vernacular and the cosmopolitan Sanskrit made less and less sense in this regional world.

1.5.5

Any structures that came to take collective action against incidents — like abuse of pilgrims, through sending petitions — never became institutionalized; instead they remained transitory, narrow goals. The “new” intellectuals had nothing new in substance to offer but only in style. No new idiom came to life to even articulate the new relationship with the past, forget critiquing it. No new knowledge, no new theory of religious, let alone political, identity was produced to reflect the changes that were being seen. No new creation of literature in a sustained manner came to be.

Pollock ends this with

“the mental and social spheres of Sanskrit literary production grew ever more constricted, and the personal and this-worldly, and eventually even the presentist-political, evaporated, until only the dry sediment of religious hymnology remained... At all events, the fact remains that well before the consolidation of colonialismcolonialism, before even the establishment of the Islamicate political order, the mastery of tradition had become an end in itself for Sanskrit literary culture, and reproduction, rather than revitalization, the overriding concern... In the field of powerpower!political of the time, the production of Sanskrit literature had become a paradoxical form of life where prestige and exclusivity were both vital and terminal.’(Pollock 2001:417-418)

2. Analysis of the “analysis”

Pollock’s acclaim as a Sanskritist leads one to expect a dispassionate presentation of facts and deductions in the subject. However he catches the reader’s attention in the very first paragraph by his overtly political tonepolitical!tone in contextualizing his writing. He describes the ‘Hindutva’Hindutva forcesHindutva!forces which have captured powerpower!political and are bent on presenting distorted pictures of the past to the masses, essentially changing the narrative which has been set in the past decades.

In this section, we take specific points from the summary above for analysis, and group logically linked points even if they are chronologically apart. Due to fear of prolixity, we will not do detailed analyses of all the points. Where necessary, we shall be referring to the point summed up in the synopsis in section B.

2.1 What is the purpose of knowledge?

In a culture that defines the four valid goals of lifelife, valid goals of – dharma,dharma arthaartha, kāmakāma, and mokṣamokṣa– and where the first three are to be subservient to the last one (even though the fourth is sometimes subsumed under the first), everything is aligned to the last of the puruṣārthapuruṣārtha-s, however mediated the link.

The only thing that needs to be done for its own sake is, according to our tradition, the preservation of the Veda-sVeda. As PatañjaliPatañjali says ‘brāhmaṇena niṣkāraṇaḥ vedaḥ saṣaḍaṅgo ‘dhyeyo jñeyaś ca’(MahābhāṣyaMahābhāṣya, PaspaśāhnikaPaspaśāhnika) [For a brāhmaṇa, one whose principal pursuit is knowledge, the Veda-sVeda along with all the six Vedāṅga-s, are to be studied and understood for no putative reason whatsoever]. This is so since the Veda-sVeda are considered to be the first manifestation of the Ultimate Truth whose knowledge leads to mokṣa. Hence, even the niṣkāraṇa part of Patañjali’s quote refers to doing so with no eye on worldly gain.

Everything is done for the sake of putting us on the path to this final goal– even kāma in its right place, and within bounds leads to that. Each point in time is linked to this ultimate goal, from before birth to beyond death (niṣekādi-smaśānāntaḥ: ManusmṛtiManusmṛti 2.16), and all key actions take the form of yajña-syajña. Even the consumption of food is linked to the ultimate goal:

āhārārthaṁ karma kuryād anindyaṁ /
kuryād āhāraṁ prāṇa-sandhāraṇārtham |
prāṇās sandhāryās tattva-vijñāna-hetos /
tattvaṁ jñeyaṁ yena bhūyo na janma || (cf Bhāgavata 11.18.34)

[Translation (ours): Take up a blameless profession for the sake of earning your food; partake of food but to sustain life; sustain life in order to know the Truth; and know that Truth as a consequence of which one is no more subject to rebirth]

Everyone is linked in a hierarchical manner to follow the leader, the pursuer of knowledge, so that each person is aligned to a path of his/her choice (sve sve karmaṇy abhirataḥ saṁsiddhiṁ labhate naraḥ - BhagavadgītāBhagavadgītā 18.45) which ultimately leads to the Summum Bonum.

Even the kāvyakāvya is a part of educating oneself to align in the right direction. Called kāntā-saṁmitakāntā-saṁmita, it is a part of the system to hand values to the people (the other two being the Veda-sVeda and Purāṇa-s).

2.2 The Measure of Vitalitymeasure of vitality

Pollock’s narrow definition of what is a measure of the vitality of a language - viz. kāvya-s of a certain calibre and type - excludes a lot of different types of literature (stotra literature,stotra literature for example) which together contribute to making a literary culture vibrant. He also gauges the ‘death’ or ‘enfeebled’ nature of the Sanskritic culture, by the non-production of any new theories in literary criticism (noted above in 1.1.1).

In such a framework of the four-fold values of life, as defined above, there is no work ‘for its own sake’ or ‘for the sake of mere pleasure’. Even pleasure can be of the right sort or the wrong sort (as kāmakāma finds its place in both the four puruṣārthapuruṣārtha-s and the ari-ṣaḍ-vargaari-ṣaḍ-varga, the set of six [internal] foes) and this imposes a certain criterion for it to be a valid goal. Hence ‘ars gratia artis’ (‘Art for art’s sake’)‘ars gratia artis’ (‘Art for art’s sake’) has never really found currency in the traditional Indian scenario (Coomaraswamy 2011:40).

When Pollock criticizes the lack of any theory of literary criticism (see 1.1.1 above) designed to oppose or replace the one which was presented before the 12th century CE, we need to examine if there indeed was any need for such an upheaval. When the Rasa Theory and the Dhvani Theory came to be presented in fairly refined forms, the scholars could only debate on certain details of the theory, they must have felt no need to come up with something completely new and revolutionary simply to displace the established ones. Where a necessity was felt through experimentation and experience to debate the veracity of a point (as in philosophy), there has been no undue reverence shown simply because it is a long-established idea of a respected saint or scholar[3]

The point to be understood here is that the tradition has always respected scholars for their ideas; however, when some lack is felt i.e., where theory fails to explain the experience, the debates have gone on relentlessly forward[4]. Of course, the human element of some personal rivalries and prejudices do reveal themselves, but the primary concern has been being more dispassionate than anything else[5]. By taking but one narrow section of the knowledge spectrum, only erroneous conclusions can be reached.

When Pollock talks of the paradoxes he sees in the Sanskrit literature produced during the Vijayanagara period, or laments the lack of literature in the pre-colonial Bengal (see 1.2.3, 1.4.2 above), he has again put on the lens of what according to him constitutes a thriving literary culture. Ignoring significant portions of literature such as the detailed bhāṣyabhāṣya that SāyaṇaSāyaṇa produced on all the four Veda-s;Veda dismissing the same as mere scholarship of the reproductive type without any originality[6]; mentioning the exciting works happening in NyāyaNyāya while saying in the same breath that Sanskrit culture was dead – this indeed is the real paradox.

The point Pollock makes, stated in (1.1.2) above, suffers again from focussing on a narrow range (viz. kāvya) of a very vast spectrum of literature, of which kāvya forms a small part after all as against the total intellectual output. Pollock has conveniently defined the parameters at the very outset to suit his own projections. HannederHanneder (2002: 302-303) shows how this argument does not hold water since there are evidences of works which are superficially stuti-s (and hence disqualified as per Pollock’s criteria), but also express the religious developments in the Kashmir valley.

The significance of the works in Sanskrit produced during the Vijayanagara period (see 1.2.4 supra) is measured (Pollock 2001:401) on the basis of whether they drew the attention of any commentator (curiously, and strangely, he does not consider production of a commentary to be a ‘valid’ measure of the vitality of a linguistic culture; for, had it been so, he could hardly have glossed over Sāyaṇa’sSāyaṇa massive commentarial workcommentarial work).

2.3 Statistical inexactitudes

While Pollock emphasizes the good effect of the rule of the Sultan Zain-ul-'abidin (see 1.1.2 supra) in that he promoted Sanskrit literature production, and also emphasizes how the bad Hindu kings before that were the epitomes of degeneracy,degeneracy he fails to mention the other side of the picture – viz. the maladministrationmaladministration of Muslim rulersMuslim!rulers in general, as too the good patronagepatronage given by most Hindu rulers. In fact, this is one of the ruling features we see in his writings - where one witnesses a systematic underplay of the negative effects of Islamic ruleIslamic rule coupled with an over-emphasis of the little good done by them, while at the same time doing the exact opposite in respect of Hindu rulers. This is elaborated upon in the next sub-section.

And as HannederHanneder points out (2002:308), terming Jagannātha as “the last Sanskrit poet” is not warranted as there are works such as those of the acclaimed Ambikādatta Vyāsa,Vyāsa, Ambikādatta the mahākāvya of the Nepali scholar Sukṛtidatta Panta,Panta, Sukṛtidatta and the writings of Kṣamā Rao,Rao, Kṣamā amongst a host of others (for more details, see Hanneder 2002:309).

2.4 List-and-dismiss

Even great jeopardies – such as the loss of valuable textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) - by fires that destroyed libraries in Kashmir (1.1.3 above) find but a very casual mention in his writings, as evidenced in the following sentence:

“important creative textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) may have disappeared, perhaps in one of the fires that periodically engulfed the capital of Kashmir, or in the Mongol invasion of 1320, which, according to a sixteenth-century Persian chronicle, left the country in ruins. Textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) may simply have eluded the notice of modern editors however carefully they may have combed the manuscript collections of Kashmir. But none of these possibilities seems very likely.” Pollock (2001:398)

After listing out the possibilities of the existential threatsexistential threats that had faced the Kashmiris, it is all dismissed with the last sentence, without giving any sensible reason. The one ‘reason’ given is that important Sanskrit literature, particularly literary theory, used to disseminate out of Kashmir, and nothing of the sort has happened during the period.

If we consider in general the destruction caused by Islamic invasionIslamic invasion from the perspective of the literary activities of any period, the greatest would be the destruction of librarieslibraries, destruction of even though the loss of the life of the scholars is no less tragic. The former, however, would mean the loss of generations of cumulative learning and creation.

Just taking one instance in the same Rājataraṅgiṇī of ŚrīvaraRājataraṅgiṇī!(Śrīvara), we come across the following verse (1.5.75):

sekandhara-dharānātho yavanaiḥ preritaḥ purā |
pustakāni ca sarvāṇi tṛṇāny agir ivādahat ||

[Translation (our own): Instigated earlier by yavana-s (Muslims), Sikandar,Sikandar Shāh Mīr (“Butshikhan”) the sultan, burnt down all the books - just as fire would burn down grass.]

The period being talked about is that of Sikandar But-shikhanSikandar Shāh Mīr (“Butshikhan”) (which means ‘Sikandar the Destroyer of Idols’Destroyer of Idols see Sikandar Shah Mir (“Butshikhan”)) (1389-1413 CE), regarding whom Śrīvara wrote (ref. Syed et al. 2011:282).

However, each of the ‘not-very-likely’ reasons that he has listed must have caused a great deal of instability in the normal life, which would undoubtedly affect any scholarly output that might have been possible at the time. Also, of the fires “that engulfed the capital” of Kashmir, one must of necessity ask - what was their cause? That was the period of the beginning of Islamic occupation - isn’t it then a part of the conflict and invasion? Śrīvara himself talks of the literature in deśa-bhāṣā which is Persian rather than Kashmiri; doesn’t this point to a large-scale conversion?conversions These are some of the questions that arise in the light of the claims made by Pollock. More work would be required if we are to find further/clearer answers.

In the case of Vijayanagara (1.2.4 above) too, the result of an Islamic invasionIslamic invasion is downplayed considerably as in the case of Kashmir (1.1.3 above). The destruction that Vijayanagara saw after the battle of TalikotaTalikota, battle of in 1565 marks a civilizational break (ref. EatonEaton, Richard M 2005:100). SewellSewell, Robert writes that the fallen capital was ruthlessly pillaged and destroyed for five months (Sewell 1962:200).

2.5 Parsimony in applying Ockham’s Razor!

While Pollock sees nothing new in content in either RasagaṅgādharaRasagaṅgādhara or the vilāsa-s of Jagannātha (1.3.2 above), he submits that there is still something novel akin to the ‘modern subjectivity’ (Pollock 2001:405). He asserts (1.3.3 above) that it is Jagannātha’s personal story of love and the loss of the beloved etc., which have been voiced in Bhāminīvilāsa,Bhāminīvilāsa while most other scholars do not even raise this question of whether there is something personal about this at all. It is just considered to be a work which is nothing but a collection of independent verses - by no means unusual in Sanskrit literature.

The four sections of Bhāminīvilāsa – Anyokti-vilāsa, Śṛṅgāra-vilāsa, Karuṇā-vilāsa, Śānta-vilāsa – have various poems arranged in the typical muktakamuktaka style (ref. LienhardLienhard, Siegfried 1984:103). While Pollock talks of Karuṇā-vilāsa as being reflective of Jagannātha’s personal bereavement, and tries hard to explain away the discrepancy between the emotionality of Jagannātha the poet and the detachment of Jagannātha the critic, one finds it easier to take the poem as just that – a poem which has come from the imagination of a great poet, rather than any portrayal of personal tragedies.

Is it not the first quality of a great poet to be able to portray his (imaginary) characters show emotions that are realistic? Does it not issue from the pratibhāpratibhā (genius) of the poet? When we come across Kālidāsa’sKālidāsa Aja bemoaning in First Person the death of his beloved wife (ref. RaghuvaṁśaRaghuvaṁśa Canto 8), are we to construe it as Kālidāsa’s personal grief coming through? The hair-splitting analysis made in order to explain away these superimposed discontinuities in Jagannātha’s theory and practice seems at best to be an exercise in futility.

2.6 Perhaps...probably...and therefore

Jagannātha’s link with a Muslim womanMuslim!woman seems for Pollock, to be the sole qualifying factor for the “something new” in his poetry (1.3.9 above)! While no one disputes the existence of poetry in Persian regarding the unattainable love (though Pollock emphasizes, that it is so on counts of ethnic difference), through ages we find in our own literature here, verses dwelling on this theme. Famous in the category is Caura-pañcāśikāCaura-pañcāśikā of BilhaṇaBilhaṇa (circa 11th c.CE), where BilhaṇaBilhaṇa, a commoner, falls in love with the princess. As for the personal tone, many works post-12th century (or even prior ones, though it is difficult to demarcate the transition) talk of their creator’s prowess, bring the personal element to ‘crush’ the opponent etc (e.g. Madhva-tantra-mukha-mardanamMadhva-tantra-mukha-mardanam of Appayya DīkṣitaAppayya Dīkṣita (16th c.CE)). This ‘cosmopolitan’ change in Jagannātha - that he broke the conventions, unlike Siddhicandra who remained celibate - again seems to be the driving point of seeing something new in his work. Can’t it suffice that Jagannātha was a truly brilliant poet (while Siddhicandra might not have been) and should it take a breaking of taboobreaking of taboo to make his brilliant poetry brilliant? Praising a truly great scholar for the wrong reasons is worse than “damnation by faint praise”misinterpretation,!techniques of,!damnation by faint praise. It would be akin to saying MahābhārataMahābhārata is truly great because it was written by the son of a fisherwoman.

In sum, by making an assumption that a disputed conjecture is indeed a fact i.e. that Bhāminīvilāsa is but a personal narrative and that it is about his beloved who was a Muslim, and trying to explain the inconsistencies in the points of view of Jagannātha in his poetic and scholarly works, Pollock is discarding simple and plausible explanations, in favour of complicated and highly unlikely speculations.

2.7 Selection of data

After considering specific kingdoms (viz. Kashmir and Vijayanagara) in the earlier two anecdotal samples, that he has chosen to consider now an individual (viz. Jagannātha) for analysis as the third (1.3.1 above) is rather telling. Taking specific geographic locations in Bhārata in order to arrive at the life (or death) of a pan-Bhārata language is not logically sound, unless it is established a priori that the sample he is considering is truly representative of the whole (via sthālī-pulāka-nyāya).sthālī-pulāka-nyāyanyāya-s!sthālī-pulāka

2.7.1 Spatial dimension of the problem:

One basic problem that we see in the anecdotal samples that are analysed to arrive at the conclusions in the paper, is the inherent contradiction between - (i) considering Sanskrit on the one hand as having pan-Indianpan-Indian (or pan-South Asian) reach and (ii) not considering the entire area of Greater IndiaGreater India or rather Bhāratavarṣa,Bhāratavarṣa at the four specific time periods that are being considered[7]. If one focuses on a particular geographic area where conditions may or may not be conducive for cultural life to thrive (as in the case of KashmirKashmir during the invasion of Islamic forces, or the case of Vijayanagara after the Battle of TalikotaTalikota, battle of in 1565), one is bound to see such ‘deaths’. On the contrary, if one looks at the entire Bhāratavarṣa as the locus of literary activity, we can see how Sanskrit is alive rather than being ‘dead’.

After all, it was a common practice for scholars to move from kingdom to kingdom. (svadeśe pūjyate rājā; vidvān sarvatra pūjyate, as the adage goes). Pollock himself mentions the ease with which Jagannātha moved from court to court, “from Andhra to Jaipur to Delhi and from Udaipur to Assam in a kind of vast “circumambulation of the quarters”” (Pollock 2001:404). To see Bhāratavarṣa as merely a collection of pieces of land that were kingdoms or janapada-s, and nothing more, would be a grave injustice to the land which is truly the cradle of an ancient and steady civilization.

2.7.2 Temporal dimension of the problem:

There are problems in choosing and considering specific slivers of time, in the long history of a language to gauge such a thing as its vitality. Such a situation obtains especially against a “problem” which is rather exclusive to the Indian civilization viz. one of the tendency for self-effacementself-effacement. As CoomaraswamyCoomaraswamy, A K (2004:175) points out, the artist is usually anonymous and it is always what is said, and not who said it, that mattered.

While this is an excellent philosophy, it does make things extremely difficult in a scenario such as we face in the present age, where historicity of all aspects of literature matters, what with the history-centricityhistory-centric that is being thrust on us. (The reason for the emphasis is not hard to fathom – since the secularism which finds wide currency in today’s scholarship has its roots in the Abrahamic traditionAbrahamic tradition, history-centric which is deeply or rather essentially history-centrichistory-centric) (ref. MalhotraMalhotra, Rajiv 2011, Ch.2) . In our eventful several millennia of history, forget the absolute dating of a poet/philosopher (to locate him/her, to wit, in the grid of a linear timeline) and locating him/her in a probable geography - even relatively placing them sees too many difficulties more often than not. Commonly, it is the mention of the reigning king that helps in placing the scholar on the time line (though even that is fraught with difficulties since there can be disputes in dating the king himself, as there can be several namesakes of a king in different periods/ages). A lot of different kinds of internal evidences will have to be consulted in the absence of external evidences, in order to deduce a possible time range. For instance, in the case of Kālidāsa,Kālidāsa assignments of date ranges from 1 century BCE to 8th century CE, and with no definite idea about his place. What is worse, confusion gets confounded with multiple scholars or poets bearing the same name.

2.7.3 Numerical dimension of the problem

kati kavayaḥ, kati kṛtayaḥ, kati luptāḥ, kati caranti, kati śithilāḥ |
tad api pravartayati māṁ nigamoktākhyāna-saṁvidhāne hā ||

If we consider the number of works produced (encompassing all genres of writing from kāvya to bhāṣya to independent works on the various sciences) , only a fraction probably were reproduced in the manuscriptmanuscript form – due to various reasons such as lessening interest in the subject, natural calamities, invasions, economic conditions etc. The major reason for the losses of the ones actually created is actually destruction of libraries.libraries, destruction of Of even that fraction, it is only a further fraction that survives till date – thanks to the tropical weather,tropical weather, effect on manuscripts ignorance in the families where they are preserved etc. Hundreds of Sanskrit textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) are available only in Tibetan translation.Tibetan translation Of the surviving ones, even if we have some information of more than half of them, there are according to the census, over 30 million manuscripts.manuscript

Sanskrit is the primary culture-bearing languageculture-bearing language of India, with a continuous production of literature in all fields of human endeavor over the course of four millennia. Preceded by a strong oral traditionoral tradition of knowledge transmission, records of written Sanskrit remain in the form of inscriptions dating back to the first century B.C.E. Extant manuscriptsextant manuscripts in Sanskrit number over 30 million - one hundred times those in Greek and LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) combined - constituting the largest cultural heritagecultural!heritage that any civilization has produced prior to the invention of the printing press. Sanskrit works include extensive epics, subtle and intricate philosophical, mathematical, and scientific treatises, and imaginative and rich literary, poetic, and dramatic texts.texts (Sanskrit/Indic) (Goyal et al 2012:1012)

The number of surviving manuscripts being that large, it is difficult to imagine the size of the corpus had all the works survived.

When we look at only one particular genre such as kāvya[8], if the numbers we are considering are even a third, hypothetically, of the total corpus available now considering the profusion of kāvya literature that has been produced, there are still so many in that number which haven’t even seen the light of the day[9]. There would then be 10 million of the kāvya manuscripts.kāvya manuscripts If even a fourth of all the manuscripts ever produced have survived till date, the total number of manuscripts originally produced would be 4 times 30million, i.e. 120 million (another hypothetical number). Even if one factors in the repetitions (50 mss for each kāvya), it would come to 5 lakh kāvya-s. If this number is to be representative of the corpus that was originally produced, one sees the difficulty of extending a deduction or a conclusion from this fraction to the original whole.

We are also aware, to but a very small extent, of the losses. Many anthologies have eulogising verses that mention poets by name. In a play of KālidāsaKālidāsa we find the mention of Bhāsa,Bhāsa (dramatist) SaumillaSaumilla (poet) and KaviputraKaviputra (poet)[10]. For centuries together, scholars had merely heard of BhāsaBhāsa (dramatist), with none of his works being available. It was only in the beginning of the 20th century that Bhāsa’s works were traced (see Sastri 1925). And we still do not have any inkling as to who SaumillaSaumilla (poet) was or what KaviputraKaviputra (poet) wrote. Likewise there are so many poetesses who are known only by the appearance of their muktaka-s in anthologies. Same is the case even of great writers in śāstra-s such as Bhaṭṭa TautaBhaṭṭa Tauta (the guru of Abhinavagupta,Abhinavagupta and the author of Kāvya-kautuka-vivaraṇaKāvya-kautuka-vivaraṇa which has not been traced) and KauṭalyaKauṭalya (a.k.a Cāṇakya,Cāṇakya the author of ArthaśāstraArthaśāstra, which was discovered only in the early 20th century).

It is often argued that if a work has not survived, it is because it did not have ideas that were worthy/capable of surviving. It is a very dangerous argument to make, for, this can be used as an explanation for any work disappearing from circulation, accidentally or deliberately, for various reasons[11] When one is trying to base one’s conclusions on mere negative evidencenegative evidence one must bear all these problems in mind[12] and recall the oft-quoted statement of wisdom, viz. “Absence of evidence is by no means an evidence of absence”. In the case at hand, simply because we haven’t found yet manuscripts of a specific genre and/or from a specific period, we are by no means entitled to conclude that there weren’t any books written – particularly in a civilization such as ours which shows such remarkable continuity and redoubtable zeal in knowledge production. All that one may conclude is – “We do not have any data from this period to theorize”. On a lighter note, one remembers Sherlock HolmesHolmes, Sherlock saying to his trusted Watson “It is a capital mistake to theorize before you have data”. But unlike Holmes who cried out, “Data! Data! I cannot make bricks without clay!” – some scholars can apparently pull off this veritable magic!

3 Meta-analysis and pattern recognition

In this section we try to recognize certain patterns of reasoning that emerge from reading (between the lines as well) the article of Pollock.

(a)
Choosing a narrow definitionmisinterpretation,!techniques of,!narrow definitionnarrow definition to determine the vitality of a tradition/language: Choosing only that kāvya-genre which according to Pollock is representative of ‘creative vitality’, he completely neglects the other genres of literature produced, including (a) the very substantial glosses by giants of scholars like Sāyaṇa, (b) stotra literaturestotra literature, and (c) scientific literatureSanskrit!scientific literature (ref. Hanneder 2002:298-99), to list but three.
(b)
Selecting data to fit a theory: He cites Jonarāja’s listing of no poets, no good works in the period of 140 years. He mentions that the presence of Turks as insignificant. However, he fails to mention the havoc wreaked by Sikandar ButshikhanSikandar Shāh Mīr (“Butshikhan”) who is mentioned by ŚrīvaraŚrīvara (see Kaul 2001:231,233 and HaigHaig, T W 1918:454,455). Such cherry-picking of factsmisinterpretation,!techniques of,!cherry-picking facts can only lead to a distorted picture.
(c)
Selective playing-up and playing-down:misinterpretation,!techniques of,!selective playing-up & playing-down We find instances of his playing down the great genocides,genocide invasions etc that happened with the coming of the Muslim invadersinvaders (see 1.1.3, 1.2.4 above). He plays up the rare good things e.g. the donation that was given by a Muslim to a temple here, a scholar supported there, and a good Sultan somewhere else – in order to project a picture of a very benevolent rule (e.g. the rule of Zain-ul-'abidinZain-ul-"'abidin) while not citing the enormous destruction caused (e.g. librarieslibraries, destruction of burnt by Sikandar). His general claim is that Muslim rulersMuslim!rulers tried to save the language and were benevolent (Pollock 2001:416) which is contradicted by other records (ref. BostomBostom, Andrew G 2008:458-460). On the contrary, every case of a ‘bad’ Hindu ruler is projected as though it is a representative sample of ‘bad’ Hindu rule, while not choosing to look at the benevolent Hindu rulers and their contributions. This can be summed up with a new rule – meyādhīnā mānasiddhiḥ“meyādhīnā mānasiddhiḥ” (Let us choose such tools and measures as suit the conclusions we want to portray!)
(d)
Using various terms/frameworks of social science, modern psychology, anthropology, Biblical studiesBiblical studies etc to superimpose on traditional Indian thought. The traditional scholars who are ignorant of other modern fields and the various theories therein are completely confounded and awed into submission to Pollock's methodology. There are inherent problems of using vocabulary and frameworks of fields of study completely alien to Sanskrit studies. (For instance, WirkungsgeschichteWirkungsgeschichte (See PollockPollock!methods 2001:393) is a term in Biblical studiesBiblical studies coined by GadamerGadamer for the hermeneutic principle of “history of effects”.history of effects see Gadamer It means that a text is understood by taking account the effects it has produced in history, by inserting oneself in this history and dialoguing with it. See EberhardEberhard, Philippe 2004:90)
(e)
List and dismiss:List and dismissmisinterpretation,!techniques of,!list and dismiss Enumerating the possible causes for a particular event (lest an opponent point out that all causes were not considered) but dismissing them without really giving even as much as substantial reason, saying no more than that they are ‘not very likely’. We see this in 1.1.3 and 1.2.4, to give but two examples.
(f)
Divida et impera:misinterpretation,!techniques of,!divida et impera Though trying to deduce the fate of a pan-Bhārata language, his focus is on specific kingdoms and janapada-s and not Bhāratavarṣa, in order to declare its death in each case. To show an apparent conflict between Sanskrit and vernaculars, he pits the production and popularity of vernacular literature against that of Sanskrit literature, drawing conclusions, and colouring them with politics.

4 Conclusion

The work under scrutiny opens our eyes to the effort that has gone into a study of our literature and culture, the intentions notwithstanding. For a true debate to even begin, there needs to be an earnest effort from the insiders of this culture under scrutiny to come up with a faithful pūrva-pakṣapūrva-pakṣa so that further efforts can be directed at coming up with a competent uttarapakṣauttara-pakṣa. There are several areas which require work in order to do the latter. We indicate a few here:

(a)
There are inherent contradictions across Pollock'sPollock!methods writings which need to be investigated and critiqued. For instance, Hanneder (2002:302) points to the contention that Śrīvara’s work is almost “clerical” (1.1.2). He underlines the conflicting opinion of Pollock himself about Śrīvara who is “the most interesting intellectual at the court of Zain-ul-'abidin” and yet “unable to create serious original work himself”. Also, his stand about the influence of Islamic forces as pointed out by Rajiv Malhotra (2016:285-286)
(b)
That very little promotion was done by King Kṛṣṇadevarāya for KannadaKannada literature production (which thrived outside) and that Sanskrit, Telugu and Tamil received courtly patronagepatronage (even though the Sanskrit literature of the day failed to make impact) – is a deduction which can and ought to be questioned though only after being armed with apt and sufficient data. It is only after a very thorough collection of information regarding the literature of the time (without making selection of any specific genre at the collection stage itself) can one even begin to challenge the conclusion.
(c)
In general, the question of how much literature (of all genres including scientific) was produced in any given period is something that cannot be easily answered given the complexity of circumstances. However, delving deep into the material that is actually available will itself probably lead to some concrete conclusions which are not arising out of emotion but are based on facts, against the questions raised in sections 1.1.2, 1.2.1, 1.2.2, 1.2.5, 1.4.1.

Working along the lines suggested above, we should, hopefully, be in a position at some future date to reply to the issues raised. While it is necessary to attack the logic of Pollock’s arguments, one needs to essentially abstain from resorting to polemicspolemics (even though that stand might not be reciprocated).

For a language which has supposedly ‘died’ so many times, Sanskrit definitely has a way of returning to life – a veritable phoenix that it is! However, rather than qualifying the low points in its history as ‘death’death, one can term it renewal or reconfiguration. This is because, unlike the other ‘dead’ languages, Sanskrit has a very dynamic and close relationship with the vernaculars which are in currency.

Hanneder (2002:309) rightly points to the essential cultural misunderstanding that Pollock displays when he repeatedly points to the ‘death’death of Sanskrit (whatever may be his measures). It is that here time is essentially cyclic and what was once an old style, renews itself and becomes current, whereas the Western mind essentially sees linear timelinear time - where the arrow moves in but a single direction, and ‘culminating’ in the present achievements. The Indian mind does more easily handle the idea of renewal than does a Western mind.

While we have only raised pertinent questions in this paper, we intend to produce sounder arguments against Pollock in a future context.

Bibliography

Bhagavadgītā (=Ch.6.25 to 6.42 of Mahābhārata).See Belvalkar.
Bhāgavata. See Tapasyananda.
Belvalkar, S. K. (1945) Ed. Bhagavadgītā. Bombay: Editor.
Bostom, Andrew G. (2005) The Legacy of Jihad: Islamic Holy War and the Fate of Non-Muslims.. New York: Prometheus Books.
Caurapañcāśikā. See Tadpatrikar.
Coomaraswamy, Ananda Kentish. (2004) The Essential Ananda K Coomaraswamy. Edited by Rama P. Coomaraswamy. Bloomington: World Wisdom.
Coomaraswamy, Ananda Kentish. (2011) The Wisdom of Ananda Coomaraswamy: Reflections on Indian Art, Life, and Religion. Edited by S. Durai Raja Singam and Joseph A. Fitzgeral. Bloomington: World Wisdom.
Eaton, Richard M. (2005) The New Cambridge History of India I.8. Cambridge University Press.
Eberhard, Philippe. (2004) The Middle Voice in Gadamer’s Hermeneutics: A Basic Interpretation with some Theological Implications. Tubingen: Mohr Siebeck.
Goyal, Pawan., Gérard Huet, Amba Kulkarni, Peter Scharf, and Ralph Bunker. (2012) “A Distributed Platform for Sanskrit Processing,” Proceedings of COLING 2012: Technical Papers, COLING 2012 (2012): 1011–1028.
Haig, T. W. (1918) “The Chronology and Geneology of the Muhammadan Kings of Kashmir”. The Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society of Great Britain and Ireland (Jul.1918), 451–468.
Hanneder, J. (2002) “On “The Death of Sanskrit””. Indo-Iranian Journal 45(2002): 293–310.
Joglekar, K. M. (Ed.) (1916) Raghuvaṁśa of Kālidāsa. Bombay: Nirnaya Sagar Press.
Kaul, Arun. (2000) “Kesar : The cultural geography of Kashmir”. India International Centre Quarterly Vol 27/28 (Winter 2000/Spring 2001), 226–234.
Kaul, Srikanth (Ed.) (1966) Rājataraṅgiṇī of Śrīvara and Śuka. Hoshiarpur: Vishveshvaranand Institute.
Kielhorn, Franz (Ed.) (1880-1884) The Vyakarana-Mahabhashya of Patañjali (3Vol.s). Bombay: Government Central Book Depot.
Krishnamachariar, M. (1989) History of Classical Sanskrit Literature. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass.
Kulczycki, Stefan.Kulczycki, Stefan (1956) Non-Euclidean Geometry. (Translated from Polish by Stanislaw Knapowski). New York: Dover Publications Inc.
Lienhard, Siegfried. (1984) The History of Classical Poetry: Sanskrit, Pali, Prakrit. Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz.
Mahābhāṣya of Patañjali (on Aṣṭādhyāyī of Pāṇini) See Keilhorn.
Mālavikāgnimitra. See Parab.
Malhotra, Rajiv. (2011) Being Different. Noida, India: HarperCollins Publishers.
Malhotra, Rajiv. (2016) The Battle for Sanskrit. Noida, India: HarperCollins Publishers.
Manusmṛti. See Shastri.
Parab, K P, (Ed.) (1924) Mālavikāgnimitram of Kālidāsa. Bombay: Nirnaya Sagar Press.
Pingree, David. (1970 et seq) Census of the Exact Sciences in Sanskrit (5 Volumes). Philadelphia: American Philosphical Society.
Pollock, Sheldon. (2001) “The Death of Sanskrit.” Society for Comparative Study of Society and History. pp.392–426.
Pollock, Sheldon. (1995) “The Sanskrit Cosmopolis”, Ideology and Status of Sanskrit. Contributions to the History of the Sanskrit Language. (Ed.) by Jan E.M. Houben, Leiden: E.J. Brill. pp.197–247
Raghuvaṁśa. See Joglekar.
Rājataraṅgiṇī. See Kaul.
Sarma, N. N. (1994) Jagannātha The Renowned Sanskrit Poet of Medieval India. New Delhi: Mittal Publication.
Sastri, T Ganapati and Bhasa. (1925) “The Works of Bhasa”. Bulletin of the School of Oriental Studies University of London Vol.3 No.4. pp.627–637.
Sewell, Robert and Fernando Nunes. (1900) A Forgotten Empire: Vijayanagar, a Contribution to the History of India. London: S. Sonnenschein & Co. Ltd.
Shastri, J. L. (Ed.) (1983) Manusmṛti of Manu. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass.
Syed, Muzaffar Husain (Ed.) (2011) A Concise History of Islam. New Delhi: Vij Books India.
Tadpatrikar, S. N. (Ed.) (1946) Caura-pañcāśikā, an Indian Love Lament of Bilhana Kavi. Poona: Poona Oriental Series No.86.
Tapasyananda, Swami (Ed.) (2003) Bhāgavatapurāṇa. Chennai: Ramakrishna Ashram.

Pollock is very critical of citrakāvyacitrakāvya genre but it takes undoubted authority on language to be able to write one. Hanneder (2002:300) comments on this (however, we cannot agree with his full substantiation) and points out that judging the literature over a very long period of time (like making a sweeping statement that after 1200s the literature is all of lesser quality) is problematic since other scholars can hold different opinions.

The latter point presented rather dramatically as “the latter lay unread and unrecopied in the palace library from the moment the ink on the palm leaves was dry.” (Pollock 2001:401).

A parallel case in point would be the acceptance of Euclidean geometryEuclidean geometry for near two millennia (from 300BCE to around 19th century CE) until non-Euclidean geometrynon-Euclidean geometry was discovered. (Kulczycki1956:53).

The cropping up of the Advaita-Viśiṣṭādvaita-Dvaita traditions and further subdivisions thereof are cases in point.

Famous is the Śaṅkara-Maṇḍanamiśra debate.

For more details on the Sanskrit works produced in the Vijayanagara empire, see Krishnamachariar (1989)

There is also the inconsistency pointed out by Hanneder (2002:295): While Pollock argues for the political function of Sanskrit, the area across which that was spread extended from present-day Afghanistan to present-day Indonesia (roughly 84 lakh sqkms), without a military conquest but through intellectuals and religious persons. Pollock (1995:231) also argues that Sanskrit was never a commoner’s language. There is ample evidence to prove the contrary which shall be taken up in a later paper.

The arbitrary choice of genres to determine if Sanskrit is alive or dead done where stotrastotra is not considered a valid genre – this, according to Hanneder (2002:301), is only in line with the comparison with LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) literature.

One has only to look at Pingree’s Census of the Exact Sciences in SanskritPingreeCensus of the Exact Sciences in Sanskrit to get an idea of how many scientific manuscripts have not been published yet.

prathita-yaśasāṁ Bhāsa-Saumilla-Kaviputrādīnāṁ prabandhān atikramya vartamāna-kaveḥ KālidāsasyaKālidāsa kṛtau kathaṁ pariṣado bahumānaḥ (MālavikāgnimitramMālavikāgnimitram 1.1+)

For instance, manuscripts could have been lost/stayed unpublished for any of the following reasons:

(a)
Preferring only to study past masters rather than also encourage/preserve newer works.
(b)
Possible repositories such as the university librarieslibraries, destruction of getting destroyed in invasions/attacks
(c)
Newer works not following the pattern of what is trending. But when a century or two later people somehow hear about it and are interested, no copies to be found.
(d)
Manuscripts not surviving in the humid and hot tropical weathertropical weather, effect on manuscripts - what is the typical life expectancy of a manuscriptmanuscript!life expectancy of in such climates? - if it is not copied and preserved, it is gone for ever
(e)
Subsequent generations having lost the cultural connect with the manuscripts - dumping them in rivers or in the fire rather than allowing unregarding collectors to take it.

The basic thesis of Pollock (1995) in his work “the Sanskrit Cosmopolis” is to portray Sanskrit as a tool for wielding political powerpower!political through what he terms as ‘aestheticization of power’aestheticization of power. Hanneder (2002:297) points to the refutation that has already been written by Buhler on the matter (f14). In this thesis Pollock claims that Sanskrit lost its “political” function whereas in “the Death of Sanskrit” essay, he claims that Sanskrit lost its true life. The manuscripts available are from a period after Sanskrit has supposedly died. If one argues that those available are the elementary works and not the top-notch productions, the opponent can easily argue that you’ll need the elementary works copied at a larger scale to be used for education across the nation, and cannot definitely be held up as “negative evidence” for lack of advanced works.

Chapter 8 On “Death of Sanskrit”

Manogna Sastry

Introduction

‘The Death of Sanskrit’ – the essay published under this rather astonishing title by the Indologist Sheldon Pollock (Pollock 2001) bids us to a dynamic re-examination and a defense of our invaluable literary instrument. The most august, venerable and determinative creations of the Indian race have been written in Sanskrit, and pronouncing death upon the language is tantamount to an inability in understanding the true role of this divine tongue. Pollock’s essay merits a clear understanding of the burden of his song. The motives for the author’s position and the method of his reasoning are studied here in order to understand why he would see efforts to promote the language as a politically biased “exercise in nostalgia”. The distinction the author makes between living and dead languages and his attempts at placing Sanskrit in the latter category are closely examined. The four major questions the author considers as a part of his analysis in proclaiming death upon the language consist of the impact of the vernaculars upon Sanskrit, the political, social and spiritual components that played a role in the decline of the language and the factors he considers necessary for consolidating the language in today’s times. Pollock cites four specific historical instances that apparently illustrate his stance and these are critically examined.

India of the ages is not dead nor has she spoken her last creative word; she lives and has still something to do for herself and the human peoples. And that which must seek now to awake is not an anglicised Oriental people, docile pupil of the West and doomed to repeat the cycle of the Occident's success and failure, but still the ancient immemorable Shakti recovering her deepest self, lifting her head higher towards the supreme source of light and strength and turning to discover the complete meaning and a vaster form of her Dharma.dharma –Sri AurobindoAurobindo

Whenever one endeavours to comprehend the value of a culture and appreciate, especially a culture into which he is born and forms the source of one’s highest standards, he tends to gloss over the shortcomings and defects of his own heritage. At this juncture, it may prove helpful to have insights from an outsider to better one’s reflection. For the outsider too, there are ways of perceiving an alien culture. There is, firstly, the sympathetic viewer and there are several foreigners who have embraced Indian culture and contributed enormously to its value, from Sister NiveditaNivedita, Sister to Romain RollandRolland, Romain. Then, there is the impartial and objective critic, who, without any prejudice in objective, balances the worth against the weakness and whose objective criticismcriticism must be welcomed to balance one’s own study. The third is the belligerent critic, whose motives need to be carefully studied as well as his methods. And Sheldon Pollock lends himself to this third type. His overcharging declaration of the ‘death’ of SanskritSanskrit!revival of summons a vigorous analysis and re-statement of the role of the language in present day India.

While Pollock’s methodsPollock!methods of analysis and recognition of the function of SanskritSanskrit!revival of as the literary instrumentliterary!instrument of India reveals a conflict between Western and Asian approaches to understanding Oriental culture, his motives are revealed in the very first part of the essay. Pollock’s biasbias against the recent attempts at revitalising SanskritSanskrit!revival of is revealed through his disdain for efforts by the Indian government as well as private organizations here for promoting the language. He holds the rise of HindutvaHindutva and the election of the Bharatiya Janata Party to powerpower!political at the central levels of government responsible for reviving a nationalistic culture. Efforts to promote the language independent of the Hindutva association that have been carried out in post independent India by several individuals and organizations are not given any credit. Pollock believes that this revival is driven by political motivations, and in the process, “distorted images of India’s past” are being created including the viewpoint that Sanskrit is native to India and that it existed during the Indus Valley CivilizationIndus Valley Civilization. He sets aside prevailing debates about the origin and geographical indigenousnessgeographical!indigenousness of the language as well as discussions of the forms of Sanskrit during the latter part of the HarappanHarappan civilsation. Pollock further betrays his lack of recognition of the true role of Sanskrit in defining the identity of the Indian soul when he scorns any championing of the language by nationalistic elements, calling them “farcical repetition of Romantic myths of primevality”.

Indeed, it is vitally important for a nation to be cautious in ensuring that exaggerated claims about its past are not made a part of its national narrative. Yet, the process of rediscovery and reinterpretation of the Indian identity that is currently taking place, in the context of globalised and liberalised policies at all levels of the State, finds the Indian of today looking back at his history without the coloured glassescoloured glasses of subjection that his colonial oppressor forced him to wear. It is very important for one to consider the state of the language and the field, leaving apart from the fringe elements who are occupying a small place. The number of people for whom Sanskrit is associated with the very template of the cultural fabriccultural!fabric of India is far too big; and to dismiss this section by labeling and associating the campaign with only ultra-nationalistic elements amounts to closing the debate for the majority of the section. And Pollock assails this process of reinterpretation and growth, which is marked by a feature of self-assertive powerpower!political, by calling it ‘the State’s anxiety’ and condemns any effort that has gone into the preservation and propagation of the language as a part of a ‘melancholic history.’ Had this condemnation arisen from a lesser mind, it would have been forgivable. For a critic of Pollock’s caliber, then, to question efforts in post independent India for the preservation and sharpening of the instrument in which the greatest canons of the land have been written, is but a pointer to the dubious and hostile motives of the man.

Pollock goes on to enlist the efforts that have gone into popularising Sanskrit since independence, and states that there have been hardly any results for all the funds and resources that have been allocated for the development of the language. While Pollock speaks about the political checks that he sees as being placed in this ‘revisionism’, he seems to be speaking of only one face of it. He makes no mention at all of how during the decades before the rise of the ‘Hindutva’Hindutva, Sanskrit had to contend with the active State and governmental neglect. In 1994, attempts were made under the P V Narasimha RaoRao, P V Narasimha government to remove Sanskrit from the CBSE syllabusCBSE syllabus. It was the intervention of the Supreme Court that ended the Government’s foolish move. The role played by these political and judicial checks in post independent India are not even discussed by Pollock while he maintains that any effort to revive the language is futile.

Having expressed his derision and disdain for the work done in promoting the language, especially as a spoken one, Pollock finally states the crux of his essay – “Government feeding tubesGovernment feeding tubes and oxygen tanks may try to preserve the language in a state of quasi-animation, but most observers would agree that, in some crucial way, Sanskrit is dead” (p. 393). When does one declare a language to be dead? In answering this question, Pollock does not establish any rigorous conditions but speaks of the distinction between written and natural languages. While admitting the influence of Sanskrit across Asia, he maintains that there have not been any theories on “whether and if so, when, Sanskrit culture ceased to make history”, and why the language could not remain creatively vital.

A further study of the paper reveals that Pollock’s definition of the ‘death’ of Sanskrit is primarily a reference to the dearth of production of creative works, especially in the domain of kāvya, over the last millennium. His method consists of singling out particular instances - over different periods of time spread over a thousand years and geographically scattered across the land - to support his thesis and overlooking those that invalidate it, pointing thus to a manner of biasedbias scholarship. His consideration, of phases when emphasis was laid on documentation and “reinscription and restatement” as periods of decline and decay of the language, is debatable; and while doing so, Pollock conveniently casts away vitally important canons from these periods which readily disprove his thesis. Thus, Pollock’s methodPollock!methods of arbitrary selectionarbitrary selection drives his thesis from two major angles – (a) his exclusive focus on the genre of kāvya (excluding even stotra-sstotra literature) as the only measure of the vitality of the language, and (b) his very small set of four instances spread over a millennium across the country during which the language declined.

In his study of the “history of Sanskrit knowledge systems,” Pollock (2001:393) remarks that “the two centuries before European colonialismcolonialism decisively established itself in the sub continent around 1750 constitute one of the most innovative epochs of Sanskrit systematic thought”. Sanskrit thrived in India until then, according to him, with massive creative output in every major genre of the language. He does not make any reference at all to the effects of the Islamic invasionIslamic invasion on the social and cultural fabric of the land and particularly on the linguistic scene. Yet, by 1800, the creative ability has disappeared from the land. Thus, according to Pollock, Sanskrit was alive enough to withstand all the shocks and turmoil the land had faced in the first half of the millennium to lead to the Navya movementNavya movement but was dead within the next fifty years, by 1800. Calling this a momentous rupture, he admits the analysis of this sudden change is complex but himself selects only the genre of kāvya to study the decline in the language, quoting the Gujarati poet Dalpatrām Dahyabhai’s work in 1857 as further evidence and highlights his case throughout the essay.

Without any analysis of the various roles Sanskrit has played in expressing the very psyche and mind of the Indian; without any recognition of the central role it has played in formulating some of the most profound spiritual, philosophical, intellectual and emotional conceptions of not just the Indian but of the human race; and by further not considering the various genres in which Sanskrit has continued to survive and thrive in India, Pollock’s proclaiming death on the language on account of its no longer being the first language of the majority population in the country is contrived and purposeful overcharging. His carefully chosen examples that purportedly demonstratepurportedly demonstrate the death of the language over the millennium consist of: (1) “The disappearance of Sanskrit literature in Kashmir,” (2) “its diminished powerpower!political in sixteenth century Vijayanagara,” (3) “its short-lived moment of modernity at the Mughal court,” and (4) “its ghostly existence in Bengal on the eve of colonialismcolonialism.” The four cases are duly considered in the following sections.

The four cases:

1 ‘The Lady Vanishes’

Pollock’s first case consists in analyzing the decline, or rather in his own words, “the complete disappearance”, of Sanskrit from Kashmir. Pollock begins his case by considering the scene in the valley during 1140, a time during which Kashmir served as a celebrated and revered seat for the learning of the language. AlaṅkāraAlaṅkāra (poet) holds a gathering in honour of his brother MaṅkhaMaṅkha, the author of the epic ŚrīkaṇṭhacaritaŚrīkaṇṭhacarita. The assembly hosts some of the greatest names in the field, from RuyyakaRuyyaka, Maṅkha’s mentor, to TrailokyaTrailokya (poet) and JindukaJinduka (poet). KalhaṇaKalhaṇa, whose work RājataraṅgiṇīRājataraṅgiṇī!(Kalhaṇa) is considered the most noteworthy historical poem of the language, is present in this august gathering as well. Every major branch of the language is represented through its best exponent in this exalted congregation, establishing the premier position held by Kashmir during the time. Not only is the assembly playing host to literary titans, but also to the leading names in the fields of physicians, philosophers and architects who were present at the gathering.

Pollock builds a strong case to highlight that, the period of 1140CE represented the zenith of the intellectual development attained by Kashmir. He is right in highlighting the remarkable lineage the place boasted of since the seventh century. KṣemendraKṣemendra, the polymath and author of Bhārata MañjarīBhārata Mañjarī and BṛhatkathāmañjarīBṛhatkathāmañjarī represented the best of the eleventh century. The twelfth century saw Maṅkha, along with his brothers, JayadrathaJayadratha (poet) and KavirājaKavirāja (poet), rise to literary acclaim with other creative titans.

Yet, within fifty years from 1140CE, the literary landscape has changed beyond recognition. Pollock highlights that production of new creations in all the major genres of the language has come to a standstill. From being a focal point of learning, Kashmir has become barren. Fifteenth century is the next age during which significant compositions emerge again. The royal patronagepatronage issued to SanskritSanskrit!revival of by the Sultan Zain-ul-'abidinZain-ul-"'abidin created the necessary conditions for the revival, says Pollock. Jonarāja was the chief scholar at the Sultan’s court and he continued Kalhaṇa’s Rājataraṅgiṇī. The gap in the narrative of the rulers of the land in the epic poem highlights the political and cultural transformations that have swept through the valley. Śrīvara’sŚrīvara anthology, SubhāṣitāvalīSubhāṣitāvalī, enlists more than 350 poets of the land, and Pollock (2001:397) asserts that even though the large number of poets enlisted can be construed to indicate that the period since 1140 did indeed produce several works in the language, the anthology does not produce any proof that works of significance were created.

Pollock then inquires into the reasons for such rupture in the creative output from the literary scene of Kashmir. He mentions that works could have been lost in the various calamities that befell the land, including frequent fires in the capital. He touches very briefly on the Mongol invasion of 1320, but makes no note at all of the remarkable transformations that took place in the social, religious and cultural fabric of the land during the reigns of Sultan Zain-ul-'abidin’sZain-ul-"'abidin predecessors, especially Sikander Shāh MīrSikandar Shāh Mīr (“Butshikhan”) (ref. Kaw 2004:108), who went on a spree of destroying idols, temples and Hindu culturetemple!destruction of in every village of the valley, as documented by JonarājaJonarāja in RājataraṅgiṇīRājataraṅgiṇī!(Jonarāja) as well. He points out that, even though Kashmir had faced a similar breakdown during the late ninth century, it was able to recover and bounce back to produce some of the finest works in the language through AbhinavaguptaAbhinavagupta, KuntakaKuntaka and MahimabhaṭṭaMahimabhaṭṭa But, he believes the twelfth century is different as the deterioration could never be reversed. Very briefly admitting that “the possibility exists that this picture of literary collapse is an artifact of our data,” (Pollock 2001:397) and that, the loss of works in the various calamities that befell the state could paint a different picture, Pollock sets it aside to present his interpretation of the decline. One thus clearly observes a pattern of the author to mention in passing probable causes for the decline but peremptorily dismisses all of them except the one he chooses to focus upon.

Pollock cites particular references from Kalhaṇa’sKalhaṇa RājataraṅgiṇīRājataraṅgiṇī!(Kalhaṇa) of the excesses and debauchery of the Hindu kings, especially King HarṣaHarṣa and holds them responsible for creating a scenario where culture degenerated. “It is a direct consequence of this, one has to assume, that for poets like Maṅkha political powerpower!political had not only become irrelevant to their lives as creative artists and to the themes of their poetry but an impediment,” (Pollock 2001:399). At this juncture, one must wonder why Pollock conveniently leaves out the patronagepatronage given by Harṣa’sHarṣa predecessors in the Lohara dynastyLohara dynasty to Sanskrit. 1286 is a significant year in the history of the land as complete anarchy broke out during the time. The attack by Rinchana, the Tibetan ruler who plundered the capital SrinagarSrinagar, the calamity that befell the whole land as well as the decisive victories of the TurksTurks over the Hindus, all occurring during the thirteenth century and the first three decades of the fourteenth century find no account in Pollock’s work. Having ignored these momentous changes as critical causes for the breakdown of socio-political structures in the place, and only mentioning the later invasion of 1320 in a single line, Pollock states, “But none of these possibilities seem very likely.” This is a highly contentious statement from the author. On the one hand, he ignores the most savage and formidable challenges Hindu culture as a whole faced during the Islamic invasionIslamic invasion in KashmirKashmir, and on the other, he emphatically places the blame on the “breakdown of the courtly-civic ethos of Kashmir” during the rule of the Hindu kings.

The stark contrast in the manner in which Pollock absolves the Turkish kings of any responsibility for the blows faced by Sanskrit literary culture is illustrated through the manner in which he condones Sultan Zain-ul-'abidin’s destruction of the idol of Goddess ŚāradāGoddess Śāradā, destruction of the idol of. Pollock’s double standardsdouble standards and duplicity in calling the Sultan a “pious devotee”, and describing the act of destruction as something the goddess made him do, “the goddess ‘made him smash to pieces her very own image’” is very revealing of Pollock’s methodsPollock!methods of analysis where he casts no light at all on any observation, or even the historical evidence that challenges and counters his tenuously built analysis.

Further highlighting his case, Pollock maintains that Sanskrit literature historically propagated out of Kashmir and the lack of any such spread post twelfth century is seen as validation of his argument that the language had significantly declined in quality and quantity during the period. Pollock points out that the very nature of the works is one of “culture reduced to reinscription and restatement”. Originality in any of the major branches of literature has disappeared but, continued secondary productions demonstrate the unbroken work carried out in the language. Thus, Pollock states that, as what was lost during the period was the more principal element of creating original work in literature, Sanskrit has disappeared from its once hallowed seat, viz. Kashmir. He does not mention even in passing the revival of the language in 1857 under the reign of Raṇavīra SinghRaṇavīra Singh, who is said to have commissioned more than 30 works in all genres of SanskritSanskrit!revival of literature. The king’s courtly poets including Pandit Sahibram, ViśveśvaraSahibram, Viśveśvara generated great keenness for the language once again in the valley (MajumdarMajumdar, R C 2001a:165) and this finds no account in Pollock’s work.

2 ‘Sanskrit in the City of Victory and Knowledge’

If the first case had at its heart the role played by the breakdown of the “courtly-civic ethos” and the “debauchery of the Hindu kings”, the second case has at its crux the “complicated politics of literary language and far sharper competition among literary cultures” in Vijayanagara (Pollock 2001:400), one of the greatest empires ever built in southern India. In holding the rise of the vernaculars responsible for the decline in Sanskrit, Pollock brings a dubious critical eye to the multilingual nature of life in the empire. In spite of KṛṣṇadevarāyaKṛṣṇadevarāya being a KannadaKannada king, Pollock argues that he did little to champion KannadaKannada at the court. TimmaṇṇaTimmaṇṇa(kavi) was the only court poet of the language while the Dāsa traditionDāsa tradition flourished in the empire. Sanskrit in the state saw no new creations but then, Pollock admits that scholarship in the language reached its zenith during the period. The governors of the state too were very well versed in the language and were learned men but, of “only reproductive and not original learning,” he states. As J Hanneder analyses in his response ‘On “The Death of Sanskrit” to Pollock’s paper, “to state this of scholars like VidyāraṇyaVidyāraṇya and SāyaṇaSāyaṇa who were crucial figures in establishing through their literary activities what came to be considered the fundamental canon of Hindu religious tenets is totally unconvincing.” (Hanneder 2002:307)

In a further analysis, especially in literature that was produced in Vijayanagara, Pollock laments that the quality of kāvya written was poor and wonders how and why the works from the court survived at all (Pollock 2001:401), after the empire was destroyed in 1565. He believes that the dynamism and spirit seen in the works of KannadaKannada and TeluguTelugu are absent in Sanskrit. Thus, in this multilingual empire, he believes Kannada was poorly represented in the court, Sanskrit was only used for State purposes and TeluguTelugu was the main medium in which even KṛṣṇadevarāyaKṛṣṇadevarāya composed. Using words such as “conflict” and “competition” between the vernaculars on the one hand and Sanskrit on the other, Pollock seems inclined to build for the reader an image that perpetuates a sharp dichotomy between the two. The scenario - where the vernaculars and Sanskrit thrived, and creative energiescreative energies flowed mutually between them as against a fight for powerpower!political -is not given even a slight consideration by the author, thus bringing his motives under scrutiny.

Selecting JāmbavatīpariṇayaJāmbavatīpariṇaya, King Kṛṣṇadevarāya’sKṛṣṇadevarāya work written in Sanskrit, he reviews the work as one whose theme has been written about before historically with no novel element in the effort and that the significance of the work is more because of its association with the king and the “political narrative of the Vijayanagara Empire”. Despite kāvya not being a genre in which personal expression has been a characteristic feature of the language, Pollock holds JāmbavatīpariṇayaJāmbavatīpariṇaya to a different standard of judgment. The defeat of the Orissa king GajapatiGajapati (King) to KṛṣṇadevarāyaKṛṣṇadevarāya and the spread of the empire until the Bay of Bengal on the east and the jubilation that followed this victory are seen as finding expression through the work JāmbavatīpariṇayaJāmbavatīpariṇaya. Thus, the work is not a true reflection of the prominent and creatively active role played by Sanskrit in state but is dismissed as a body that is only politically significant. Most of the work of this period in Sanskrit is an expression of the “mytho-political representation of the king’s person” and of the nature of “imperial documents”. Having ignored stotra-s and religious works as significant examples of literary activity earlier in the essay, Pollock now points out that the vernaculars were more active in propagating religious sentiments in Vijayanagara and Sanskrit was only reserved for official state purposes. Thus, it is not the absence of works in Sanskrit that establish its decline during the period but, the nature of the works that Pollock questions, using standards that are arbitrary.

3 The Last Sanskrit Poet

Pollock’s third section, The Last Sanskrit Poet, considers three remarkable figures – Jagannātha PaṇḍitarājaJagannātha, Paṇḍitarāja, the Jain poet SiddhicandraSiddhicandra and KavīndrācāryaKavīndrācārya Sarasvatī. Hailing Jagannātha as the last poet to have attained canonical status in the legion of kavi-s, Pollock laments that one does not have literary information about the life of the poet despite his period of existence being closer to our present time. He then goes on to make the startling inference that this is because “the cosmopolitan space occupied by Sanskrit literaturestotra literature for much of the two preceding millennia persisted well into the seventeenth century despite what are represented as fundamental changes in the political environment with the coming of the Mughals in the previous century,” (Pollock 2001:404). Repeatedly, one finds Pollock’s methodPollock!methods - of dismissing the negative impact of the Islamic invasionsIslamic invasion on the creation, preservation and restoration of the Sanskrit language in India – as a characteristic attribute of his work.

The manner in which Jagannātha’s BhāminīvilāsaBhāminīvilāsa and Rasagaṅgādhara Rasagaṅgādhara achieved massively widespread dissemination is never seen again in the history of the land, and his RasagaṅgādharaRasagaṅgādhara remains among the finest literary treatises in the language. Briefly describing Jagannātha’s personal story - as a Brahmin born into an orthodox Telugu family, who fell in love with a Muslim womanMuslim!woman, and died by drowning in the Gaṅgā - Pollock then moves onto the study of the Navya ageNavya age. The departure from the prācya styleprācya brought with it a novel approach and tone and methods of analysis into the language. Along with Jagannātha, some of the extraordinary exponents of this movement include Bhaṭṭoji DīkṣitaBhaṭṭoji Dīkṣita, the author of Siddhāntakaumidī, Nīlakaṇṭha CaturdharaNīlakaṇṭha Caturdhara, SiddhicandraSiddhicandra the Jain poet, and KavīndrācāryaKavīndrācārya Sarasvatī.

Analysing Siddhicandra’sSiddhicandra time and place in the Mughal court, Pollock presents Abul FazalAbul Fazal and AkbarAkbar himself as men who provided patronagepatronage to SiddhicandraSiddhicandra and in the process, played significant roles in his life. SiddhicandraSiddhicandra had learnt PersianPersian, and the period saw many Sanskrit works translated into Persian, while Sanskrit too was influenced by the Mughal language of the State. While he combined impressive learning in both languages, Pollock believes that the quality of his work is mediocre, and does not embody and express the transformative events of the age. Discussing Siddhicandra’sSiddhicandra debates with the Mughal emperor JahangirJahangir and empress Nūr Mahal, Pollock speaks about how SiddhicandraSiddhicandra was pressurised to give up his celibacy and marry, yet the poet stood resolute in his position, even at the threat of exile; Pollock suggests that this is a pointer to the idea that the prevailing literary and social idea was that “all innovation should be in service of the oldest of Jain monastic ideals,” (Pollock 2001:407). Siddhicandra’sSiddhicandra work and self identification as a navyanavya kavi are thus indications of how the very nature of scholarship in Sanskrit has changed; and Pollock interprets this as a definitive end of the prācyaprācya.

Considering Kavīndra Sarasvatī’s life and work next, Pollock expounds that the massive transformations that swept through the society failed to mark the poet’s work. Highlighting that Kavīndra’s major achievement was the abolition of the jizya taxjizya that was imposed on Hindus during the Mughal rule, Pollock states that the work of the poet remained conventional, and bore no marks of innovation or creativity. Again dismissing the work done in the genre of hymns and restating of older problems in newer language, Pollock makes a sweepingly damning statement: “What Sanskrit learning in the seventeenth century prepared one to do, one might infer from the works of Siddhicandra and Kavīndrācārya, was to resist all other learning,” (Pollock 2001:408). Pollock reduces all the transformations taking place in the language - including his own admission in the earlier part of the essay viz. that this period corresponded with some of the most innovative departures that took place in Sanskrit - to the statement that the outcome of the literary era is an inert unresponsiveness and resistance. This is indeed a very dismissive and contemptuous position Pollock elects to take.

Returning to comparisons with Jagannātha, Pollock searches for information about the Sanskrit culture of the age in Jagannātha’s personal life, and concludes that part of this culture is “the historical fact of a literary representation linking the greatest Sanskrit poet of the age with a Muslim womanMuslim!woman,” (Pollock 2001:409). The themes Jagannātha explores, such as the death of his wife and child, and the tone of his personal reference - are all shown as features of the navya tradition. Pollock’s mode of analysis is not only questionable but his conclusions and inferences in each of these instances of study are labored and factitious. Thus, the highlight of the literary analysis of Sanskrit in the seventeenth century that Pollock makes, pivots on the role played by Jagannātha’s marriage to a Muslim woman. It is indeed startling that this is the conclusion the acclaimed Indologist makes.

4 ‘Under the Shadow of The Raj’

Pollock begins the last case by recounting the surveys commissioned during the British RājBritish Rāj, of the state of Sanskrit learning in the Bengal and Madras presidencies. Despite Pollock’s insistence that Sanskrit as a language had lost the vital force to spread and survive, he admits that the surveys provided information to the contrary picture. Discussing the statistics from the ‘Third Report’, the survey commissioned by William AdamAdam, William in the 1830s in five districts in the Bengal presidency, one finds that there were 353 Sanskrit schoolsSanskrit!schools with over 2500 students in them. He points out that most of the students in the schools belonged to the Brahman community while half the students in the Muslim schools of Burdwan district were non-Muslims, with the Brahmins forming one third of this population. Pollock notes that, “The vast majority of Sanskrit students were engaged in the study of grammar, logic or law. Other subjects, among them literature, figure far less prominently,” (Pollock 2001:412).

Admitting though, that this does not imply the absence of creation of new literature in Sanskrit, Pollock mentions that, in fact, new works were being produced in Bengal even in 1830s. One is sure to find this true across the country, with R C MajumdarMajumdar, R C writing about the numerous works that were being created throughout the nation (Majumdar 2001b:960-967). But the standards and quality of the creations were, maintains Pollock, poor and constitute “literary atrophy”. While other knowledge systems of Sanskrit, such as logic, continued to thrive with the creation of remarkable material, Pollock also states that the spread of the new creations across the country demonstrates the strength and vitality of the disseminating systems. But, as literary textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) weren’t a highlight of this distribution, and school syllabi carried in it outdated works, Pollock hastily concludes that, “That the literary textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) were no longer inserted into this distributive network – and they were not – must be due to the fact that they did not merit insertion in the eyes of the Sanskrit readers themselves,” (Pollock 2001:413).

Socio-political factors such as the termination of the zamindāri system and cessation of the patronagepatronage, cessation of extended to pundits are, maintains Pollock, not the main cause of this decline in literary output. Across various genres of Sanskrit, excepting literature, scholarly inventions and accomplishments continued, however, to pour new life into the language, especially in various courts of the Hindu kings. The Maratha court of TanjoreTanjoreMaratha court of Tanjore, the courts of Krishnaraja WodeyarWodeyar!Krishnaraja in MysoreMysore, and Jai Singh IIJai Singh II in JaipurJaipur provided patronagepatronage for the development of the language, and this resulted in a capacious and extensive production of analytical textstexts (Sanskrit/Indic) and newer commentaries on older topics. “But, how did the Sanskrit literary imagination react to all this? It simply did not,” concludes Pollock.

Numerous newer and interesting works came up during the period : works such as those of Rāghava Āpa KhanḍekarKhanḍekar, Rāghava Āpa in Maharashtra who wrote a lexicon KośāvataṁsaKośāvataṁsa, a book on astronomy KheṭakṛtiKheṭakṛti and the literary work KṛṣṇavilāsaKṛṣṇavilāsa; other writers such as Achyutarāya ModakModak, Achyutarāya, GaṅgādharaGaṅgādhara of Nagpur; writers from the Kashmir seat of learning such as ŚivaśaṅkaraŚivaśaṅkara (Kashmiri writer), VāsudevaVāsudeva (Kashmiri scholar), GaneśaGaneśa and Lāla PaṇḍitaLāla Paṇḍita; and writers from the southern regions such as Rāmasvāmi ŚāstriRāmasvāmi Śāstri and Sundara Rāja; all these and more importantly, he ignores the changing trends that found their expression through the publication of short stories and journals through the influence of Western style, and goes on to state, “In terms of both the subjects considered acceptable and the audience it was prepared to address, Sanskrit had chosen to make itself irrelevant to the new world.” One wonders why the critic is so determined to set aside any evidence that is contrary to his position.

Taking the example of Ishwar Chandra VidyasagarIshwar Chandra Vidyasagar, Pollock (2001:414) asserts, “Sanskrit intellectuals seemed able to respond, or were interested in responding, only to a challenge made on their own terrain – that is, in Sanskrit.” Furthermore, “Sanskrit had ceased to function as the vehicle for living thought, thought that supplemented and not simply duplicated reality.” (2001:414). If this is indeed the state of affairs in the country, as suggested by Pollock, one must question how a song like Vande MātaramVande Mātaram - written in simple Sanskrit with a sprinkling of Bengali words, as a part of ĀnandmaṭhĀnandmaṭh by Bankim Chandra ChaṭṭopādhyayChatterji, Bankim ChandraChaṭṭopādhyay, Bankim Chandra see Chatterji, Bankim Chandra - spread throughout the length and breadth of the nation, and indeed became a call for galvanizing energy during the Swadeshi movementSwadeshi movement; it was as well a call for fight for freedom, calling upon the people to take up the fight, the ones who had been oppressed by centuries of economic, political and social bondage. It was among the very first attempts at forging an identity of Motherland; and in the process, the song has given an entire people a timeless conception of one’s nation as a living force, and in a language they have seen as the mother of all their native languages.

In this context, as Pollock sounds the death-knell for SanskritSanskrit!death-knell for, during this latest period in his analysis, one feels Hanneder’s statement (Hanneder 2002:308) holds true:

“It would be possible to add instances, where Pollock has interpreted the evidence to fit his thesis without considering other options. But let us briefly mention two examples of, if one wishes, innovations: The first is the development of a particular brand of Campū from tenth century onwards. The other is the recent adaptation in Sanskrit literature of new genres like that of the modern short story. One, in my view, particularly impressive synthesis of classical Sanskrit style and the modern social – critical short story is found in Kṣamā Rao’sRao, Kṣamā works. It would not be surprising to find more of this sort in the Sanskrit literature of 19th and 20th century. One should also not forget that the transformation of the Sanskrit Pandits who came in contact with or were under the influence of the British education system in India, are not examples for the power of ‘Sanskritic culture’ to adapt and interact with modernity; this innovation was even a necessary condition for the emergence of IndologyIndology!emergence of itself.”

Pollock goes on to suggest “Perhaps those who are not inheritors of a two-thousand year long tradition cannot possibly know its weight – the weight of all the generations of the dead who remain contemporary and exigent” (2001:414). Firstly, the tradition is much older than the two thousand years that Pollock mentions. Secondly, it appears that Pollock is responding to William Adam, who conducted the survey in Bengal presidency in 1830, as a man who loves the language, but having made such a biasedbias case for declaring Sanskrit dead, Pollock now takes the stand of a duplicitously benevolent critic. Criticizing Adams is certainly pointless, for it would amount to breaking a butterfly on a wheel but Pollock makes the truest statement of the essay in responding to the former –

“The love and care of language (‘complicated alliterations’), the vast and enchanting Borgesian library of narratives (‘absurd fictions’), the profound reflections on human destiny (‘metaphysical abstractions’) are central values marking Sanskrittexts (Sanskrit/Indic) literature from its beginning, and a source of incomparable pleasure and sustenance to those with cultural training to appreciate them.” Pollock (2001:414)

Pollock then sets the stage for his conclusion with trying to understand “when and why this repertory became a practice of repetition and not renewal; when and why what had always been another absolutely central value of the tradition – the ability to make literary newnessliterary!newness, or as a tenth century writer put it, ‘the capacity continually to reimagine the world’ was lost to Sanskrit forever.” (2001:414).

Conclusion

Pollock is only right when he states “It is no straightforward manner to configure these four moments of Sanskrit literary culture into a single, plausible historical narrative.” (2001:414). The reason for this difficulty is that there is no naturally connecting threadconnecting thread that runs between them; and Pollock is trying to laboriously and synthetically create a case for the death of the entire Sanskrit language by highlighting disconnected moments in the genre of literary activity alone in a perpetually changing scenario over a millennium of India. He asserts his particulars, often “anecdotal factoidsanecdotal factoids,” as Rajiv MalhotraMalhotra, Rajiv rightly calls them, and sometimes outright untrue statements, in such an assertive manner even while consciously ignoring evidence contrary to his claims. Thus,

“in Kashmir after the thirteenth century, Sanskrit literature ceased almost entirely to be produced; in Vijayanagara, not a single Sanskrit literary work entered into transregional circulation, an achievement that signaled excellence in earlier periods; in seventeenth century Delhi, remarkable innovations found no continuation, leaving nineteenth century Sanskrit literary culture utterly unable to perpetuate itself into modernity.” Pollock (2001:414)

Pollock goes on to compare Sanskrit with GreekGreek and LatinLatin - two cultures which apparently have shared the same fate as Sanskrit. GreekGreek literary activity met an end when the Academy was shut down in 529 CE; and received its final blow when ConstantinopleConstantinople fell to the Turks in 1453 CE. Comparing Sanskrit with GreekGreek is not only unfair and unreasonable, one wonders what other similarity the two languages have, apart from their classicism. With Pollock’s own examples, one can witness the resilience and indomitabilitySanskrit!resilience and indomitability of the Sanskrit language - to have withstood shocks, assault, negligence and attempts to actively destroy it over a millennium; and what is more, it continues to survive and rediscover itself even in our own day and age.

In comparison with Latin,Latin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) Pollock (2001:415) considers the later period of the language and says “Both died slowly, and earliest as a vehicle of literary expression.” “Politics of translocal aspiration” have ‘forced’ attempts at renewal, he says, brushing into this ‘forced attempts’ all the remarkable literary work that was carried out in the courts of the PeshwasPeshwas and the WodeyarsWodeyars in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. “Both came to be ever more exclusively associated with narrow forms of religion and priestcraft, despite centuries of a secular aesthetic.” (2001:415). While Pollock associates this insular characteristic to the language, one is reminded of recent efforts to study Sanskrit even by scientists at NASANASA for its grammatical structure and the manner in which it lends itself naturally to artificial intelligence (see BriggsBriggs, Rick 1985). It is also important to consider here the words of J HannederHanneder (2002:309) in his paper responding to Pollock on the matter,

“Perhaps the parallel with the decline of LatinLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) leads him to take the production of religious literature as less indicative of an alive Sanskrit culture, while the religious Stotrastotra literature is for this reason not a valid genre for him! Whether literary theoryliterary!theory is really that important for the creativity of a language remains doubtful. It is a mode of reflection attesting an intellectually sophisticated climate, but it could also be argued that the state of discussion in Alaṃkāraśāstra did not call for another 1000 years of revolutionary theories. And I imagine that not only Sanskrit poets would have protested against the notion that the real indicators of intellectual activity are the professional critic and the professor of literature, rather than the poet.”

Pollock then mentions the differences between the two languages viz. Sanskrit and Latin,Latin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) with the first being the role of communicative expertise that has been a part of Sanskritic culture throughout its history until the time of the British, when MacaulayMacaulay, T B famously introduced his system of education (see MacaulayMacaulay, T B 1835) with the explicit aim of ending learning and communication in Sanskrit. While both Europe and India have seen vernacularisationvernacularisation over the last millennium, the two situations differ in their nature. Pollock acknowledges that “the intellectuals who promoted the transformation, certainly in its most consequential phases, were themselves learned in Sanskrit”, and this, as against the situation with Latin in Europe. His assessment that those who could read vernacular poetry in India were also well versed in Sanskrit is valid and true.

In his search for the causes of the “death” of Sanskrit, Pollock emphatically sets aside, without any consideration of unbiased evidence, any impact by the Islamic invasionIslamic invasion on the state of the language. He maintains, “The evidence adduced here shows this to be historically untenable,” (Pollock 2001:416), and has presented carefully selected instances that support his claim, while consciously discounting the works of so many writers who have written contrary to it. He further continues, “It was not ‘alien rule unsympathetic to kāvya’ and a ‘desperate struggle with barbarous invaders’invaders that sapped the strength of Sanskrit literature. In fact, it was often the barbarous invader who sought to revive Sanskrit.” (2001:416). It becomes impossible to attach credibility to Pollock’s conclusions when one reads accounts of the manner in which the culture of the land, with its unparalleled structures of learning including its vast libraries,libraries, destruction of was massacred under the invasions of Muhammed GhazniGhazni, Mahmud (Muhammed), Muhammed GhoriGhuri, Mahmud (Muhammed), and their cultural successors until AurangzebAurangzeb four centuries ago. This is not to forget that there were stray instances of Muslim rulersMuslim!rulers who have attempted to bring peace and tolerance to the land – AkbarAkbar and Dara ShikohDara Shikoh readily come to one’s mind – but glossing over a whole major part of one’s cultural history and absolving Islamic ruleIslamic rule of any responsibility of adversely impacting Sanskrit is outright willful misrepresentationmisinterpretation,!techniques of,!willful misrepresentation.

Probing further with his coloured glassescoloured glasses into the reasons for the “death” of Sanskrit, Pollock enlists three major causes. The first of these is the “internal debilitation of the politicalpower!political institutionsinstitutions!political that had previously underwritten Sanskrit, pre-eminently the court.” (2001:416). The second is the “heightened competition among a new range of languages.” (2001:416). While comparing the two cultures of Latin and Sanskrit,Latin!and SanskritLatin!(Vulgar, Medieval, Church) Pollock was right in maintaining that those who encouraged the spread of the vernacular in India were themselves well versed with Sanskrit. But now, he feels that the increasing usage of the vernaculars throughout the country seemed to have adversely affected Sanskrit. He cites the example of the court of Vijayanagara to support his case once again. One can easily recount the vernacular poets Keśavdās and BihārīlālBihārīlāl but not any Sanskrit poet, maintains Pollock. By describing Sanskrit as “the idiom of a cosmopolitan literature,” Pollock attempts to present a nonexistent dividenonexistent divide between the Vernaculars and Sanskrit. India has always been a land of multiplicity; and having both the vernaculars and Sanskrit existing simultaneously, with constant flow of ideas and energies between the two - is an unacceptable scenario to Pollock.

The third cause for the ‘death’ is the dramatic erosion of “the civic ethos embodied in the court.” Pollock again repeats his assertion that the ethos “had more or less fully succumbed by the thirteenth century, long before consolidation of the Turkish power in the Valley.” (2001:416). One certainly hopes that a lie repeated a thousand times does not become truth. Pointing out that Sanskrit had no establishments and structures to help it adapt, disseminate and percolate the changes more intensely into the social fabric of the land, Pollock believes that the traditional networks and collective efforts went into fighting limited and temporary goals. Once again, this position of Pollock seems conflicting with the idea expressed by many historians and critics that there was, indeed, a proliferation of publishing material towards the later parts of the nineteenth and twentieth centuries with the introduction of the printing press to India.

Pollock admits, no doubt, that newer works and invaluable critiques and interpretations did indeed develop during the VijayanagaraVijayanagara period and later; but then, in his conclusion, he believes that the impact of the Navya phase was insignificant as it was “a newness of style without a newness of substance.” Pollock betrays the fault in his reasoning, with his arbitrary selectionarbitrary selection of examples and illustrations, and further limiting to only the genre of kāvyakāvya on the one hand to the sweeping, overreaching generalizationsoverreaching generalizations he makes for the entire language from these examples, on the other. He limits his survey while making specific points but makes the following statements for the entire field – “No idiom was developed in which to articulate a new relationship to the past, let alone a critique; no new forms of knowledge – no new theory of religious identity, for example, let alone of the political – were produced in which the changed conditions of political and religious life could be conceptualized.” (2001:417).

Pollock ends his essay with a further belabouring of the same statement - “At all events, the fact remains that well before the consolidation of colonialismcolonialism, before even the establishment of the Islamicate political order, the mastery of tradition had become an end it itself for Sanskrit literary culture, and reproduction, rather than revitalization, the overriding concern.” (2001:418).

The analysis Rajiv MalhotraMalhotra, Rajiv has performed of this particular theme of Pollock’s work in his book The Battle for SanskritBattle for Sanskrit, The (2016) has been invaluable for its preciseness and clarity. The systematic compilation of all the attempts that have been made over the last millennium to end any attempts to reinvigorate Sanskrit language as well as the focused rebuttals given to Pollock’s essay set a sound and apposite platform for pūrva-pakṣapūrva-pakṣa. The significance of Pollock’s workPollock!work, significance of lies in the stirring it has provided and the clarion call it has given in urging Indians to once again take up the stewardship of the creation and organisation of their cultural instruments. In heeding to the call and rising to the challenge alone would one find a commensurate response to ‘The Death of Sanskrit’.

Bibliography

Briggs, Rick (1985) “Knowledge Representation in Sanskrit and Artificial Intelligence”. AI Magazine, Vol. 6, No. 1, pp. 32–39
Hanneder, J (2002). “On The Death of Sanskrit”. Indo-Iranian Journal. 45. pp. 293–310.
Kaw, M. K. (2004). Kashmir Education, Culture, and Science Society - Kashmir and Its People: Studies in the Evolution of Kashmiri Society. A.P.H. Publishing Corporation. Jammu and Kashmir.
Macaulay, T. B. (1835). Minute on Education.
Majumdar, R.C. (Ed.) (2001a) The Struggle for Empire. Vol. 5. 5th Edition. Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan.
Majumdar, R.C (Ed.) (2001b) The Struggle for Freedom. Vol. 7, 5th Edition. Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan
Malhotra, Rajiv (2016) The Battle for Sanskrit. Harper Collins. New Delhi.
Pollock, Sheldon (2001). “Death of Sanskrit”. Comparative Studies in Society and History. Vol. 43. Issue 2. Pp 392–426.
Sri Aurobindo (1997). The Renaissance in India and Other Essays on Indian Culture. The Complete Works of Sri Aurobindo – Volume 20. Sri Aurobindo Ashram Publications Department

Our Key Partners

The organisers of the conference are indebted to the various~institutions and individuals for the invaluable help rendered by them, without which this work would just not have been possible. It is a pleasure to thank them heartily for the same.

We are indebted to our individual and institutional sponsors: Sri Mohandas Pai and Foundation for Indian Civilization Studies, Sri MV Subbiah and Vellayan Chettiar Trust, Sri J K Jhaver, Sri Kiron Shah, Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts (IGNCA), Sri Rakesh Bhandari, and Sri Nagesh Bhandari and Indus University. Without all their financial support and help we would not have been able to attract the high level of scholarship that has contributed to this volume.

We are grateful to IIT-Madras and IGNCA, New Delhi for organizing the Swadeshi Indology Conferences 1 and 2 respectively. In particular, we are thankful to Prof. Devendra Jalihal and his colleagues at IITM, Sri Ram Bahadur Rai, Chairman IGNCA, Sri Sachchidanand Joshi, Member Secretary IGNCA, Sri Aravinda Rao, Smt. Sonal Mansingh and their team at IGNCA. The teams at these institutions put in enormous efforts to make the conferences a success and we owe them a huge debt of gratitude for the same.

Our Contributors

(in alphabetical order of last names)

Naresh Prakash Cuntoor

Dr. Naresh Prakash Cuntoor is a Senior Research Scientist, Intelligent Automation Inc., Rockville, MD, US. He has an M.S. and PhD from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of Maryland. His research interests include human activity recognition, scene understanding, perceptual organization and computer vision for robotics applications. He pursues Sanskrit with keen interest and is a volunteer for Samskrita Bharati USA.

Satyanarayana Das

Satyanarayana Dasa is a BTech from IIT(Delhi) in Mechanical Engineering and MTech from the same institution in Industrial Engineering. After working in this line for a while in Mumbai and then in the US, he gave up that career in favour of a quest for his spiritual roots. He took up Sanskrit studies and studied the entire literature of the Gauḍīya Vaiṣṇava tradition under the tutelage of Guru Haridasa Shastri Maharaj and completed his PhD in Sanskrit from Agra University. Dr. Dasa is the founder of the Jiva Institute of Vedic Studies in Vrindavan.

Koenraad Elst

Dr. Elst is a scholar of Philosophy, Chinese and Indo-Iranian Studies and is well-known for this several books and articles on various India-centric issues such as the Ayodhya Ramjanmabhoomi issue and the Aryan question as well as those reflecting a deep study of Nazism amongst other things. Amongst the books he has penned are The Saffron Swastika, Ayodhya and After: Issues before Hindu Society, Negationism in India – Concealing the Record of Islam and Psychology of Prophetism – a Secular look at the Bible.

K Gopinath

Prof. Gopinath is currently employed as Professor at the Indian Institute of Science in Bangalore in the Computer Science and Automation Department. He has a doctorate from Stanford, Master’s from UW Madison, BTech from IITM and has worked at AMD and Sun Microsystems Labs.

K S Kannan

Prof. K S Kannan is a Visiting Professor at the Centre for Ancient History and Culture, Jain University, Bengaluru, and is the Academic Director of the Swadeshi Indology Conference Series. He is a Former Director, Karnataka Sanskrit University and has a PhD in Sanskrit. His pursuits include research into Sanskrit literature and Indian Philosophy, and he is the author of about 20 books, prominent among them being Theoretical Foundations of Āyurveda published by FRLHT, Bengaluru in 2007 and Virūpākṣa Vasantotsava Campū, Annotated Edition, published by Kannada Vishvavidyalaya, Hampi, Karnataka in 2001. He is also the co-translator of Vibhinnate, the translation into Kannada (2016), of the seminal work in English Being Different written by Rajiv Malhotra.

Jayaraman Mahadevan

Dr. Jayaraman Mahadevan is currently serving as Director, Research Department, Krishnamacharya Yoga Mandiram, Chennai, Scientific Industrial Research Organisation. He has a PhD in Sanskrit from the Department of Sanskrit, University of Madras, His thesis was titled The Doctrine of Tantrayukti – A Study. He has presented 20 papers in various National and International conferences and has given talks in universities, colleges and institutions of national eminence. He has also written books, organised seminars, funded projects and been the guide for students pursuing their PhD. His areas of interest are Yoga, Tantrayukti, Vedanta, Sanskrit Poetic Literature and Manuscript Studies.

H R Meera

H R Meera is an engineer graduate with BE degree from BMS College of Engineering, Bangalore. After serving as a consultant and software engineer for several years, she yearned to connect to her roots and pursued study of Sanskrit, procuring an MA. She is currently doing her PhD in interdisciplinary work at the National Institute of Advanced Studies, Bangalore. She is the co-translator of Vibhinnate, the Kannada translation of Rajiv Malhotra’s Being Different.

Ashay Deepak Naik

Ashay Naik is a software developer at Matific Ltd. and has just released his first book Natural Enmity: Reflections on the Niti and Rasa of the Panchatantra [Book 1]. He has a Masters in Information Technology from the Queensland University of Technology, Australia and an Honours in Sanskrit from the University of Sydney, Australia.

Manogna H Sastry

Manogna H Sastry is Chief Operations Officer as well as Mentor and Research Associate at the Centre for Fundamental Research and Creative Education, Bengaluru http://www.cfrce.com/manognahshastry.htm. Manogna has an M.S. from the Indian Institute of Astrophysics, Bengaluru, where her thesis was on Inflationary Cosmology. She is a keen student of Sanskrit literature and Indic studies, a passionate environmentalist and gardener.

Series Editorial

It is a tragedy that many among even the conscientious Hindu scholars of Sanskrit and Hinduism still harp on Macaulay, and ignore others while accounting for the ills of the current Indian education system, and the consequent erosion of Hindu values in the Indian psyche. Of course, the machinating Macaulay brazenly declared that a single shelf of a good European library was worth the whole native literature of India, and sought accordingly to create “a class of persons, Indian in blood and colour, but English in taste, in opinions, in morals and in intellect” by means of his education system - which the system did achieve.

An important example of what is being ignored by most Indian scholars is the current American Orientalism. They have failed to counter it on any significant scale.

It was Edward Said (1935-2003) an American professor at Columbia University who called the bluff of “the European interest in studying Eastern culture and civilization” (in his book Orientalism (1978)) by showing it to be an inherently political interest; he laid bare the subtile, hence virulent, Eurocentric prejudice aimed at twin ends – one, justifying the European colonial aspirations and two, insidiously endeavouring to distort and delude the intellectual objectivity of even those who could be deemed to be culturally considerate towards other civilisations. Much earlier, Dr. Ananda Coomaraswamy (1877–1947) had shown the resounding hollowness of the leitmotif of the “White Man’s Burden.”

But it was given to Rajiv Malhotra, a leading public intellectual in America, to expose the Western conspiracy on an unprecedented scale, unearthing the modus operandi behind the unrelenting and unhindered program for nearly two centuries now of the sabotage of our ancient civilisation yet with hardly any note of compunction. One has only to look into Malhotra’s seminal writings - Breaking India (2011), Being Different (2011), Indra’s Net (2014), The Battle for Sanskrit (2016), and The Academic Hinduphobia (2016) - for fuller details.

This pentad - preceded by Invading the Sacred (2007) behind which, too, he was the main driving force - goes to show the intellectual penetration of the West, into even the remotest corners (spatial/temporal/thematic) of our hoary heritage. There is a mixed motive in the latest Occidental enterprise, ostensibly being carried out with “pure academic concerns”. For the American Orientalist doing his “South Asian Studies'' (his new term for “Indology Studies”), Sanskrit is inherently oppressive - especially of Dalits, Muslims and women. And as an “antidote", therefore, the goal of Sanskrit studies henceforth should be, according to him, to “exhume and exorcise the barbarism'' of social hierarchies and oppression of women happening ever since the inception of Sanskrit - which language itself came, rather, from outside India. Another important agenda is to infuse/intensify animosities between/among votaries of Sanskrit and votaries of vernacular languages in india. A significant instrument towards this end is to influence mainstream media so that the populace is constantly fed ideas inimical to the Hindu heritage. The tools being deployed for this are the trained army of “intellectuals” - of leftist leanings and “secular” credentials.

Infinity Foundation (IF), the brainchild of Rajiv Malhotra, started 25 years ago in the US, spearheaded the movement of unmasking the “catholicity” (- and what a euphemistic word it is!) of Western academia. The profound insights provided by the ideas of “Digestion'' and the “U-Turn Theory” propounded by him remain unparalleled.

It goes without saying that it is ultimately the Hindus in India who ought to be the real caretakers of their own heritage; and with this end in view, Infinity Foundation India (IFI) was started in India in 2016. IFI has been holding a series of Swadeshi Indology Conferences.

Held twice a year on an average, these conferences focus on select themes and even select Indologists of the West (sometimes of even~the East), and seek to offer refutations of mischievous and misleading misreportages/misinterpretations bounteously brought out by these Indologists - by way of either raising red flags at, or giving intellectual responses to, malfeasances inspired in fine by them. To employ Sanskrit terminology, the typical secessionist misrepresentations presented by the West are treated here as pūrva-pakṣa, and our own responses/rebuttals/rectifications as uttara-pakṣa or siddhānta.

The first two conferences focussed on the writings of Prof. Sheldon Pollock, the outstanding American Orientalist (also of Columbia University, ironically) and considered the most formidable and influential scholar of today. There can always be deeper/stronger responses than the ones that have been presented in these two conferences, or more insightful perspectives; future conferences, therefore, could also be open in general to papers on themes of prior conferences.

Vijayadaśamī
Hemalamba Saṃvatsara
Date 30-09-2017

Dr. K S Kannan
Academic Director
General Editor of the Series

Volume Editorial

Infinity Foundation India conducted two conferences in the recent past (in July 2016 and February 2017) which examined the impact of some of the writings of Prof. Sheldon Pollock of Columbia University. While the first conference had four themes, the second had six more; and all these ten topics pertained to the interpretations proffered by Pollock.

While there is no intention of, or point in, targeting particular individuals, the focus on Pollock was due to the fact that he is the most formidable of the American Orientalists today, and his views and interpretations appear to Hindus to be most pernicious, nevertheless most pervasive in influence: a good many contemporary scholars, especially in the West build on his pet ideas.

Pollock is obsessed with the notions of power and politics. As Malhotra points out, the word “power” occurs 600 times in his 2006 book The Language of Gods...; and the words “political” and “politics” occur 900 times! There is no event or utterance, be it the most innocuous, where he cannot see some vicious play of power. Pollock cannot be too proud of this idiosyncrasy, for he has lucid company in Prof. O’Flaherty for whom the most innocent of moves can reek of sexual ramifications. (We promise our readers to reserve a couple of volumes for her too). Eight volumes are being presented now for dealing with the ideas of Pollock: six volumes of around 250 or more pages each and two monographs authored by two young Sanskrit scholars. Of these eight, Volume 1 is being presented now.

A conspectus of the various papers in this volume is quite in order here. This volume presents eight papers in two parts – three on what is perceived by the ilks of Pollock as the diabolical influence that Sanskrit and the Śāstra-s have had, directly or indirectly, on Nazism; and five on the vile theme of the putative death of Sanskrit.

Part 1 of the book is devoted to the treatment of the supposed Sanskrit springs of the Nazi holocaust: the weird and convoluted links Pollock belabours to manufacture between the two stand exposed here.

The first paper authored by K Gopinath (Ch. 1) exposes the propagandist designs evidenced in Pollock’s 1993 paper “Deep Orientalism: Notes on Sanskrit and Power beyond the Raj”. Gopinath's paper shows how Pollock subtly brings in extraneous elements, invokes selective evidence that can suggest his own prefixed conclusions, and employs other devices – all typical protocols of propagandism. Pollock supposes a trans-mogrification of German Indologists into supporters of Nazism, blatantly ignoring all the same, how, for example, famed German physicists and philosophers too vouched for their Nazi sympathies. Gopinath musters evidence from writers such as Grunendahl to show how Pollock is a past master in the suppression of inconvenient facts, and thus proves himself a prevaricator par excellence.

The second paper by Ashay Naik (Ch. 2) makes a pūrva-pakṣa of Pollock’s 2001 paper “Deep Orientalism?”. Pollock endeavours to establish therein a link between German Indology and the notorious Nazi ideology. The Nazis indulged in the worst of horrors, and linking Sanskrit with the Nazis can easily make Sanskrit culpable: is not an abettor a partaker of crime, after all? Naik organises his paper under the four labels of Orientalism viz. the British, the German, the Sanskrit, and the American. Pollock has sought to implicate Sanskrit knowledge as a factor in the development of Nazi ideology. Equipped with pertinent facts and cogent logic, Ashay shows how Pollock’s comparative morphology of domination, for all its polemic, remains untenable.

The third paper by Koenraad Elst (Ch. 3) closely considers the claims of Pollock only to find them “surprisingly weak or simply wrong”; Pollock is not, of course, the first person to exploit the links between racism, Nazism, and the study of Indo-European culture on the one hand, and Sanskrit on the other. The counterpoint viz. Adolf Hitler’s contempt for Hinduism, though well known, is cautiously concealed by Pollock, and blatant lies are made use of so as to subserve his own polemical writings. While there is, of course, a general animus against Hinduism in American academe, Pollock’s deliberate and concocted links between Hinduism and National Socialism suggest “a rare animosity against Hinduism”. Again, Western Indologists spare no efforts to depict the Indian caste-system as slavery and racism, for which they invoke the discredited yet handy AIT (Aryan Invasion Theory), and fantasize a Nazi parallel, notwithstanding the fact that nowhere in the long history of India do we find even a faint hint of genocide in connection with the varṇa system. He who makes public allegations, and cannot prove them, is guilty of slander, which Pollock patently is. The author of the paper asks the rhetorical question, finally, as to whether Pollock is at all fit to be trusted to preside over the publication of Indian classics.

Part 2 of the book is devoted to the projection of the “death” of Sanskrit. The discovery non pareil of Pollock is that Sanskrit has died multiple times, even though it was still-born (his own naive fancy, again!) Fallacies galore of Pollockian polemics are well laid bare here.

The first paper in this part by Naresh Cuntoor (Ch. 4) prepares for us a decoction of Pollock’s concoctions. To sample but three: Sanskrit had a symbiotic relationship with royal power; Sanskrit grammar and śleṣa (paranomasia) enhanced the political status of kings; royal patronage favoured Sanskrit over vernacular language. Extraordinary is Pollock’s sacrifice of empirical data at the altar of his own brand of narrative building. What comes handy as a powerful tool for butchery of facts is the complicated style of writing Pollock meticulously deploys. Unfortunately for Pollock, opacity of diction cannot always shield the deviousness of his designs. Pollock freely posits theories that never once make even a pretense of being at first a hypothesis that may naturally need to be justified. All the accoutrements of posturing are well in place: like a conscientious author, Pollock starts with meticulous and detailed enumeration of various caveats; one however has only to wait to get to the section of his conclusions to realise that all those caveats are thrown into winds unceremoniously. Pollock draws, again, analogies of Sanskrit with the truly dead languages, but only fallaciously.

The second paper is by Satyanarayana Das (Ch. 5). Simply entitled “Sanskrit is not Dead” this paper puts Pollock in the dock by presenting a case study – of the Vraja literature of the 16th-17th centuries - that betrayed, against the wishful thinking of Pollock, the remarkable historical continuity and vitality of Sanskrit. The author shows how Pollock does not provide either statistical evidence, or even proper references for his claims. The only point of note in Pollock’s presentation of a “momentous rupture” (post the “vibrant period'' 1550-1750), is that it is just sensational-in lieu of being really sensible. As against the whimsical claims of Pollock, the paper of Das makes its own argument sound, buttressed with apt statistical evidence.

The third paper by Jayaraman Mahadevan (Ch. 6) deals with the classic inane statement by Pollock viz. “Government feeding tubes and oxygen tanks may try to preserve the language [Sanskrit] in a state of quasi-animation .... Sanskrit is dead”. The paper sets forth pertinent information in abundance from one of the most important documents of the Government of India (which Pollock knows cannot claim ignorance of) viz. the Report of the First Sanskrit Commission constituted by the Government of India in 1956 with Dr. Suniti Kumar Chatterji as its Chairman; Chatterji, by the way, was by no means known for his sympathies with any “Hindutva” philosophy that Pollock is so fidgety about. This was in fact at a time when no “Hindutva force” worth the name was even heard of, much less had been shaping things, and, to speak the truth, it was during the very reign of the government headed by Jawaharlal Nehru, “secularism” incarnate, euphemism for allergy to Hinduism, which called all the shots.

The Report was prepared covering a cross-section of India - (the then) 14 states of India, at 56 centres, and interviewing over 1100 persons – thus representing various shades of opinion. A perusal of the Report shows that the Britishers paid Sanskrit teachers half the salary they paid others, and worse, the hypocritical Nehru Government unabashedly perpetuated it! It was the response from the public – from Maharajas to the ordinary folk including non-Brahmins - that sustained Sanskrit in these adverse times. The paper has ably bleached the p(f)igments of Pollock’s political imagination.

The fourth paper by Kannan and Meera (Ch. 7) scrutinises Pollock’s paper of 2001 on the “Death of Sanskrit”. The paper draws attention to the methodological idiosyncrasies of Pollock that can do no credit to a conscionable author: there is nothing for Pollock, for example, that cannot have a bearing on power. Pollock is aghast that Hindutva propagandists have sought to show – what is an elementary fact, after all – that Sanskrit is indigenous to India. Revival of Sanskrit is to him a mere “exercise in nostalgia”. From the vast canvas of several millennia of the history of Sanskrit, Pollock picks (read cherry-picks) just four tricky points of time - to delineate the degeneration/disappearance of Sanskrit. Pollock indeed “sees things” that few others can: viz. that it is the benign Muslim kings that tried to patronize and protect Sanskrit (and not jettison and jeopardize Sanskrit), while Hindu kings were apathetic towards it! Pollock does not even attempt to camouflage his intense Islamophilia (matched only by his high Hinduphobia) when he makes light of the atrocious burning of libraries in Kashmir as but “fire accidents” – in lieu of speaking of the wanton destruction by the Muslim marauders, which no chronicler has ever made any secret of. Pollock can have few sympathisers even among American Orientalists except, of course, his own intellectual offsprings like Audrey Trushke. The other typical techniques of “List and Dismiss”, “Perhaps...Probably...And therefore”, “divida et impera”, “Selective playing up and playing down”, and the anachronistic and unprincipled superimposition of the frameworks of modern psychology and social science on Indian traditional lore of antiquity, to mention but a few – all illustrative of the contumely of an unchallenged maverick – are tellingly set forth in this paper.

The fifth (and the last) paper by Manogna Sastry (Ch. 8) also deals with Pollock’s “Death of Sanskrit” paper of 2001. Starting with Sri Aurobindo’s note on India’s distinctness from the Occident, Ms. Sastry notes how there is a vast continuum of Western critics – from Sister Nivedita and Romain Rolland, sympathetic and understanding towards the Indian heritage at one end of the spectrum, and, at the other, the pompous and belligerent critics exemplified by Doniger and Pollock. American Orientalism has only spawned a plethora of scholars of the latter type. The facile and puerile assertion of Pollock that Sanskrit is championed just by promoters of Hindutva, is easily repudiated by her by way of citing the numerous independent attempts in support of Sanskrit, of several individuals and organizations that are totally independent of or utterly unaware of the Hindutva movement. And to no small effect has been related by her the research of Hanneder, to show how Pollock is eminently capable of interpreting all evidence to fit just his own pet theses, and by whatever means. Summoning “anecdotal factoids” to suppress key facts staring in the face, or again, reinforcing devious attempts so as to drive a wedge between Sanskrit and vernaculars (which many European Indologists have carefully and consistently cultivated for long) - are all no small feats of Pollock. Very telling are her words towards the conclusion of the paper that the opus of Pollock is not all in vain in that it has actually provided the clarion call to Indians – to resume the stewardship of the creation and organization of their own cultural instruments.

It goes without saying that the opinions expressed in the papers presented here are those of the respective authors. The authors hold themselves responsible for the veracity of their statements.

***

A survey of all the papers above may be said to reveal one important trait of Pollock. While not one paper here doubts or questions the profusion~of Pollock's scholarship, every one without exception has expressed apprehensions about the integrity of Pollock reminding us thus of the subhāṣita – “vyartham pāṇḍityam guṇa-varjitam” (“What avails scholarship, after all, sans integrity?”)!

Vijayadaśamī
Hemalamba Saṃvatsara
Date 30-09-2017

Dr. K S Kannan
Academic Director
General Editor of the Series

Acknowledgements

Our conferences could not have happened without the active support and participation of our volunteers and well-wishers.

We wish to thank Sri Udaykumar and his team from the Vande Mataram Student Circle at IIT-Madras for their help in making full arrangements for the first conference at Chennai. Sri Jithu Aravamudhan and Smt. Lakshmi Sarma of the IFI group of volunteers also deserve our hearty thanks for their active participation. Ms. Ruchi Sood and her team of volunteers as also Smt. Shilpa Memani, Sri Abhishek Jalan, Sri Roushan Rajput and Sri Divyanshu Bawa made no small efforts in making the New Delhi conference a success.

Our gratitude is due to Sri Ramnik Khurana, Sri Sanjeev Chhibber, and Sri Chetan Handa who have kindly offered to bear the expenses of bringing out these volumes in print. We wish to thank Sri Sunil Sheoran who has been a long-time supporter of our work. His help in coordinating the printing of these volumes is deeply appreciated.

We are grateful to all the paper-presenters and the keen audience for maintaining a high academic standard and decorum at the conference. There of course are many more who have helped us and guided us behind the screen and deserve our thanks.

IFI Team

IFI Team